Trump's threats again and dismissed the idea of direct talks. I mean does this
kind of rhetoric from the US president strengthen Iran's position rather than
weaken it? I think if you were sitting in Tehran and you are not sure if President
Trump is playing a game with you or if he's serious about diplomacy this kind
of language probably is going to give him reason more reason to think he's
not serious about diplomacy. Again remember the big context here
President Trump is asking Iran to surrender unconditionally essentially to
give up everything their nukes, their missiles, their proxies, their influence
in the region and opening up the Strait of Hormuz the latest one to be added to
the list of demands. So if you're sitting in Tehran and you then get this
message as they did I'm assuming and that has certainly been what we've
heard from again people like the Speaker of the Iranian Parliament, Qali
Baf and others who are dismissing the message saying I think the word they
used was it was unbalanced, the Adrian. Trump's also talked again about taking
Iran's oil excuse me if there's no deal I mean what does that tell us about US
objectives in this conflict? Yeah I wouldn't read too much into that again
he's sort of talked along these lines before even in other sort of context
again it's more of expression of frustration than to suggest to us that
is a clear path here that the United States with this American president is
getting ready to essentially control Iranian oil and gas. I don't see
anybody sort of talking along those lines obviously this is a conflict that
you know was about the nuclear issue, the missiles, the proxies and now it's
about also the Strait of Hormuz but for the United States to sort of
seriously contemplate controlling Iranian oil that has really never
been on the cards again he is posturing is showing his frustration
more than anything else but it doesn't really change where we are
right now if you are serious about diplomacy what the US president should
to do start perhaps thinking of maybe softening his position demanding the
Iranian side to soften their position in turn and then look for that potential
middle ground where you can have some kind of a ceasefire that you can then
in a best-case scenario build on obviously we're not even close to
scenario like that but that's the that's the only scenario we can
contemplate other than more military escalation.
Good to talk to you again Alex many thanks indeed Alex Vatanka there
in Washington a US Airman that has been rescued in Iran after an intense 48 hour
search operation the weapons systems officer had been missing since Friday
when the fighter jet he was in went down in the province of Okagi
Loya and Boya Ahmad Tehran said it shot down the F-15E of two-seater
aircraft the pilot was rescued shortly afterwards.
It was a daring and risky mission to save an American airman from
becoming an Iranian prisoner of war Iranian forces search the mountainous
areas of southwestern Iran after an F-15E fighter jet went down on Friday
it was the first time a US aircraft had crashed in hostile territory in the
five-week old war two Black Hawk helicopters took
fire as US teams raced to find the missing crew member an A-10 Warthog
an air support aircraft was also damaged its pilot ejecting over the gulf
Iran broadcast photos of what it said was debris from the fighter jet
including a jump seat although the pilot had been rescued on Friday
the weapon specialist remained in hiding evading Iranian forces
for two days finally early on Sunday deep in Iranian territory
the US search operation was successful president Donald Trump made the
announcement on social media posting we got him saying the colonel had
been behind enemy lines in the treacherous mountains of Iran
being hunted by our enemies he said US forces had been
monitoring his location 24 hours a day and sent dozens of aircraft armed
with the most lethal weapons in the world to retrieve him
Trump added he sustained injuries but he will be just fine
a US official told Al Jazeera the rescue operation began in darkness but ended
in an intense firefight and daylight before dozens of heavily armed aircraft
and hundreds of troops transported the airmen out of Iran
a US officer in Iranian custody could have given Iran leverage
as it had when Iran took US hostages in 1979
with that crisis averted attention now shifts to the US deadline for Iran to
open the Strait of Hormuz John Hendron Al Jazeera Washington
well as John reported there the US says the rescue mission involved
central aircraft Iranian state media released these pictures
reportedly showing the wreckage of a C-130 aircraft in Isfahan province
now American media are reporting that US forces destroyed at least
one of their own planes on purpose because it had become stuck and unable to fly
but Iranian armed forces dispute those accounts of events claiming that its soldiers destroyed
two C-130 aircraft and two Black Hawk helicopters in what it characterized as a failed US rescue
operation the so-called rescue operation by the US army framed as a deception
an immediate escape under the pretext of rescuing their downed pilot at an abandoned airport in
southern Isfahan ended in complete failure due to the timely presence of the armed forces
of the Islamic Republic of Iran following prior intelligence further investigations
by experts on the scene revealed that two C-130 military transport aircrafts
and two US army Black Hawk helicopters were destroyed
thanks to the divine promise and assistance from the Almighty God
as well as the righteous fury of the Islamic forces in the powerful armed forces
this action increased the level of continuous failures faced by the US army
Adam Weinstein is a former US Marine and Deputy Director of the Middle East Program
at the Quincy Institute for Responsible Statecraft
he says that the US Airmen would have relied on his military training to stay safe
all pilots go through seer school which is a survival evasion resistance in escape school
so it's where they're trained for this exact scenario so they're trained in techniques to
evade capture escape if they are captured resist if they have to
with their sidearm or whatever else they might get a hold of
and then escape you know devoid detection that's the that's the main goal
and so when he landed he apparently went up a 7 000 foot ridge line of a mountain
to make capture less likely and to make a rescue easier so that a helicopter could
reach him and and take him away and they would have a clear line of sight to wherever
they were extracting him to once you're in a real-world scenario everything that you've been
game planning sort of goes out to the window and you have to improvise I think the skills
that these pilots learn for this situation come come into play almost instinctively
because they've trained so well but remember many of these pilots might be years out of seer school
and they they haven't they're not accustomed to this situation I mean I think the last time
that a plane went down and enemy territory was during the during the Kosovo war
so we've gotten accustomed to about a quarter century of US wars where
we have complete air superiority and that's changing now
let's take a look at what else is making news around the world right now in the Gaza Strip Hamas
says it will not disarm disarmament is part of the second phase of the Gaza ceasefire plan but
the armed group says calls to lay down its weapons are unacceptable especially as Palestinians
continue to be targeted by Israel more than 700 people have been killed since the ceasefire
came into effect in October as for raising the issue of weapons in this crude manner
it is nothing but a scandalous attempt by the occupation to continue killing and genocide
against our people which we will not accept under any circumstances we affirm that what the enemy
was unable to seize from us with tanks and genocide it will not seize from us with politics
or at the negotiation table the occupation's aggression against our people and its continued
closure of the blessed al-Aqsa mosque to worshipers in an unprecedented manner and the approval of the
law for executing Palestinian prisoners we call upon the masses of our Palestinian people in the
brave west bank the blessed Jerusalem and the occupied interior to march toward al-Aqsa mosque
let's speak to Mu'an Rabani managing editor of Jalaliyah and non-resident fellow at the
Middle East Council on Global Affairs he joins us from Montreal good to have you with us
Hamas is now openly saying the disarmament is off the table under any circumstances
how significant is that what does it tell us about where these talks really stand
well it basically confirms that the talks are completely deadlocked for the following
reasons what Hamas informed the mediators is that it will not discuss issues such as disarmament
relating to the second phase of the plan for the Gaza Strip until the items of the first phase
are implemented that includes a cessation of hostilities as you noted virtual daily Israeli
attacks on the Gaza Strip have resulted in more than 700 Palestinians killed humanitarian aid
continues to be restricted and most notably this national committee for the administration
of the Gaza Strip which was established by the board of peace continues to be prohibited from
entering the Gaza Strip by the Israelis and the board of peace is doing absolutely nothing
to ensure its ability to get in and so I think Hamas is taking two positions a it won't discuss
the second phase until the first phase is properly implemented and b when those discussions do
take place it's not going to simply surrender its weapons unless Israel clearly meets its own
obligations as well and those are obligations that have to be consistent not just with what the
board of peace wants but with the international consensus that and the rulings of the international
court of justice that this is an illegal occupation that must end I bought a beta called
these demands extremely dangerous is this a warning to the mediators that the entire ceasefire is at
risk of collapsing well there isn't really a ceasefire if you consider that daily shootings and bombings
during a supposed ceasefire agreement that render that ceasefire null and void it has been the
case that Hamas has thus far refrained from responding to these continuous Israeli attacks
and I suspect that its ability to respond is very limited but what we're also seeing now is that very
similar to Israeli demands with respect to Hezbollah and Lebanon with respect to Iran it seems to be
a consistent Israeli demand that its enemies are not entitled to have any weapons while Israel
had retains the capacity to launch unrestrained attacks for them and I think this is really
a few sift through these statements what the Palestinians are saying is no we won't accept
that we will be completely disarmed and you can simply continue with your genocide as if nothing
has happened if disarmament is off the table what does that mean for the future governance of Gaza
well the future governor governance of Gaza remains very much in the balance because as I
noted a few moments ago Israel continues to prohibit the committee that was established to
govern the Gaza Strip from even visiting the Gaza Strip and those who appointed them and who
have real power over the Israelis are doing absolutely nothing to change Israel's mind
in this respect as you may recall a few months ago Israel consistently stated that if Hamas did
not disarm that it would then once again launch a massive invasion of the Gaza Strip I think that's
currently not on the table given the wars against Lebanon and Iran but I think it needs to be considered
as a very serious possibility and it's not at all surprising that as Israel continues to make
these threats that the Palestinians are saying only when we have clear guarantees not only
about a real ceasefire but also about a real Israeli withdrawal only then will serious discussions
about disarmament be considered good to talk to you again so many thanks indeed for being with us
Moan Rubani there in Montreal thank you it's been a subdued Easter in the occupied Palestinian
territories where ceremonies have been scaled back because of the Iran war a small Sunday mass
was held at the church of the holy sepulchre in occupied east Jerusalem the sites revered by
Christians as the traditional site of Jesus Christ's crucifixion and resurrection Israeli
authorities have limited access on Palm Sunday last week the latin patriarch was blocked from
entering the church sparking international condemnation in Gaza orthodox Palestinian
Christians who followed the eastern calendar have celebrated Palm Sunday it marks the beginning
of the holy week leading to orthodox Easter worshipers attended mass at the saint porphyrios
I'm sorry porphyrios prophyrios church in Gaza city it came under Israeli attack several times
before the ceasefire and as Christians around the world marked the Easter holiday under the
shadow of war religious leaders are calling for peace sonia gaego reports it is the most
important date in the christian calendar marked this year by both tradition and tension addressing
more than a billion Catholics worldwide from the Vatican Pope Leo led his first Easter mass
as pontiff and the message from st peter square was shaped by events far beyond it
death is always lurking we see it present in injustices in partisan selfishness in the oppression
of the poor in the lack of attention given to the most vulnerable we see it in violence in the
wounds of the world in the cry of pain that rises from every corner because of the abuses
that crush the weakest an appeal for mercy as the conflict in the middle east loomed over
what is meant to be a celebration of renewal where despite airstrikes and destruction
many felt the need to commemorate the holiday over the weekend the message resonated in Germany
in the annual Easter marching cologne not a religious procession but a demand for an end to
hostilities and in France as the bells of Notre Dame in Paris rang out calling worshipers to
in Lyon thousands of adults were baptized a sign said church leaders of the search for meaning
in an evermore uncertain world sonia gallego aljazeera it is good to have you with us this is
aljazeera with continuing coverage of the war between the u.s israel and iran the latest
developments this hour u.s president donald trump has posted yet another warning to iran
over the strait of homoes he's set a deadline of tuesday at 8 p.m eastern time for taqran to
reopen the strait saying that u.s forces will hit power plants and bridges iran has dismissed the
ultimatum as a quote unbalanced action iran has attacked critical civilian infrastructure
across the gulf but rain reported attacks on its largest oil refinery on sunday and cuwait
state petroleum company said that drones had severely damaged oil and petrochemical facilities
a u.s amon shot down over iran has been rescued after a 48 hour search operation american media
reports u.s forces destroyed at least one of their own planes on purpose during the mission
because it had become stuck iran though claims its forces destroyed the aircraft
u.s politicians have been reacting to donald trump's online outburst over iran with some calling
the president unhinged speaking on nbc's meet the press democratic senator tim cane called on
trump and defense secretary pete hegseth to tone down their rhetoric they wake up this morning
and hear about the rescue of the pilot so very so very grateful for that for the service of
the search and rescue teams christin this is why the the president and secretary hegseth's
rhetoric about no mercy no quarter death from above the bomb you to the stone ages this kind of
rhetoric is really dangerous because the likelihood of having a downed pilots or others who are
captured in a war like this is very high and if you send the message that there's no quarter
for the folks on the other side that that really encourages them to mistreat our folks and so i hope
the white house i doubt the president will but please dial back the rhetoric because you
don't need to put people like these pilots more at risk by the rhetoric that you use
earlier my colleague sirle vanier spoke to rashid al mohanadi from the center
for international policy research at the university of tahran professor
fired azadi part of that conversation focused on what would happen if the u.s launched significant
strikes on iranian energy science i think the whole region will go dark if iran goes dark if they
hit uh power but they have already had power plants plenty but if they escalate uh you know
trump is saying that he wants to turn uh iran into they send it back to the uh
stonage and if iran is experiencing a stonage the whole region will experience a stonage
this is called an eye for an eye you have i'm glad that our brother in your studio
is a defense expert secretary of war says that they have done nine thousand sorties can
a country do nine thousand sorties
countries out of an aircraft carrier that's 2,000 miles away, the answer is no.
They have used the territories of our neighboring countries to attack Iran.
Attacking a country is against international law without a UN resolution.
Defending under Article 51 is Iran's right.
And helping a country to attack a neighboring country, that's also illegal.
So the best way for Trump to find an off-ramp is to declare victory.
He can declare victory today, you know, he has that ability.
And then go and take over Greenland or Canada or do other mischief.
But if he does to Iran what he's talking about, he's not scaring anyone here.
At the end of the day, he has to pay for all these damages, or his friends have to pay
for all these damages.
And Iran will respond, Iran has no other choice.
Rashid, your thoughts?
Well, the sorties came out of two aircraft carriers which can deliver significant amount
of sorties, but also...
So one of them is gone, by the way.
Oh, another one's coming back.
But so 9,000 in a month.
But also there were aircrafts flying out of Israel and out of Jordan.
The Gulf states made it clear that their lands, seas and air will not be used to
attack Iran.
Until today, Iran has not presented credible evidence for that.
If the Gulf wanted, the Gulf could have opened its air and there would be even more significant
damage towards Iran.
The Gulf has shown strategic restraint, its ability to thwart Iranian attacks, even
though it was aggressive just here in Qatar, 200-plus ballistic missiles fired at Qatar.
The country that was mediating, the country that was trying to stop this war, Oman
was attacked multiple times, Oman's civilian infrastructure was attacked multiple times.
So, and you know, I don't accept the strategy, but I know the strategy of the IRGC is to
cause as much damage as possible to pressure everybody to stop the war.
This is their strategy.
It's not working.
And you know, the Gulf states are still showing restraint.
The Gulf states are still welcoming a diplomatic solution.
And like I said, I think Trump is offering off-ramps.
If we go and read every truth social post, you know, verbatim literally, we will go nowhere.
And that's my, you know, recommendation to the brothers in Iran.
Look at the big picture.
Don't focus on semantics.
A residential building in the Israeli city of Haifa has partially collapsed after being
hit by a projectile.
Israeli authorities say four people have been wounded with one of them in a critical
condition.
They also fear that more people could be trapped.
Search efforts are continuing.
Let's go live now to the occupied West Bank.
Health is here as Nur Ode is following events for us.
Nur Haifa, a vital economic and industrial hub, talk us through what's been happening
there today.
And it's been in the eye of the storm really for much of the, for much of this war.
We've seen Haifa targeted time and again because it's so strategic, because it's so important,
the oil refinery, the power grid, the bay itself, which is also, which also hosts part
of Israel's Navy and so on.
This attack targeted a multi-story building.
It is believed now that the ballistic missile either didn't explode or only partially
exploded in any, exploded in any case.
The building is now unstable.
Three up to three or four people that are believed to be trapped under the rubble are
feared to be dead at this moment.
That is the latest coming out, the latest lines coming out of Israel.
A paramedic source told the Israeli military radio that much.
In the meantime, of course, the number of Israelis injured throughout the day.
There have been many Iranian missiles fired as well as rockets from Hezbollah.
The number of Israelis injured has risen to 36.
And all in all, it's not just Haifa.
It is every city.
And when those sirens go, all Israelis have to head to the shelters or to the safe
rooms.
That is why Israel has been able to keep down the number of casualties and injuries
considering that over 600 missiles have been fired at Israel just from Iran.
The reason why the casualties have been kept at a minimum is because people are
obeying the instructions of the home front command, getting to the shelters
when they have them, especially in those large, large cities in Israel.
The underserved areas is really where we saw more casualties.
Al Jazeera is now a day reporting live from the occupied West Bank.
Many thanks indeed, no.
In Lebanon, the Israeli army has carried out new strikes on Beirut's southern
suburbs in a densely populated residential area.
At least four people have been killed and 39 others injured.
It says that it's continuing attacks on Hezbollah's military
infrastructure, more than a million people have been forcibly displaced
across the country.
They hit a completely civilian area.
It's mostly migrants here, Sudanese people.
People were at home and they struck them.
Are those military objectives?
Where is the UN?
No one says anything.
Aren't they human too?
They're killing children and women.
The whole world has to speak up.
It has to see and say something.
Have we become nothing but numbers, a people of numbers?
How is that possible?
We are devastated.
Our morale is low.
When you see your friends and neighbours in pieces on the ground
and blood everywhere and the house destroyed,
our house was destroyed.
Where are we going to sleep?
Where do we go?
Live now to Beirut Al Jazeera's Heidi Pettis there.
What are you learning, Heidi, about what was hit in Beirut
and were these pre-worn strikes or surprise attacks?
Yeah, so there were about eight airstrikes on Beirut's
southern suburbs over the course of the day,
starting at around midday.
Now, most of those were in areas that are subject
to these rolling forced evacuation orders
by the Israeli military.
But the last one on Jena,
which is a heavily populated residential area,
there was no warning given for that strike.
It's a very densely populated area.
The strike hit just meters from one of Beirut's
main hospitals and MSF has described
basically a mass casualty event there.
They said people were being carried into the hospital
on other people's shoulders with severe injuries.
The initial toll that we have
from the Ministry of Health here in Lebanon
is that four people were killed in that attack
and 39 wounded, but they are still going through that site.
And so the number of casualties
from that particular strike could indeed rise.
But it has been a very heavy day here in Lebanon.
There were significant airstrikes throughout last night
all through the day across the country.
And in the last hour and a half, actually,
another assassination strike, it seems,
in eastern Beirut in a Christian neighborhood
called Ainsadeh.
So a residential building was targeted.
It looks like the missile was going for an apartment
on the third floor, which the mayor says
was empty at the time.
However, the floor collapsed
and has killed some people on the second floor.
And one of those killed is a man called Pyamouad.
Now, he is a local leader in the Lebanese forces,
which is a right-wing Christian party here in Lebanon.
The news we're getting from the scene
is that he and his wife are among the casualties there
and it's causing a lot of consternation in that area.
There is a lot of suspicion and fear
about sheltering displaced people already in Lebanon.
Local MPs from the party are saying
that stringent measures need to be taken
when rental agreements are made
if you're welcoming in displaced people
and that, in fact, displaced people
should only be sheltered in official shelters.
And so this is really upping the temperature
in terms of the amount of fear and suspicion here
in Lebanon and increasing community tensions,
which we've seen after a number of these
Israeli assassination strikes
when they hit areas of Beirut with no warning
and indeed areas outside where people might expect them to be.
So that is areas where people thought
that they would be safe.
This is an assault on two parts of the country.
How are Israeli attacks hiding in the south
affecting his wallet supply lines
and, of course, the people who live there?
Yeah, so Israel has been engaged
in a systematic campaign against civilian infrastructure
in the south of Lebanon.
We've seen them targeting many of the bridges
over the Lattani River in the last couple of weeks.
It's a total of nine bridges that they've hit so far.
Some of them are major crossings,
like on the coastal highway.
And then there are a number of other smaller secondary bridges
that they've hit right from the Mediterranean Sea
with that one near the coastal highway
and then all the way up into in the last 48 hours,
targeting two bridges actually
in the southern part of the Bekar Valley.
Now, Israel says that the reason it's doing that
is to cut off his bullet supply lines,
stop them from moving men and weapons to south Lebanon.
But, of course, this is civilian infrastructure.
It belongs to the Lebanese state
and it is used by civilians.
In fact, used by the thousands of civilians
who do remain in southern Lebanon
in defiance of these forced evacuation orders
by the Israeli military.
And speaking with aid organizations
over the last couple of weeks there,
increasingly concerned about their ability
to deliver supplies to those civilians
who remain down there.
They're worried about getting them food and medicine
and civilians in the area.
It makes it a lot more difficult for them to move around.
And indeed, as these rolling forced evacuation orders come in,
if people do choose to move out of the south
and try to cross to the rest of the country,
it's just made that more difficult.
Heidi Pet, reporting live from Beirut.
Many thanks, indeed, Heidi.
A major border crossing between Lebanon and Syria
has been closed until further notice.
After warnings of an imminent Israeli strike,
around 10,000 people usually passed through
the al-Masnah crossing every day.
On Saturday, Israel threatened to attack the area.
It says the crossing is being used
to smuggle weapons to his bollard,
a claim denied by the Lebanese government.
The Middle East conflict is having far-reaching effects,
including impacting artisans
and Indian administered Kashmir.
The region relies heavily on handicrafts
with thousands of people working in the industry.
But their livelihoods are at risk,
as at least half the goods that they make are sold in the Middle East.
With the region stuck in a war,
orders are being delayed or cancelled.
Lina Abu Akle reports.
The Kotas are one of thousands of families
who have been part of Kashmir's craft industry for generations.
They spin yarn from the wool of Himalayan
chang-thangi goats on traditional handlooms,
creating Peshmina scarves.
Peshmina is not just work for us, it's our legacy and identity.
I am one of the thousands of women who hand-spin the yarn,
and this spinning is the backbone of our livelihood.
However, their income is in jeopardy.
The family has reduced production,
using only two of their four handlooms.
That's because at least 50% of Kashmir's handicrafts
are sold to the Middle East,
and the regional conflict has led to cancellations.
This is impacting us a lot.
The work is minimal, about 90% less than usual.
Tausif Bhatt also comes from a family of Peshmina makers.
But now, he runs a company employing around 60 people.
If the situation remains the same and the conflict continues,
I think we may eventually have to shut down the business.
The Kashmir Chamber of Commerce says it's not only a lack of orders
that is a problem, but the cost of sending anything
has risen astronomically.
Nobody can send the shipments,
because we have the airline problems,
we have the by-sea, there are problems,
and I would rather say 400,000 people
are affected with this war.
That's a lot of families at risk of losing their livelihoods.
In France, rising oil and gas prices
are disrupting the fishing industry,
with some boats staying in port,
because they can't cover the costs.
Natasha Butler reports from Boulogne-sur-Mer
on the north coast of France.
Early morning in the northern French port of Boulogne-sur-Mer.
Bruno Marcolin's sons prepare their boat
before it heads back to sea,
but these are difficult times.
The price of marine diesel has almost doubled
because of the war in the Middle East.
Sales barely cover costs.
Bruno says he's never experienced anything like it.
I've seen crises before, but never this severe.
In my 40 years fishing, we've had highs and lows,
we've been resilient,
but today it's an unprecedented situation.
I can't say when it will end.
Bruno takes us to see the head of the port's fishmongers union.
I'm Mariek Chazan says if fuel costs and inflation keep rising,
the impact on the industry could be devastating.
If the war continues and energy prices get worse,
it could destroy parts of the industry.
Some boats won't be able to return to sea.
It won't be worth it for them.
There'll be less fish,
and some companies might have to shut down.
The weather is as gloomy as the mood here.
The war may be far away,
but the ripple effect on the global economy
is being felt on these shores.
When the costs are going up for fishermen and women at sea
and the processing companies,
it inevitably pushes up the prices for consumers.
At this market,
Sondrine says people are buying less,
forcing fishmongers to adapt.
Everything is getting more expensive,
so we try to offer cheaper fish varieties to attract customers.
It's true that when I'm shopping,
prices are higher.
I'm more careful than before.
The French government has announced
some limited financial aid for the industry this month,
but unless costs come down,
Boulogne's fishing community says it will need more help
to keep boats at sea and livelihoods afloat.
Natasha Butler, Al Jazeera, Boulogne-sur-Mer, France.
In other news, Serbia says that powerful explosives
have been found near a pipeline
that carries Russian gas to Hungary.
Authorities say the discovery was made outside of Serbia
and town near the Hungarian border.
It comes just a week before closely watched elections in Hungary.
Prime Minister Viktor Orbán is fighting to extend
his 16 years in power.
He's linked Ukraine to those explosives.
For years,
Ukraine has been working to cut Europe off from Russian energy.
They blew up Nord Stream,
shut down the gas pipeline supplying Hungary,
and this year placed Hungary under an oil blockade
by closing the Družba pipeline.
The Russian section of the Turk Stream
is also under continuous military attack.
Ukraine's efforts pose a life-threatening danger to Hungary.
Kyiv has rejected Orbán's accusations,
posting on X, the foreign ministry spokesman said,
Ukraine has nothing to do with this,
most probably a Russian false flag operation
as part of Moscow's heavy interference
in Hungarian elections.
More than 70 people are missing after a boat
carrying refugees and migrants
sank in the central Mediterranean.
At least two people died and 32 have been rescued.
The boat believed to be carrying more than 100 people
left from Northern Libya on Saturday.
The survivors were rescued by two merchant ships
and brought to the Italian island of Lampedusa.
Since the beginning of the year,
more than 680 migrants have died
or have gone missing in the central Mediterranean,
according to the International Organization for Migration.
Cuba is facing an unprecedented public health emergency
caused by an acute fuel shortage.
It's the result of a near total US blockade
on fuel imports now into its fourth month.
Human rights organizations have condemned the ban
as an extreme form of collective punishment.
Our Latin America editor Lucia Newman reports from Havana.
At Cuba's largest pediatric hospital,
the emergency room is unusually empty,
not for lack of emergencies,
but of public transport to get here
and not just for patients, but doctors and nurses too.
Dressing us in oversized surgical robes
that were recently donated
anesthesiologist Anjot Ferdnandes
takes us to the recovery room.
It's almost barren
because surgeries have been reduced to the bare minimum.
We used to carry out 10,000 surgeries a year.
I don't think we'll reach 1,000 this year.
After COVID, we went progressively downhill,
but the public health system prioritizes pediatrics,
so we may do.
But now our reserves are hitting rock bottom
because of the power crisis.
Our laboratories can't produce medicine or anesthesia either.
More than three months of a near total US fuel blockade
on Cuba are having deadly consequences,
especially in hospitals and clinics
where conditions are rapidly deteriorating.
If in mortality,
once the lowest in the Americas is rising steadily.
And these are two very modern machines.
This one is much older, but it's essential
and it doesn't have a battery.
So as the light goes out, it's off.
I'm gonna do a blank.
Dr. Ferdnandes says it's like operating blind.
Acute fuel shortages and constant blackouts
are also impacting life-saving treatments
like kidney dialysis.
At the Carlos Finley Hospital,
patients say they're under extreme stress.
We have to come three times a week.
And if you don't have transportation to get here,
you can die.
So some of us can't leave the hospital at all.
In this salon,
there are six patients receiving dialysis right now.
But if there is a power blackout,
this machine, all of these machines have a battery,
but they only last for 15 minutes.
That means that if the power generator
of this hospital isn't working or it runs out of fuel,
the staff tell me that they've had to manually pump the blood
back into the patient's body.
The Trump administration seems to believe
the fuel blockade will speed up
the fall of its socialist neighbor.
Yet even critics of the Cuban government
acknowledge that this latest act
of collective punishment is harming,
not helping ordinary Cubans
who are not responsible for this decade's old dispute.
You see a new man in Al Jazeera, Havana.
How can AI be used to prevent gun deaths?
That's the question be asked in Birmingham, Alabama,
a U.S. city with a big gun violence program.
It's just renewed a deal for a system of sensors
that detects gunshots and deploys drones
to crime scenes autonomously.
But critics say they target black communities
and make little difference.
As Phil Lavel reports.
I don't want to see anything like it.
that. Cherie and Rosalyn are two mums with the most painful bond imaginable.
Imagine seeing your loved one shot over 12 or 13 times. That picture would never go out my head.
Both received a heartbreaking call. Their sons had been shot dead. Different men,
but same day one year apart. I remember that day like yesterday. I remember pulling up on the
scene and seeing the vehicle shot up blood on the car. There are hundreds of stories like this here
in Birmingham, Alabama, all with the same ending. Gun violence is rife. Could AI have saved any of
them? It doesn't work now. And that is what this is all about because AI is being used here to
try to combat gun violence. There is this network of sensors dotted around listening
for the sound of gunshots. They hear them and they dispatch police automatically but where those
sensors are located. That's what's controversial. These devices are placed in predominantly poor
neighborhoods. They're placed in black and brown neighborhoods and what it means is more police
presence. Multiple sensors. The technology has been used in cities across the US for years. Yet
many are rolling it back or cancelling it all together. But in this city, synonymous with
the civil rights movement, they have just spent millions of dollars to extend the contract. On
top of that, they've added drones which take off autonomously and can get to the scene of any
potential crime long before the police can. Birmingham saw a 44% drop in homicides last
year. That is a 10 year low. Another statistic, 88% of victims were black. It's evident that
it's not working. It's not the technology that's keeping us safe. And it may be other
reasons why crime is not as prevalent. The company behind the tech says it has seen a reduction of
61% in gunfire incidents over the last two years and that it helps because up to 85% of gunshots
are never reported by residents. There are some areas where we do respond to shootings,
but we don't get a 911 call. We identify those areas as a priority. And it is solely
the police who choose which neighborhoods to put sensors in. The family members that won't
forget, that's retaliation. That's what worries these mums. Shootings lead to revenge and more
shootings. They spend their lives now consoling other parents and trying to break that cycle.
I never be healed until I make it up there. That's my goal. I'm gonna make it up there
with him. For these mums, it is not about the sounds that are picked up,
but the silence that follows and the emptiness it leaves behind.
Phil Lavelle, Al Jazeera, Birmingham, Alabama. We'll be right back. On my left you can see the thick
column of the smoke that is the continuation of the American and Israeli strikes. Women,
children killed in an Israeli strike that targeted southern Lebanon. Continuing to hear
the sound of sirens according to Israeli media, one drone has infiltrated the borders.
There is a move in Congress to basically tie Donald Trump's hands and end the conflict.
They say that's not America first, that's Israel first. There is so much concern about what all
this is going to do to energy markets, oil prices, gas prices, not just in the region,
but around the world. Stay with Al Jazeera for the latest developments.
In-depth analysis of the day's headlines. Diplomacy yet again was used as a
ruse for war. Critical debate. Who betrayed the table? Who attacked the negotiations for the
second time? For the third time during the talks we should be attacked? Who is talking
about a greater country for itself? Israel, not Iran? Iran has been a huge supporter of
terrorism over the years. I really have to take exception to the idea that Iran is innocent in
this. Inside story on Al Jazeera. Hello, this is Al Jazeera with our continuing coverage of
the war between the US, Israel and Iran. I'm Rob Matheson. This is the news live from Doha and
coming up in the next 60 minutes. Donald Trump sets a Tuesday deadline for Iran to reopen the
Strait of Hormuz or the US will bomb its power plants, bridges and quote, unleash hell.
We are determined to defend Iran's foreign ministry dismisses the US president's warning
and vows a swift retaliation to any US attacks. US troops rescue a second airman in a high-stakes
mission in Iran two days after his fighter jet went down. In Lebanon, a new wave of Israeli attacks
on parts of Beirut caused extensive damage, killing at least four people. And the Iran
war squeezes global economies. Workers are the worst hit. Weavers in Indian
administered Kashmir say orders for the famed Kashmina shawls have dried up.
Donald Trump's threatened to unleash the might of the US military on Iran to get the Strait of
Hormuz reopened. He set a fast approaching deadline promising to attack civilian sites
if it remains shut. And just a short time ago, he simply posted the day and the time,
Tuesday, 8 p.m. Eastern time. Earlier, Trump posted that Tuesday is going to be
Power Plant Day and Bridge Day, all wrapped up in one in Iran. He went on,
there will be nothing like it. Trump then uses an expletive demanding that the Strait be opened,
saying otherwise Iranians will be living in hell. But Tehran has warned it will retaliate.
Foreign ministry spokesman Esmael Bahay says any US-related location in the Middle East
would be a target. Our armed forces have made it clear that in case Iran's infrastructure
is attacked, we would react in kind. Our armed forces would target any similar infrastructure
that is owned or in any way or manner related to the United States or contributes to their
act of aggression against Iran. We're going to be live from Tehran shortly.
First, Al Jazeera's Mike Hanna reports from Washington, DC. The unusual use of an expletive
by a national leader, perhaps a symbol of President Trump's frustration with the Iranian
government and their refusal to concede to the demands that he is making. That reference
as well was to the Strait of Hormuz, which in recent days President Trump had insisted
he did not care about saying the US did not need the oil passing through the Strait
and it was up to the countries who are reliant on that oil to deal with the situation. But now
the demand about opening the Strait of Hormuz appears front and center of the President's
new demands of the Iranian government. President Trump threatening to, and I use his words,
blowing everything and taking the oil if Iran does not meet his new deadline,
which has now been set at 8 p.m. Eastern time on Tuesday evening. He says in an earlier media post
that a power plant day and bridge day all wrapped up on Tuesday. But on the other hand,
in addition to these threats, President Trump is sending signals that there's some kind
of negotiation process underway. He's indicated that his close confidants Jared Kushner and
Stephen Whitcoff are in consultation with either the Iranian government and identified
figures or some form of intermediary. And speaking to US news outlets, President Trump
says that he is optimistic that there can be an agreement very soon. He says the agreement could
come within a matter of days rather than a matter of weeks. So you've got this dichotomous
approach from the president on the one hand threatening obliteration to civilian targets
within Iran, which some observers would contend to be a war crime. But on the other hand,
what he is saying is, yes, we are talking, the talks are going well, and they could come
to fruition before that new deadline I set, which is 8 p.m. Eastern time on Tuesday.
Mike Hanna, Al Jazeera, Washington. Well, the Speaker of Iran's Parliament,
Mohamed Bakhar Khalibaf, has also responded to Donald Trump saying your reckless moves are dragging
the United States into a living hell for every single family. And our whole region is going to burn
because you insist on following Netanyahu's commands. Make no mistake, you won't gain
anything through war crimes. I'm going to bring in Mohamed Vahl, who's life for his
entire crime. So the Speaker of Iran's Parliament accusing Donald Trump of war
crimes. What else is Iran saying about this? Well, Rob, there is a lot of statements
today, like every day, but today there is a lot of statements, not only from the Foreign
Ministry, but also from the Speaker of the Parliament, from IRGC, and all of them are
speaking in one voice. We have already quoted, you have already quoted the Foreign
Ministry spokesman talking about Iran's approach to this situation and what it
is going to do if its infrastructure gets destroyed by the Americans. He also
tried to explain how the whole war is based on lies. He said that first there is the lie that
Iran is pursuing the production of nuclear weapons. There is the lie that Iran is presenting a
threat, an imminent threat to the United States. Instead, he said the real threat is the threat
that the Americans are presenting right now to Iran and have been presented for,
presenting for a long time. And including also this threat to destroy Iranian people's
infrastructure, which is to him an equivalent to a threat of genocide against Iranian people.
Also, he spoke about the lie that Americans are waging this war in order to help the Iranian
people. He said this war is not here to help the Iranian people. That's also one of the
series of lies he talked about in order to convince the viewers and general public,
international public that Iran has the right to defend itself and this war is wrong. Also,
the IRGC commander, today he said that the state of Hormuz is never going to return to its previous
position or situation, especially for the United States and Israel. IST is going to be subjected
to a new order after this war and understandably because they have been explaining what type
of order is going to be there. He said Iran is going to extract fees on ships from now on
so that they can compensate Iran, can compensate the destruction that has been visited on the country
in this war. So there is no indication that Iran is being intimidated by these threats,
even though that deadline is approaching very quickly. So they have been consistent from
day one that there is going to be no change. They are not going to submit to the threats
and they are going to retaliate and they know how to retaliate. They know the places
they are going to strike at and they have what it takes to do that.
Mohammad, we're also hearing, of course, about attacks in Bushar province and that's where the
Bushar nuclear power plant is. Tell us more about that and tell us also about the attacks
across Iran. There have been several strikes today across Iran, including in Ahvaz, the Ahvaz
International Airport and many other cities. Here I have a list of those cities but
Bushar is an outstanding situation because I think this is the fifth time that it has been
hit since the beginning of this war, not direct hits that have caused extensive damage because if an
extensive damage has been inflicted on that power plant, it is the only one that is functioning
and it has a huge store of radioactive material in it, then it would be a catastrophe equal to
Chernobyl or maybe worse. It is a power plant that is very close to most of the Gulf countries
and also in a populated region of Iran and that's why the IEA has always been warning that this
plant in particular should be spared and also the Russians are very much concerned about it
because they have some of their experts there in that plant so that's the major incident today
even though there is no destruction in the plant, so far all the hits were near misses and
sometimes somebody was killed there in the plant but the destruction of the plant itself is what
people are afraid of and warning against right now. That's Mohamed, I'll talk to you as they're
from Tehran. Mohamed, thank you very much indeed. We've got two experts joining us
from the US Capitol, Kenneth Kasman is a Middle East policy analyst and a senior fellow at the
Sufan Center. Alex Fatanka is a senior fellow at the Middle East Institute. He's also the author
of the book The Battle of the Ayatollahs in Iran, the United States foreign policy
and policy rivalry. Gentlemen, thank you very much indeed for being with us. Alex, I want to
start with you. Let's talk about this statement that came out of this text rather that came
out from Donald Trump threatening the attacks on Iran in the event that the Strait of Hormuz does
not get opened. What is the tone of this latest post by Donald Trump? Tell us about the way that
he's thinking at the moment given the fact that he's using language that we have very rarely,
if at all, ever seen from any statesman. Oh, it's great to be back with you. Look,
I think exactly what you just said is so true. We haven't heard this kind of language
before. It's a surprise, frankly, even for President Trump to speak in such a tone.
But it's probably nothing more than an expression of his frustration. He's kind of boxed in. He
doesn't know which way to go. He really doesn't want to escalate militarily. He really wants
to have the Strait of Hormuz opened up. And he really wants to get a bigger deal with the
Iranian side if he could. And he's not going to get there by adopting this sort of language.
And we've heard from the Iranians already. They're kind of dismissing the language.
They're pointing to the fact that this seems to be Donald Trump expressing frustration
and not laying any sort of signpost for how we can move forward from here if the diplomatic
track should have any chance to succeed at all. Although President Trump, as we've also heard,
is claiming the diplomatic track is still very much alive. But it just doesn't seem to
be sitting nicely next to the language that he's been using the last couple of days.
Yeah. Kenneth, as Alex was just referring to there, Donald Trump was also talking to,
I think it was Fox News about this. He took a very different tone when he's talking to them. He was
saying the negotiating track was still open. I understand that some of the Iranian negotiators
had been given some sort of amnesty in order while they were doing, carrying out the talks.
How difficult is it, do you think, for whoever is doing the negotiations at the
moment, within the leadership of Iran, to be able to identify what message Donald Trump is actually
sending? Well, thank you for having me, Dan. Yeah, I think it's very difficult. And you know, we have
very clear divisions within the Iranian regime that are emerging now. And that makes it even
more difficult because some of the regime interpret his comments to be somewhat willing to
compromise, and others view it. They would probably look at the statement today with the curses as
very disparaging and not something they want to, they feel they can negotiate with. But
I think it's instructive to look at an article that former Foreign Minister Zarif issued this
week, which was basically, I read it as a message to the hardliners in his own
in his own country, in the regime, saying, you know, you guys need to figure out a way to
settle this with Mr. Trump before you get us all killed. And I think it was a very, very
important article that bears reading. And he lays out some steps that could could potentially form
the basis of a successful negotiation, possibly. Alex, throughout all of the negotiations or
the putative negotiations that apparently have been going forward, Iran has invariably called
the demands by the Trump administration as maximalist. And those are also allegations that
the administration has made against Iran as well. Is there any position that Iran would be able to
take in these negotiations, Alex, in order for it to be able to move forward to some sort of
diplomatic solutions, at least start some sort of negotiation, but at the same time
retain some sort of control over its sovereignty and its national interests?
You know, the basic reality is that United States could tomorrow, President Trump tomorrow could
declare victory and walk away from this and say he brought about regime change that is
destroyed so much of Iran that Iran set back 10, 15 years. I mean, he has that capacity or that
option to declare victory. The Iranian side, for them, this war isn't one that they're
going to win militarily. They've never said they're going to win militarily against the United
States. For them, strategic victory is if you bleed the United States, that you make the cost of
another war so high that United States and partner states are never going to try that again. That's
what victory looks like there. But look, even in that kind of a best case scenario, both sides
decide, you know, let's just call it there and walk away. Where is the region going to be at?
Where particularly the Gulf States, whose economies depend on the idea of stability, invest the
confidence. What's going to happen to them? Iran could choose not to want to invest in its economy.
The rest of the neighborhood wants to invest in their economy. They're thinking of post-oil economies.
They can't sit in a situation where you're basically in a limbo. So, you know, you have to
hope if the diplomatic track, which by the way is not the only track, but this is the one track
that the two sides soften their positions. You know, Ken was talking about Zarif's article.
Now, Zarif has already been threatened with execution into Iran for having written that
article. That just shows you, in Tehran, they're not speaking with one voice.
But I agree with Ken. If the Iranians are going to find a way out of this, they need to get their
voices around the idea that, you know, now they've made their point, if that's what they want to
call it, now maybe look for that off-ramp. Because I think the American president too
might be open to softening this position, despite what he might be saying in social posts that
we've seen in recent days. Kenneth, is there a navigation that could be brought against the
Iranian leadership that they, because of the level of response that they have been able to
show in reaction to the attacks from Israel and from the U.S., that they might be running
the risk of being overconfident in this? And then by digging in, they're actually creating
a situation where they are forcing the U.S., forcing Donald Trump to exacerbate the situation
when, in fact...
If it just took a little bit of a rethinking, if you like, as Alex was referring to, just a
rethinking of their stance, that there might be a way of de-escalating this.
That's exactly what I was saying before, and that's exactly what Zaryf's article was saying.
If you guys continue down this road and keep provoking Trump, he is going to blow up
civilian sites, he is going to have a ground offensive, and you're going to get us all killed.
So you need to find a way out of this. That's exactly what Zaryf is saying.
Trump is open to a negotiation. Mr. Trump, where I might differ though, is Mr.
Trump cannot go to the American people and say and call it quits with the strain of
hormones closed. He must as a minimum have that waterway, that choke point, fully open for
free passage. He could not realistically explain to the American people why he entered into this
conflict and ends it up with the strain of hormones closed. I think that is just a non-starter
politically for Trump. Alex, I just want to go back to a point that Ken was making earlier,
that the divisions that we're seeing within the leadership inside Iran as well. Now,
they're not particularly public, but we are led to believe that those differences,
shall we say, of opinion and differences of approach are there. How much of an issue is
that going to be? Should we get to the point where negotiations of some sort can begin?
You know, that takes us to the issue of whether the United States had a bigger strategy to begin
with. Before this war started, if the United States wanted to sort of, if you will, empower
those people inside the regime that believe in the idea of diplomacy, what did the United
States or Israel, for that matter, do to empower them, if anything? I mean, are we,
for example, seeing some of these continued assassination of Iranian officials to be
part of that game plan where you're sort of taking a particular faction out of the equation
in order to empower moderates who want to come back to diplomacy? I haven't seen a systematic,
kind of clear evidence that that's happening, but that, if that was the case, that seems pretty
solid sound. But as of today, five, six weeks into this war, the IRGC commanders, the first
generation commanders who have been together since 1979 are running the show,
and as of today, they don't seem to believe diplomacy is what they want. They don't think
the American side is going to give them anything that is not going to be short of humiliating.
They want, they don't want to be humiliated. You hear this constantly coming around Iran.
They want their dignity preserved, but others like Zarif are saying, well, you're dead,
then do your dignity is no good for you. And that's basically the fighting around as far
as I can tell. Again, as I mentioned before, that you're a senior fellow at the Sufran
Center. I was looking on the website, there is a big article there about the possibility
of the Houthis becoming involved to a greater degree in this conflict. Of course,
they've already been firing missiles towards Israel. I do know that an advisor to Iran's
new Supreme Leader has said that Iran could close the Bab al-Mandab Strait at the southern end
of the Red Sea. That is something, of course, that the Houthis have threatened to do in the
past and they have done to some degree effectively. Previously, what is the impact?
Do you think if that Strait is closed, and how much does that exacerbate the situation?
Well, thank you. That was my piece. Thank you. The advisor to the Supreme Leader,
I don't know what he's advising. He must be advising a comatose
virtual corpse, because there's no evidence that West Ham is even conscious at this point.
But anyway, the Houthis, they can complicate the picture. They've been hesitant so far.
They don't know, you know, Tehran does not have a lot more weapons to give them.
Tehran has its own problems right now. They're worried about, again, bringing
Mr. Trump full force against them. They're worried about, again, a possible ground offensive.
And I think anybody that's dismissing Mr. Trump's willingness to go in on the ground,
either to Iran or Yemen, I think is very much underestimating his determination.
So, I think it's time for the Iranians to start negotiating and stop what appears to be the
same strategy that led the Gaza Strip to be completely destroyed, which is to refuse
every offer. And every day this goes on, the deal on the table for Iran is going to get worse.
And it's probably time the regime started understanding that.
Kenneth Katzmann and Alex Vatanka, we appreciate you being with us and all of you gentlemen.
Thank you very much indeed. Thank you.
Now, the threat of escalation in Iran puts the Gulf region squarely in the crossfire.
The sites Iran is threatening to hit are almost entirely located in GCC countries,
which are already coping with daily attacks. Kuwait says it's been hit by a series of drone
attacks. Authorities report to major power and desalination plants have been targeted.
One of the facilities is in Al-Zor, it's nearly 90 kilometers south of Kuwait city.
Another attack hit the finance ministry complex. That building is in central Kuwait city in Bahrain.
Iran targeted an oil facility, sparking several fires. Emergency response team said the blaze has
been fully extinguished. Over the past few weeks, Manama has come under repeated Iranian missile
and drone attacks. Mohamed Jamjoum is here in the Catholic capital, Doha. So attacks
in Gulf countries in the last 24 hours. Now they're having to prepare for an
escalation of Donald Trump. Carries out his threats, Mohamed.
Yeah, Rob, and let's just walk our viewers to where we are at this particular hour,
because just in the past few minutes, we are now hearing reports out of Kuwait
that those sirens are sounding throughout Kuwait city, that potentially there are missiles
having been launched from Iran that are being intercepted over the skies of Kuwait city.
We'll get you those details as more of them emerge. That's the latest of what we've
heard from Kuwait right now. As you mentioned in the last 24 hours, several attacks on energy
infrastructure sites in Kuwait, as well as water desalination sites. You had those attacks
also happening in Bahrain, attacks happening in the UAE, and we are at a point right now
when there is this deadline that's been imposed by Donald Trump within the next 24 hours or so,
in which he says if Iran does not reopen the Strait of Hormuz, then
energy infrastructure sites, power plants, bridges, other sites in Iran will be targeted.
And in the past when Donald Trump has made those threats, the Iranians have clearly said
that they will then target similar sites in the region. So that is where we're at right now.
So much concern in Gulf countries about what is going to happen next. At this stage,
you've already seen desalination plants, energy infrastructure sites in several countries that
have been hit by Iranian aggression over the course of this past month. Now we're at this
critical moment, people wondering what exactly is going to happen next. Now, the Gulf countries
have repeatedly stated that they want to try to de-escalate the situation. They are in a
defensive posture, but the question becomes what happens if the US goes ahead attacks Iran
in the way that they have threatened to do so? Iran's retaliation, what that's going to mean
for all of these countries going forward? And at the center of those that you're talking about
there of course is the Strait of Hormuz. It is open apparently at the moment. Iran insists at
least that it is open and it's been holding meetings with the man. What more do we know
about those meetings? It's an interesting time because over the course of the past couple of
days you've had these reports that ships from different countries have been able to
navigate the Strait of Hormuz, have been able to pass through the Strait of Hormuz,
whether they be some Asian countries, European countries. And the question now is,
is that going to continue at this critical juncture? Now we know that the Omanis and the
Iranians have held these talks. They're happening at a deputy foreign minister level.
So that seems to be a pretty high level. They are trying to figure out a way forward
for the smooth transit of ships through the Strait of Hormuz. They are discussing
lots of options. The question is what are those options going to be
and who exactly is going to be involved in talks going forward? Also,
whatever option may be settled on by Oman and Iran, is that going to be something that would
satisfy the Americans or would the Americans feel that they once again need to retaliate
against Iran for not completely opening the Strait of Hormuz to the way that the
Americans would like? So many questions at this particular juncture that have not yet been
answered. Also, how will GCC countries react? Look, the fact of the matter is most of the
world and the region has said that they want to see a complete reopening of the Strait of
Hormuz. It will be critical to see what the Omanis and the Iranians agree upon going forward,
how much longer that takes, and what the other players in the region and beyond
will think about any potential plan.
Mohammad, I appreciate you breaking that down for us. Mohammad, I'm June there here in Doha.
Well, the residential building in the Israeli city of Haifa has partially collapsed after
being hit by a projectile. Israeli authorities say four people have been wounded with one
in a critical condition. They also fear more people could be trapped. Search efforts are
continuing late into Sunday night. Rob McBride joins us now from the Jordanian capital.
Amman, he's monitoring events from there. Okay, so Haifa is a significant site,
it's a big industrial area. What do we know about this attack, Rob?
Yeah, that's right. I mean, Haifa is often targeted in these attacks. It is a very
important strategic transport and industrial hub. A lot of Israel's oil refining takes place
in Haifa. It often comes under missile attack, but given its proximity to the Lebanese border
in the north of the country, it also comes within rocket range of Hezbollah just across
the border in Lebanon. The authorities believe though this was a strike by an Iranian missile
that managed to get through the missile defensive shield. They also believe that it was a very heavy
warhead, possibly several hundred kilograms in weight. And there is a lot of talk at the scene
that it could be partly unexploded. The building that they are searching through at the moment
is already in danger of collapse. The possibility that there could be further unexploded
elements within there in the rubble is obviously causing complications. We understand that
among the injured around about 10 people were hurt for those more seriously injured. One of them
is an elderly man said to be in a very serious condition. And they are looking specifically
now for four people who are believed to be from the one apartment who remain unaccounted for.
Israel on Sunday was subjected to four salvos of incoming missiles from Iran,
according to the authorities. One of those missiles fell near the southern city of Beishiva
on the Neyot Khuvav industrial park. This is a very important industrial area
in the south of the country. It landed near a toxic waste dump. There is no talk of
hazard threat from this site. But it is of concern. This site has been hit three times
before during this conflict the last time just over a week ago, which caused a fire at a chemical plant.
Rob, thanks very much indeed. That's Robert Breid there talking to us from Amman.
A U.S. airman has been rescued in Iran after an intense 48-hour search operation.
The weapons systems officer had been missing since Friday when the fighter jet they were in
went down in the province of Kogelua and Boya Ahmad. Takran said it shot down the F-15E,
it's a two-seater aircraft. The pilot was rescued shortly afterwards.
And John Hendren reports from Washington, D.C.
It was a daring and risky mission to save an American airman from becoming an Iranian prisoner
of war. Iranian forces searched the mountainous areas of southwestern Iran after an F-15E
fighter jet went down on Friday. It was the first time a U.S. aircraft had crashed in
hostile territory in the five-week-old war. Two Black Hawk helicopters took fire as U.S.
teams raced to find the missing crew member. An A-10 Warthog, an air support aircraft,
was also damaged, its pilot ejecting over the Gulf. Iran broadcast photos of what it
said was debris from the fighter jet, including a jump seat. Although the pilot had been
rescued on Friday, the weapon specialist remained in hiding, evading Iranian forces for two
days. Finally, early on Sunday, deep in Iranian territory, the U.S. search operation was successful.
President Donald Trump made the announcement on social media, posting We Got Him, saying the
Colonel had been behind enemy lines in the treacherous mountains of Iran being hunted by
our enemies. He said U.S. forces had been monitoring his location 24 hours a day
and sent dozens of aircraft armed with the most lethal weapons in the world to retrieve him.
Trump added, he sustained injuries, but he will be just fine.
A U.S. official told Al Jazeera the rescue operation began in darkness but ended in
an intense firefight and daylight, before dozens of heavily armed aircraft and
hundreds of troops transported the airmen out of Iran. A U.S. officer in Iranian custody
could have given Iran leverage, as it had when Iran took U.S. hostages in 1979.
With that crisis averted, attention now shifts to the U.S. deadline for Iran to open the
Strait of Hormuz. John Hendron, Al Jazeera, Washington.
Well, as John was just mentioning, U.S. officials say the rescue mission involved
several aircraft. Iranian state media released these pictures, reportedly showing the
wreckage of a C-130 aircraft in Isfahan province. American media reporting that U.S.
forces destroyed at least one of their own planes on purpose because it had become
stuck and unable to fly out. Iranian armed forces dispute those series of events, claiming the
soldiers destroyed two C-130 aircraft and two Black Hawk helicopters in what it characterized as a
failed U.S. rescue operation. With God's help and support and through the vigilance
and readiness of the fighters of Islam in the armed forces using electronic warfare, advanced
new air defense systems, the implementation of a ground mosaic defense plan, and the creation of
a military and security cordon, a number of these aircraft, including two C-130 military transport
planes and two Black Hawk helicopters, were hit and forced to make emergency landings
in an area south of Isfahan. After Iranian Islamic fighters completed the operation to
encircle the enemy, in order to prevent the disgrace of Trump, the President of the United
States and the hollow prestige of the army, was forced to carry out heavy bombing of its
downed aircraft, equipment, commanders and soldiers. Simon Mail is a retired British
Army general and former Middle East advisor at the UK Ministry of Defense. He explains
how this rescue operation unfolded. An F-15 has two aircrew, obviously a pilot and a
weapons officer. The Colonel rescued his, the weapons officer, he'll be the back seat for
those who watched Top Gun, that is the Goose as opposed to Maverick Post. And when the aircraft
is hit, obviously both eject. What was interesting is the pilot ejected and was found
relatively quickly and was rescued and the weapons officer was not. They would have landed
inevitably a good distance probably from each other. They'd both have transponders,
they'd know pretty quickly where they'd landed. There'd be a transponder probably in the ejector
seat, I'm not an airman, I'm a cavalryman, armor officer and clearly on the pilot. Now in this
case of course the pilot, although we understand to have been wounded or damaged in some way,
whether by the ejector or the strike on the aircraft, will have gone into his escape and
evasion tactics which every pilot, every aircrew is taught as just part of their basic training
and there will be inevitably that any number of films about this locals will know where it's
landed, they'll have seen the parachutes come down, there will be local police, there may be a local
barracks and all of these have a certain degree of sheer luck if you're far enough away for them
to A, put a distance between yourself and the ejector seat or the debris of the crashed
aircraft and you can quickly be located. But even if you're located, you've actually got to
be retrieved. I don't know the circumstances of the pilot being rescued, but this obviously was a
man who was, say, however badly injured, trying to put distance between himself and the aircraft,
the ejector seat. And meanwhile of course they will have got drones over him, armed drones,
so they will have had eyes on him in many ways, they would have been able to track him anyway,
but they'll sooner or later had eyes on him, Thurbin imaging at night, visual during the
day. But even then you've got to imagine a net getting closer and closer around him. And eventually
you've got to put somebody on the ground who can physically lift him off. And in that you've
got to create a sort of area, sanitized area around him. And certainly the report does refer
to possibly the idea that they put some aircraft on the ground or helicopters. And that again,
they're vulnerable as well. And those may have been hit while they destroyed them,
in which case they'd have trans-shipped crew.
Minder of our top stories this hour, US President Donald Trump has posted yet another warning to
Iran over the Strait of Hormuz. He set a deadline of Tuesday at 8pm Eastern time for Taqran to
reopen the Strait, saying US forces will hit power plants and bridges. Iran says Trump's
threats are an indication of a criminal mindset and an expression of public incitement for
war crimes. Taqran warned it would retaliate by launching reciprocal attacks targeting
US-linked infrastructure in the Middle East. And Iran has attacked critical civilian infrastructure
across the Gulf. Buckrange reported attacks on its largest oil refinery on Sunday,
and Kuwait State Petroleum Company said drones had severely damaged oil and petrochemical
facilities. Russia's state nuclear company says it's evacuated nearly 200 workers from
Iran's Bushar nuclear plant in the south. And that's after a strike near its vicinity killed a
security guard and damaged a support building. Russia partly constructed the Bushar nuclear
plant in Iran and helps operate it. Iran says the plant's been attacked four times since the
war began. The International Atomic Energy Agency has expressed deep concern and is called for
de-escalation. The World Health Organization has also raised the alarm, saying in a
statement, the latest incident involving the Bushar nuclear power plant is a stark reminder
that a strike could trigger a nuclear accident with health impacts that would devastate generations.
With every passing day of this escalating conflict, the stakes and the threats are
raised higher and higher. We must de-escalate now. Peace is the best medicine. Well joining
us now, we have Akshay Dioras. He's a research scientist at the University of
Reddy. Thank you very much indeed for being with us. If a strike was to hit, say a nuclear reactor
or a storage used for nuclear fuel, what would happen?
So I think it's very important to keep in mind that, you know, nuclear reactors are designed
to be safe and this particular reactor in Bushar has been hit four times in the past since
since two months but so far there has not been any major radiation leak as such. If you assume
a really worst-case scenario that the strike is really bad and it starts creating problems,
the very first thing that's going to happen is that areas around the nuclear power plant will
be impacted because the radioactive stuff will start getting into the air, it will also start
getting into the water and it will not be an area where people can live because it will just
create damage to their health and eventually what really would matter is how much this radioactive
stuff is able to spread further but we don't know that at the moment. Let's talk about the spread
though because that is something that clearly is concerning a lot of the Gulf nations that are on
the opposite side of the Gulf to the Boucher nuclear plant. In the event that there was a
strike and there was a significant enough shall we say radiation leak what would be the outcome
of that how would the environment in and around the Gulf be affected? Yeah so if you assume that the
strike is really bad everything fails the reactor gives up, cooling systems fail and there's a lot
of radiation leakage but like I said you know the very first thing that's just going to happen
is that radioactive stuff will get into the air that could be isotopes of iodine or cesium
they will also get into water which means that the water is not going to remain
safe for any operations be in desalination or even the marine life is going to be impacted over there
for people the very first thing is like those living near the reactor they need to they will
have to evacuate because the air will really become toxic and if it starts spreading further like you
know just talking about countries surrounding the Persian Gulf so if the leakage is really
strong then I would say there will be some impact but that would be mainly through water
when it comes to countries like Qatar and Kuwait because of the distance between Iran and these
countries and that does rather imply that if the water does become affected by radio activity
that of course is going to affect the ability of the desalination of plants to actually deal
with that because if I understand it correctly the the ability of desalination plants broadly
is fairly limited when it comes to trying to filter out radiation from water are we looking
at a scenario here where the water is going to become almost impossible to use that could happen
but again that is just going to be a situation when it's really really bad at the moment even
if you assume that strikes happen and there is a bit of you know leakage of radioactive stuff
it will still not end up being really that bad so as to really paralyze
the entire desalination system so all the impacts are going to be across the region
itself like across parts of Iran and what happens after that would really depend on how
intense that strike is. I'm going to ask you about the global response to the potential threats to
the Bashar nuclear plant now there has been a global response of course to Russia's attacks on the
Zaporizhia plant in Ukraine during the war Russia's war on Ukraine what is your assessment of the
way that the world is responding to the potential threat to Bashar? I think the world is reacting
and responding in a very proper manner because now we also have got statement from the WHO that
you know this is really a situation that needs to be monitored because you know it's not just about
let's say the marine life getting impacted or even public health getting impacted the problem is
that you know these things if they continue to escalate the impact is just going to continue
forever and just keeping aside the nuclear reactor at the moment we have already seen
lots of strikes on oil facilities in Iran and for example last month itself on the 8th of March
people in Tehran woke up to black rate and there has to be a lot of smoke and all different cocktails
of Hazard and stuff in the air that is already getting into let's say the bodies of people
over there so it's just a very bad cocktail of all different I would say environmental hazards
and implications that all these attacks are causing. I really appreciate you joining us
and Al Jazeera giving us the benefit of your expertise in this actually a deal thank you very
much indeed well in Lebanon the Israeli army has carried out new strikes on Beirut's southern suburb
in a densely populated residential area at least four people have been killed 39 others have been
injured in those strikes it says it's continuing attacks on Hezbollah military infrastructure
more than a million people have been forcibly displaced across the country.
Heidi Petz live for us now in Beirut Heidi what are you learning about what was hit in Beirut
and this time were there any warnings given ahead of time? Yes so the majority of strikes that
hit Beirut's southern suburbs today which was eight strikes beginning shortly after midday
were in areas that are covered by these rolling forced evacuation orders by the Israeli military
which as you mentioned have left more than a million people displaced in the country but
one later this afternoon on a suburb called Jena it's a densely populated very busy
urban residential area that one came in with no warning there was no no evacuation order
issued for that one and the civilian toll has been enormous we've just had some figures come
in from the Lebanese Ministry of Health that confirmed that five people were killed in
that strike including a 15 year old girl and three Sudanese nationals and that more than and
that 52 people were wounded now MSF said that that strike hit just meters from a hospital where
they operate and they described a chaotic mass casualty event with people you know carrying
in the wounded on their shoulders and that it was just an absolutely enormous disaster for
people in this very densely packed civilian area now in the last couple of hours there have
been further strikes on Beirut one of these hit in a Christian area called Ainsadeh it appears
have been another attempted Israeli assassination attempt where they hit one apartment in a residential
building they were apparently targeting the third floor but the build that apartment was empty at
the time but the floor collapsed and has killed three people on the second floor including a local
leader from the Lebanese forces which is a right-wing Christian party here and we've seen
statements from his colleagues and other MPs from the local area stressing their concerns about
sheltering displaced people in their neighborhoods calling for further checks and it's really raised
the the level of tension here in Beirut and also the level of fear which has been on for some some
weeks now about sheltering displaced people and Heidi we've got to remember of course the
attacks aren't just happening in southern Lebanon they're also have excuse me in southern Beirut
they're also happening in southern Lebanon how are these attacks affecting
Hezbollah's operations there and of course the people in the south of the country
yeah so since this war reignited about a month ago Israel has been systematically destroying
bridges across the Lattani River they've destroyed eight nine of them so far in fact including one
couple of days ago just south of the Bekar Valley so they've destroyed bridges on major
highways right near the Mediterranean Sea linking the city of Tyre to the rest of the country
and we saw two further airstrikes very close to the remaining bridge on that road in fact
earlier today and so what this has done is it's had the effect of isolating southern
Lebanon from the rest of the country Israel says the reason it's hitting these bridges
is to stop Hezbollah from moving men and weapons back and forth but the impact on civilians
and there are many thousands of civilians who have remained in southern Lebanon they are
defying these forced evacuation orders issued by the Israeli military and speaking to aid
organizations in the last couple weeks they are increasingly concerned about their ability
to provide food and medicine to these people Israel has said that it would target any large
trucks moving on the postal highways and it also makes it a lot more difficult for people to you
know to move around to get to hospitals if they need to or indeed if there are fresh forced
evacuation orders issued it makes it more difficult for people to even obey them
Heidi Perth they're live for us in Beirut thank you all Israel's forced evacuation orders
that Heidi was just talking about have forced hundreds of thousands of people out of their
houses in southern Lebanon tire resident Jamal Saleem Farhan says he won't leave his home despite
repeated Israeli bombings
a major border crossing between Lebanon and Syria has been closed until further notice
after warnings of an imminent Israeli strike around 10,000 people usually pass through the
al-masnah crossing every day Israel says the crossing is being used to smuggle weapons to his
baller the Lebanese government denies that claim due to Israeli security threats at the
masnah border crossing we closed it from our side we've suspended the movement of passengers
entering and exiting the Jadid Yabuz border crossing we also halted the flow of incoming
and outgoing cargo trucks although it is a humanitarian crossing that provides humanitarian
services for the movement of travelers entering and exiting the country it also handles commercial
traffic for incoming and outgoing cargo it is not used for any type of military purpose
Senegal is limiting government ministers travel abroad to reduce costs as the energy crisis
deepens Prime Minister Osman Sonko says the budget was based on oil at 62 dollars a barrel
the prices have nearly doubled because of the Iran war Nicholas Huck reports from the capital
Dakar like much of the world the war is affecting the price of petrol and that's affecting
transporters including taxi drivers here but it doesn't stop here we're in a popular market
in the capital Dakar and this has become the unexpected frontline of the war why well because
much of the food that you see in the market here is imported and when the streets of Hormuz
is choking well the economies here are gasping for air because all of these produce that comes
from various regions or various countries well there's transport costs and that means that
the prices have shot up and it's not just food it's also the price of fertilizer that
comes from the gulf and china and so in a country where most are farmers this is badly
affecting the economy so what is the government of senegal doing about it senegal's 2026 budget
was based on the idea that the barrel of crude oil would be around 60 dollars now it shot up
above a hundred dollars so the government is introducing restrictive measures starting with
cabinet members and the prime minister himself halting any travel abroad but that's just
one small step because there's more to come with this war thousands of kilometers away
reshaping the economies here many people hear fear that they have become victims to this conflict
Nicholas Hawke Al Jazeera the car well the conflict is having far-reaching effects Indian
administered Kashmir relies heavily on handicrafts thousands of people work in the industry
but their livelihoods are at risk at least because half the goods are sold in the Middle East
with the region stuck in a war orders have been delayed or cancelled in the Abu Akhle reports
the Kotas are one of thousands of families who have been part of kashmir's craft industry for
generations they spin yarn from the wool of Himalayan Chang Thangi goats on traditional
hand looms creating pashmina scarves pashmina is not just work for us it's our legacy and identity
i am one of the thousands of women who hand spin the yarn and this spinning is the backbone of our
livelihood however their income is in jeopardy the family has reduced production using only
two of their four hand looms that's because at least 50 percent of kashmir's handicrafts
are sold to the Middle East and the regional conflict has led to cancellations
this is impacting us a lot the work is minimal about 90 less than usual
Tausif Bhatt also comes from a family of pashmina makers but now runs a company
employing around 60 people if the situation remains the same and the conflict continues
i think we may eventually have to shut down the business the kashmir chamber of commerce says
it's not only a lack of orders that is a problem but the cost of sending anything has risen
astronomically nobody can send the shipments because we have the airline problems we have the
by sea if there are problems and i would rather say 400 000 people are affected with this war
that's a lot of families at risk of losing their livelihoods
going to take a look at some of the world's other news now and the Gaza Strip Hama says it
will not hand over its weapons disarmament is part of the second phase of the Gaza ceasefire plan
but the armed group says calls to lay down its weapons are unacceptable especially as Palestinians
continue to be targeted by Israel more than 700 people have been killed since the ceasefire came
into effect in october as for raising the issue of weapons in this crude manner it has
nothing but a scandalous attempt by the occupation to continue killing and genocide against our people
which we will not accept under any circumstances we affirm that what the enemy was unable to seize
from us with tanks and genocide it will not seize from us with politics or at the negotiation
table the occupation's aggression against our people and its continued closure of the blessed
al-Aqsa mosque to worshipers in an unprecedented manner and the approval of the law for
executing Palestinian prisoners we call upon the masses of our Palestinian people in the brave
west bank the blessed Jerusalem and the occupied interior to march toward al-Aqsa mosque moan
robani is a non-resident fellow at the center for conflict and humanitarian studies he says
Hama statement confirms the talks to implement the second phase of the Gaza ceasefire plan
deadlocked what Hamas informed the mediators is that it will not discuss issues such as
disarmament relating to the second phase of the plan for the Gaza Strip until the items of the
first phase are implemented that includes a cessation of hostilities as you noted virtual
daily Israeli attacks on the Gaza Strip have resulted in more than 700 Palestinians killed
humanitarian aid continues to be restricted and most notably this national committee for the
administration of the Gaza Strip which was established by the board of peace continues
to be prohibited from entering the Gaza Strip by the Israelis and the board of peace is doing
absolutely nothing to ensure its ability to get in and so I think Hamas is taking two positions a
it won't discuss the second phase until the first phase is properly implemented and b when those
discussions do take place it's not going to simply surrender its weapons unless Israel clearly
meets its own obligations as well and those are obligations that have to be consistent
not just with what the board of peace wants but with the international consensus and the rulings of
the international court of justice that this is an illegal occupation that must end for hundreds
of thousands of Palestinians made homeless by Israel's war on Gaza every day is a struggle
as bombed out neighborhoods are so slowly cleared of rubble some families are collecting scrap metal
to survive and in Ahmad reports from Gaza city trucks arrive one after another offloading what
remains of homes shops and entire streets across large part of Gaza rubble removal continues
month after Israeli bombardment flat in entire neighborhoods but for some these dumping grounds
are more than just fields of debris they are workplaces children search the mountains of broken
concrete and twisted metal for anything they can sell wood copper wire aluminum each piece they
collect means a few more coins each truck brings another opportunity and another risk the ground
is unstable sharp edges from broken walls aid agents is worn unexploded ordinance may still be
buried beneath the debris is an abdel al lives in a tent near one of the dumping sites we come
here hoping to earn 20 shuckles about six dollars but it comes at a cost injuries exhaustion cuts
everywhere you can see the wounds and the blood the war has left hundreds of thousands of families
without stable income factories are shut shops are gone entire businesses reduced to dust post war
recovery is measured by reconstruction in plans funding and pledges but here on the ground recovery
looks different it looks like its children navigating the rubble household depending on
the fragments of what was destroyed as long as livelihood is remains absent and reconstruction
uncertain the rubble will continue to serve two purposes one reminder of loss and for some people
it is a means of survival informal scrap collection has become one of the few ways to
earn cash we come here to earn money for food my father has no work so we have to come
we come here hoping to find bits of woods or pieces of cable that we can sell anything that
may help us buy food for our children we know climbing onto the moving trucks is dangerous
but when your family depends on it you take the risk
The parents say they don't want their children here, but survival leaves little room for a
choice.
Hani Mahmoud Al-Jazeera from Gaza City, Palestine.
Serbia says powerful explosives have been found near a pipeline that carries Russian gas
to Hungary.
Authorities say the discovery was made outside of Serbia in town near the Hungarian border.
It comes just a week before closely watched elections in Hungary.
Prime Minister Viktor Orban is fighting to extend his 16 years in power.
He's linked Ukraine to those explosives.
For years, Ukraine has been working to cut Europe off from Russian energy.
They blew up Nord Stream, shut down the gas pipeline supplying Hungary, and this year placed
Hungary under an oil blockade by closing the Družba pipeline.
The Russian section of the Turkstream is also under continuous military attack.
Ukraine's efforts pose a life-threatening danger to Hungary.
Kiev's rejected Orban's accusations, posting on X, the foreign ministry spokesman has said
Ukraine's got nothing to do with this.
Most probably, it's a Russian false flag operation, despite Moscow's heavy interference
in Hungarian elections.
As Christians around the world mark the Easter holiday under the shadow of war, religious
leaders are calling for peace.
Sonya Gallego reports.
It is the most important date in the Christian calendar, marked this year by both tradition
and tension.
Addressing more than a billion Catholics worldwide from the Vatican, Pope Leo led his first
Easter Mass as pontiff.
And the message from St Peter's Square was shaped by events far beyond it.
Death is always lurking.
We see it present in injustices, in partisan selfishness, in the oppression of the poor, in
the lack of attention given to the most vulnerable.
We see it in violence, in the wounds of the world, in the cry of pain that rises from
every corner because of the abuses that crush the weakest.
An appeal for mercy as the conflict in the Middle East loomed over what is meant
to be a celebration of renewal, where despite airstrikes and destruction, many felt the need
to commemorate the holiday.
Over the weekend, the message resonated in Germany in the annual Easter March in Cologne,
not a religious procession, but a demand for an end to hostilities.
And in France, as the bells of Notre Dame in Paris rang out, calling worshippers to
mass.
In Lyon, thousands of adults were baptized.
A sign said church leaders of the search for meaning in an evermore uncertain world.
Sonia Gallego, Al Jazeera.
I'll be back in a couple of minutes.
I'm Rob Matheson.
Stay with us on Al Jazeera.
The latest news as it breaks.
According to reports, Donald Trump is keen to end this war in order to try to regain
some of the popularity which he has lost because of this war.
With live coverage, Trump's frustration with NATO now seems as hot as ever, goading them
into action in the Strait of Hormuz, particularly France and the United Kingdom.
From the heart of the story, many Republicans are saying that a ground operation is the
only way to finish this war.
We bomb a political future into existence.
I don't think that's what we're trying to do.
I think the objective here is to destroy the instruments of Iranian state power.
Let me ask you this directly.
Is Israel effectively leading US foreign policy?
They want to do a Gaza-like effort on the main power centers in Iran to kill thousands
of people, not just the court.
Up front tackles the big issues only on Al Jazeera.
Examining the impact of today's headlines, setting the agenda for tomorrow's discussions.
International filmmakers and world-class journalists bring programs to inform and inspire you on
Al Jazeera.
This is Al Jazeera live from Doha with our continuing coverage of the war between the
US, Israel and Iran.
I'm Rob Matheson, coming up in the next 60 minutes.
Donald Trump sets a Tuesday deadline for Iran to reopen the Strait of Hormuz.
All the US will bomb its power plants, its bridges and, quote, unleash hell.
We are determined to defend.
Iran's foreign ministry dismisses the US president's warning and violates a swift retaliation to
any US attacks.
US troops rescue a second airman in a high-stakes mission in Iran two days after his fighter
jet went down.
And rescuers in the northern Israeli city of Haifa look for the missing after an Iranian
strike targets an apartment complex four people are injured.
In the Iran war squeezes global economies.
Workers are the worst hit.
Weavers in Indian administrative Kashmir say orders for the famed Pashmina Shoals have
dried up.
You know, as President Donald Trump has renewed threats to destroy Iranian power plants and
bridges if it doesn't reopen the Strait of Hormuz.
He's shared what appears to be a deadline on social media, Tuesday, 8 p.m. Eastern
time.
Earlier, Trump posted an expletive laden threat to his truth social account.
He promised that Iranians would be, quote, living in hell if the Strait isn't reopened.
Tehran has emphasized that it's going to retaliate if struck.
Foreign ministry spokesman Esmeralda Bakheri says any US-related location in the Middle
East would be a target.
Our armed forces have made it clear that in case Iran's infrastructure is attacked,
we would react in kind.
They would, our armed forces, would target any similar infrastructure that is owned or
in any way or manner related to the United States or contributes to their act of aggression
against Iran.
And that says missile strikes pound areas across the region.
An Iranian missile struck this residential building in the northern Israeli port city
of Haifa hours ago, and Israeli attacks are bombarding the southern suburbs in
the Lebanese capital of Beewood.
Now, we're going to be alive from Tehran in a moment.
First, Al Jazeera's Mike Hanna has more on President Trump's comments from Washington,
D.C.
The unusual use of an expletive by a national leader, perhaps a symbol of President Trump's
frustration with the Iranian government and their refusal to concede to the demands
that he is making.
That reference as well was to the Strait of Hamouz, which in recent days President
Trump had insisted he did not care about saying the U.S. did not need the oil passing
through the Strait, and it was up to the countries who are reliant on that oil to deal
with the situation.
But now the demand about opening the Strait of Hamouz appears front and center of the
President's new demands of the Iranian government.
President Trump threatening to, and I use his words, blowing everything and taking
the oil if Iran does not meet his new deadline, which has now been set at 8 p.m. Eastern Time
on Tuesday evening.
He says in an earlier media post that a power plant day and bridge day all wrapped up
on Tuesday.
But on the other hand, in addition to these threats, President Trump is sending signals
that there's some kind of negotiation process underway.
He's indicated that his close confidants Jared Kushner and Stephen Whitcoff are in consultation
with either the Iranian government and identified figures or some form of intermediary.
And speaking to U.S. news outlets, President Trump says that he is optimistic that there
can be an agreement very soon.
He says the agreement could come within a matter of days rather than a matter of
weeks.
And you've got this dichotomous approach from the President on the one hand threatening
obliteration to civilian targets within Iran, which some observers would contend to be a war
crime.
But on the other hand, what he is saying is, yes, we are talking.
The talks are going well, and they could come to fruition before that new deadline
I set, which is 8 p.m. Eastern Time on Tuesday.
Mike Hanna, Al Jazeera, Washington.
The Speaker of Iran's parliament, Mohamed Balhar Ghalibaf, has also responded to Donald Trump
saying your reckless moves are dragging the United States into a living hell for every
single family, and our whole region is going to burn because you insist on following Netanyahu's
commands.
Make no mistake, you won't gain anything through war crimes.
I'm going to bring in Mohamed Valh in tech rounds.
So the Speaker of Iran's parliament accusing Donald Trump of war crimes, what else is
Iran saying?
Yeah, Rob, there is a lot of statements by many Iranian leaders today, including the one
you mentioned, also the spokesman for the foreign ministry, who gave a long statement
and also a long explanation of why this war is wrong, why this war is illegal, and why
it is imposed, or how it is imposed on the Iranians and also on many other people
in the region, and even on the Americans.
He said this war is based on lies.
The lie that Iran is pursuing nuclear weapons, the line that Iran presents an imminent threat
to the United States, and the lie that this war is meant, among other things, to help
the Iranian people gain freedom from a regime that the Americans consider despotic and so
on.
So he's also saying that these intimidations or these attempts at intimidating Iran will
not work, that Iran is not going to change its course of action and its approach towards
the state of Hormuz.
And about also the state of Hormuz, the IRGC spokesman also said that the state of Hormuz
is not about to be subjected to any kind of change in its status, as far as Iranians
are concerned.
It's not going to return to the previous status.
It's going to be used by Iran in the future.
It's going to be controlled.
And it's going to be used to compensate Iran for the destruction that have been inflicted
on the country since the beginning of this war.
So there will be fees.
That's not what, I mean he didn't say this specifically, but that's what they have been
saying by way of explanation of how they are going to proceed regarding the state
of Hormuz in the future.
So it's not about to be open, particularly to the Americans and the Israelis.
It is open to other countries, the countries that are not participating in this war
against Iran.
But also in the future it is going to remain under a sort of control by Iran and it is going
to be a source of income to compensate the loss that Iran has been subjected to during
this war.
And Mohamed, we've been hearing of attacks in Boucher province.
It's worth remembering, of course, that's where the Boucher nuclear power plant is.
Tell us more about the attacks that have been happening across Iran.
Yes, Rob, there is a long list of cities.
As particularly the airport has been bombarded today, Mahshahr city.
We have also Bandar-Lenge, we have Kong city.
Those are in the south where 17 people were wounded, six were killed in those two cities
Bandar-Lenge and Kong city.
We have Shiraz, Isfahan, Karaj, Tehran as usual, these cities, all of these cities
have been bombarded today.
But also let's focus on Boucher a little bit because it's the most sensitive place
actually that has been hit today.
It's the fifth time that is targeted.
And that's where the reactor, the only reactor that is functioning in Iran.
It includes a lot of radioactive material in it that there is the risk of exploding
that radioactive material, which is going to cause a huge catastrophe across the region.
Boucher is located not far from many of the Gulf countries.
And also it's on the Iranian side of the Gulf.
So, I mean, there is a lot of warnings.
Even the IAEA has been warning that this reactor shouldn't be targeted again.
The Russians also are very much concerned because they have some experts there in the facility.
So it's really, really a subject of concern to many people, not only Iran,
but also even across the world.
Mohammad Val in Tehran, thank you very much indeed.
Well, earlier I spoke to two experts about the U.S.'s position in the war with Iran.
Kenneth Kasman is a Middle East policy analyst, is also senior fellow at the Sufan Center,
and Alex Fatanka is a senior fellow at the Middle East Institute.
He's also the author of the book, The Battle of the Ayatollahs in Iran,
the United States foreign policy and policy rivalry.
Here's some of our conversation, starting with Alex Fatanka's thoughts
on President Trump's latest threat.
We haven't heard this kind of language before.
It's a surprise, frankly, even for President Trump to speak in such a tone.
But, you know, it's probably nothing more than an expression of his frustration.
He's kind of boxed in. He doesn't know which way to go.
He really doesn't want to escalate militarily.
He really wants to have the Strait of Hormuz opened up.
And he really wants to get a bigger deal with the Iranian side if he could.
And he's not going to get there by adopting this sort of language.
And we've heard from the Iranians already they're kind of dismissing the language.
They're pointing to the fact that this seems to be Donald Trump expressing frustration
and not laying any sort of signpost for how we can move forward from here
if the diplomatic track should have any chance to succeed at all.
Although President Trump, as we've also heard,
is claiming the diplomatic track is still very much alive,
but it just doesn't seem to be sitting nicely next to the language
that he's been using the last couple of days.
Yeah, Kenneth Azanis was just referring to there.
He said Donald Trump was also talking to, I think it was Fox News about this.
He took a very different tone when he's talking to them.
He was saying the negotiating track was still open,
that I understand that some of the Iranian negotiators
had been given some sort of amnesty in order
while they were doing, carrying out the talks.
How difficult is it, do you think, for whoever is doing the negotiations
at the moment within the leadership of Iran
to be able to identify what message Donald Trump is actually sending?
Yeah, I think it's very difficult.
And you know, we have very clear divisions within the Iranian regime
that are emerging now, and that makes it even more difficult
because some of the regime interpreted his comments
to be somewhat willing to compromise,
and others view it, they would probably look at the statement today
with the curses as, you know, very disparaging
and not something they want to, they feel they can negotiate with.
But I think it's instructive to look at an article
that former Foreign Minister Zarif issued this week,
which was basically, I read it as a message to the hardliners
in his own country, in the regime, saying, you know,
you guys need to figure out a way to settle this with Mr. Trump
before you get us all killed.
And I think it was a very, very important article that bears reading,
and he lays out some steps that could potentially form the basis
of a successful negotiation, possibly.
Alex, throughout all of the negotiations
or the putative negotiations that apparently have been going forward,
Iran has invariably called the demands
by the Trump administration as maximalist.
And those are also allegations
that the administration has made against Iran as well.
Is there any position that Iran would be able to take
in these negotiations, Alex, in order for it to be able
to move forward to some sort of diplomatic solutions,
at least start some sort of negotiation,
but at the same time retain some sort of control over its sovereignty
and its national interests?
You know, the basic reality is that United States could tomorrow,
President Trump tomorrow could declare victory
and walk away from this and say he brought
about regime change that is destroyed so much of Iran
that Iran set back 10, 15 years.
I mean, he has that capacity or that option
to declare victory.
The Iranian side, for them, this war isn't one
that they're going to win militarily.
They've never said they're going to win militarily
against the United States.
For them, strategic victory is if you bleed the United
States, that you make the cost of another war so high
that the United States and partner states are never
going to try that again.
That's what victory looks like there.
But look, even in that kind of a best case scenario,
both sides decide, you know, let's just call it a day
and walk away.
Where is the region going to be at?
Where particularly the Gulf states,
whose economies depend on the idea of stability,
invest the confidence.
What's going to happen to them?
Iran could choose not to want to invest in its economy.
The rest of the neighborhood wants to invest in their economy.
They're thinking of post-oil economies.
They can't sit in a situation where you're basically
in a limbo.
So, you know, you have to hope if the diplomatic track,
which by the way is not the only track,
but this is the one track, that the two sides soften
their positions.
You know, Ken was talking about Zarif's article.
Now, Zarif is already being threatened with execution
in Tehran, for having written that article.
This just shows you in Tehran,
they're not speaking with one voice.
But I agree with Ken.
If the Iranians are going to find a way out of this,
they need to get their voices around the idea that,
you know, now they've made their point,
if that's what they want to call it,
now maybe look for that off-ramp,
because I think the American president too
might be open to soften this position,
despite what he might be saying in social posts
that we've seen in recent days.
Kenneth, is there an allegation
that could be brought against the Iranian leadership
that they, because of the level of response
that they have been able to show in reaction
to the attacks from Israel and from the US,
that they might be running the risk
of being overconfident in this.
And by digging in, they're actually creating a situation
where they are forcing the US,
forcing Donald Trump to exacerbate the situation,
when in fact, if it just took a little bit of a rethinking,
if you like, as Alex was referring to,
just a rethinking of their stance,
that there might be a way of de-escalating this.
That's exactly what I was saying before,
and that's exactly what Zareev's article was saying,
is that if you guys continue down this road
and keep provoking Trump,
he is gonna blow up civilian sites,
he is gonna have a ground offensive,
and you're gonna get us all killed.
So you need to find a way out of this.
That's exactly what Zareev is saying.
Trump is...
open to a negotiation. Mr. Choep, where I might differ though, is Mr. Choep cannot go to the American
people and say and call it quits with the Strait of Hormuz closed. He must as a minimum have that
waterway that Choep points fully open for free passage. He could not realistically explain
to the American people why he entered into this conflict and ends it up with the Strait of
Hormuz closed. I think that is just a non-starter politically for Trump.
Alex, I just want to go back to a point that Ken was making earlier that the divisions that we're
seeing within the leadership inside Iran as well. Now they're not particularly public, but we are
led to believe that those differences, shall we say, of opinion and differences of approach
are there. How much of an issue is that going to be should we get to the point where negotiations
of some sort can begin? You know that takes us to the issue of whether the United States had a
bigger strategy to begin with. Before this war started, if the United States wanted to sort of,
if you will, empower those people inside the regime that believe in the idea of diplomacy,
what did the United States or Israel for that matter do to empower them, if anything? I mean,
are we, for example, seeing some of these continued assassination of Iranian officials to
be part of that game plan where you're sort of taking a particular faction out of the equation
in order to empower moderates who want to come back to diplomacy? I haven't seen a systematic kind
of clear evidence that that's happening, but that, if that was the case, that seems pretty solid
sound. But as of today, five, six weeks into this war, the IRGC commanders, the first generation
commanders who have been together since 1979 are running the show. And as of today, they
don't seem to believe diplomacy is what they want. They don't think the American side is going to
give them anything that is not going to be short of humiliating. They want, they don't want to be
humiliated. You hear this constantly coming around Iran. They want their dignity preserved.
But others like Zarif are saying, well, you're dead, then the dignity is no good for you. And
that's basically the fight into Iran, as far as I can tell. Well, the threat of escalation
in Iran puts the Gulf region squarely in the crossfire. The sites Iran is threatening to hit
are almost entirely located in GCC countries, which are already coping with daily attacks.
Kuwait says it's been hit by a series of drone attacks. Authorities report two major power and
desalination plants have been targeted. One of the facilities is in Al-Sour. It's nearly 90
kilometers south of Kuwait city. Another attack has hit the finance ministry complex,
and that building is in central Kuwait city. In Bahrain, Iran is targeted and oil facilities
sparking several fires. Emergency response teams said the blaze had been fully extinguished.
Over the past few weeks, Manama has come under repeated Iranian missile and drone attacks.
Mohammad Jamjoum is in the Qatari capital, Doha. So the attacks in Gulf countries in the last
24 hours, they're now having to prepare for an escalation if Donald Trump carries out his
threats, Mohammad. Yeah, that's right, Rob. And last you and I spoke, I was telling you
about the fact that we were hearing reports emanating from Kuwait, saying that there were
sirens that were heard throughout Kuwait city, and that it looked as though they were
dealing with more attacks launched from Iran towards Kuwait. There has been a statement
put out by the Defense Ministry in Kuwait saying that Kuwait is in fact dealing with
hostile missile and drone attacks at this hour. We will get you more details as they
emerge. That's the last we've heard officially from any Kuwaiti government spokespeople.
Now, beyond that, as you said, we are at this pivotal moment now, Rob, where we know that
the deadline that's been imposed by Donald Trump, 8 p.m. Tuesday, as Donald Trump has said in his
post on social media, for Iran to fully reopen the Strait of Hormuz. Otherwise,
as he has said in other posts, all hell will rain down on Iran. Now, that is so concerning for
these Gulf countries, because Iran has stated in the past that if the U.S. is to go after
energy infrastructure power sites in Iran, water facilities that they, the Iranians, will then
target facilities like that in these countries in the Gulf region. That's where things are right
now. People are wondering what exactly is going to happen next. And this coming specifically at a
time when you've seen these attacks that have happened from Iran towards Kuwait, in which
petrochemical plants, energy infrastructure sites, desalination sites, not just in Kuwait,
other countries in the Gulf region as well. Those have been happening more and more over
the course of the past month. Now, everybody wondering if Trump is to follow through on his
threat to Iran. What's going to happen when it comes to these countries? This is a pivotal moment
coming at a time when nerves very much on edge. The posture from these Gulf countries has been
a defensive one up until now. They said they do not want to escalate. They want to de-escalate.
The question is, what happens if Iran does strike out in retaliation for any attacks
that the U.S. might impose on Iran? What happens to the Gulf countries? And then what will the Gulf
countries do in response? Yeah, Mohammad, central to all of this is the Strait of Hormuz. Now Iran
says the Strait of Hormuz is open. It's been holding meetings with the Manis. What do we
know about those meetings? Well, what we've heard from the Omanis is that there was a meeting
that took place on Saturday. Some details emerged on Sunday, that this was a meeting that
took place at the deputy foreign minister level, that there were experts involved as well,
that the Omanis and the Iranians want to try to allow for smooth passage of ships in the Strait of
Hormuz and that options were being discussed. Certainly, that's a lot more questions of this
hour than answers, because we don't know what those options are. And the fact of the matter is,
even if those are options that are agreed to by the Omanis and the Iranians,
would the Americans agree to that? If the Americans don't agree, are they going to
escalate their attacks on Iran? Also, of course, beyond what the Americans think,
you have to factor in what other GCC countries may think. We've heard again and again
from countries in this region, countries around the world, that they want to see the Strait of
Hormuz fully reopened. Now, in the course of the past 48, 72 hours, we have heard reports
of more ships that have been able to transit, to navigate the Strait of Hormuz. Some of those
ships Asian, some of those ships European. So, there is a question as to how many ships
might now be able to navigate the Strait of Hormuz going forward? Which countries may
be speaking to the Iranians to try to get their ships through? That's very much an open question
right now, too. But the fact of the matter is, the Omanis, the Iranians, they want to try to
allow for more passes of ships. But what options exactly are on the table? When will
they be announced? Will it be before this deadline has been imposed by Donald Trump
to reopen the Strait of Hormuz? What exactly happens next? That's, again, Rob,
why we are at this critical holding pattern at this hour.
Mohammad Jumjum in the Qatari capital, Doha. Mohammad, thank you.
While a U.S. airman has been rescued in Iran after an intense 48-hour search operation,
the Weapons Systems Officer had been missing since Friday when the fighter jet he was in
went down in the province of Khoriloy and Boyar Ahmad.
Dehran said it shot down the F-15E to two-seater aircraft. The pilot was rescued shortly
afterwards. John Hendren reports from Washington, D.C.
It was a daring and risky mission to save an American airman from becoming an Iranian prisoner
of war. Iranian forces searched the mountainous areas of southwestern Iran after an F-15E fighter
jet went down on Friday. It was the first time a U.S. aircraft had crashed in hostile territory
in the five-week-old war. Two Blackhawk helicopters took fire as U.S. teams raced
to find the missing crew member. An A-10 Warthog, an air support aircraft, was also damaged,
its pilot ejecting over the Gulf. Iran broadcast photos of what it said was debris from the
fighter jet, including a jump seat. Although the pilot had been rescued on Friday,
the weapons specialist remained in hiding, evading Iranian forces for two days.
Finally, early on Sunday, deep in Iranian territory, the U.S. search operation was
successful. President Donald Trump made the announcement on social media, posting,
We Got Him, saying the colonel had been behind enemy lines in the treacherous mountains of
Iran being hunted by our enemies. He said U.S. forces had been monitoring his location 24 hours a
day and sent dozens of aircraft armed with the most lethal weapons in the world to retrieve him.
Trump added, He sustained injuries, but he will be just fine.
A U.S. official told Al Jazeera the rescue operation began in darkness but ended in an
intense firefight and daylight, before dozens of heavily armed aircraft and hundreds of troops
transported the airmen out of Iran. A U.S. officer in Iranian custody could have given
Iran leverage, as it had when Iran took U.S. hostages in 1979. With that crisis averted,
attention now shifts to the U.S. deadline for Iran to open the Strait of Hormuz.
John Hendron, Al Jazeera, Washington.
Well, as John was just talking about, U.S. officials said the rescue mission involved
several aircraft. Iranian state media released these pictures, reportedly showing the wreckage
of a C-130 aircraft in Isfahan province. American media are reporting that U.S. forces
destroyed at least one of their own planes on purpose because it had become stuck and unable
to fly out. Iranian armed forces dispute those series of events, claiming its soldiers destroyed
two C-130 aircraft and two Black Hawk helicopters in what it characterized as a failed U.S. rescue
operation. With God's help and support and through the vigilance and readiness of the
fighters of Islam in the armed forces using electronic warfare, advanced new air defense
systems, the implementation of a ground mosaic defense plan and the creation of a military
and security cordon, a number of these aircraft, including two C-130 military transport planes
and two Black Hawk helicopters, were hit and forced to make emergency landings in an area
south of Isfahan. After Iranian Islamic fighters completed the operation to encircle the enemy
in order to prevent the disgrace of Trump, the President of the United States,
in the hollow prestige of the army, was forced to carry out heavy bombing of its downed
aircraft, equipment, commanders and soldiers. Simon Mail is a retired British Army general
and a former Middle East advisor at the UK Ministry of Defense. He explains how this
rescue operation unfolded. An F-15 has two aircrew, obviously a pilot and a weapons officer.
The Colonel rescued his, the weapons officer, he'll be the back seat
for those who watched Top Gun, that is the Goose, as opposed to Maverick Post,
and when the aircraft is hit, obviously both eject. What was interesting is the
pilot ejected and was found relatively quickly and was rescued and the weapons officer was not.
They would have landed inevitably a good distance probably from each other.
They'd both have transponders, they'd know pretty quickly where they'd landed.
They'd be a transponder probably in the ejector seat. I'm not an airman, I'm a cavalryman,
armor officer, and clearly on the pilot. Now, in this case of course the pilot, although we
understand to have been wounded or damaged in some way, whether by the ejector or the
strike on the aircraft, will have gone into his escape innovation tactics, which every pilot,
every aircrew is taught is just part of their basic training. And there will be inevitably
any number of films about this, locals will know where it's landed, they'll have seen the parachutes
come down, there will be local police, there may be a local barracks, and all of these have
a certain degree of sheer luck if you're far enough away for them to A, put a distance between
yourself and the ejector seat or the debris of the crashed aircraft, and you can quickly
be located. But even if you're located, you've actually got to be retrieved.
I don't know the circumstances of the pilot being rescued, but this obviously was a man who was,
say, however badly injured, trying to put distance between himself and the aircraft,
the ejector seat. And meanwhile, of course, they will have got drones over him, armed drones,
so they will have had eyes on him in many ways, they would have been able to track him
anyway, but they'll sooner or later have had eyes on him, thermo imaging at night,
visual during the day. But even then, you've got to imagine a net getting closer and closer
around him. And eventually, you've got to put somebody on the ground who can physically lift
him off. And in that, you've got to create a sort of area, sanitized area around him. And
certainly the report does refer to possibly the idea that they put some aircraft on the ground
or helicopters, and that again, they're vulnerable as well. And those may have been hit
while they destroyed them, in which case they'd have trans-shipped crew.
Rescue workers in Israel are searching for people feared trapped under the rubble of a building
hit by an Iranian strike on Haifa. The residential structure partially collapsed after the attack
on Sunday. Israeli authorities say four people have been wounded. One person
is in a critical condition. Well, Rob McBride's following developments
from the Jordanian capital, Amman. Haifa is a strategically important industrial area, Rob.
What do we know about the attack? Yeah, this northern port city, it is very important as an
industrial center. It is also the center for a lot of the oil refining that takes place
in Israel. And consequently, it has often come under attack from missiles from Iran since the
start of this conflict, given its proximity in the north, close to the border with Lebanon.
It also is within range of Hezbollah's rockets and is often under attack by both in
coordinated attacks. On this occasion, the authorities say this was a missile that got
past the missile defensive shield. It landed on the building. And they say it was a heavy warhead
of possibly several hundred kilograms in weight. And there is some speculation at the scene that
this building, which is already close potentially to collapse as they continue to search very
carefully through the nighttime hours for any survivors, that there could be the chance of
unexploded elements and ordinance in the rubble. So that does complicate this effort. It's thought
that there are four people unaccounted for, and they are from the same one apartment
that it was the more heavily damaged in this building. On Sunday, the authorities say that
Israel was subjected to four different salvos of missiles from Iran. One of them saw a
missile landing in the south of the country near the city of Beishiba at the Neyotkhovav
industrial park. Now, this is a very large industrial center for a lot of factories and
production. One of these, the missile that fell there was close to a toxic waste dump. Now,
the authorities say there was no danger of any kind of environmental hazard or leak.
But it is of concern because this whole park has now been hit three times by missiles
since the start of this conflict. The last time was just about a week ago when fragments
started an explosion and fire at a chemical plant. Again, there wasn't any leak of hazardous
material, but it is of concern. And just to finally overall, the authorities say that in
a series of attacks through Sunday, the ambulance service treated a total of 36 people who needed
treatment from these different strikes across Israel through Sunday. Rob, thanks for breaking
that down for us. Rob McBride, right there in Amman. You're watching Al Jazeera, reminder
of our top stories in this hour. US President Donald Trump has renewed his threats to attack
Iran's infrastructure if it doesn't reopen the Strait of Hormuz. He set a deadline of
Tuesday at 8 p.m. Eastern US time. He says US forces are going to strike Iranian power plants
and bridges otherwise. Iran's vow to retaliate if it's attacked. It promises to launch reciprocal
strikes on US linked infrastructure in the Middle East. Iran's parliament speakers also
accused Trump of, quote, war crimes. GCC states face another day of Iranian attacks in
Bahrain and oil tankers caught fire following a drone strike on Sunday and in Kuwait, two power
and water desalination plants were damaged. Qatar has also intercepted several drone and
missile attacks. Russia's state nuclear company says it's evacuated nearly 200 workers from Iran's
Boucher nuclear plant in the south. And that's after a strike near its vicinity killed a
security guard and damaged a support building. Russia partly constructed the Boucher nuclear
plant in Iran and helps operate it. Iran says the plant's been attacked four times since the war began.
The International Atomic Energy Agency has expressed deep concern and called for de-escalation.
The head of the World Health Organization also raised the alarm, saying in a statement,
the latest incident involving the Boucher nuclear power plant is a stark reminder that
a strike could trigger a nuclear accident with health impacts that would devastate
generations. With every passing day of this escalating conflict, the stakes and the threats
are raised higher and higher. We must de-escalate now. Peace is the best medicine.
Akshay Dioras is a research scientist at the University of Reading,
and he says an attack on the Boucher power plant would cause radioactive leakage.
I think it's very important to keep in mind that, you know, nuclear reactors are designed
to be safe, and this particular reactor in Boucher has been hit four times in the past since
two months, but so far, you know, there has not been any major radiation leak as such.
If you assume a really worst-case scenario that the strike is really bad and it starts,
you know, creating problems, the very first thing that's going to happen is that
areas around the nuclear power plant will be impacted because the radioactive
stuff will start getting into the air, it will also start getting into the water,
and it will not be an area where people can live because it will just create damage to their health,
and eventually, what really would matter is how much this radioactive stuff is able to spread
further, but we don't know that at the moment. The first thing that's just going to happen is that
radioactive stuff will get into the air, that could be isotopes of iodine or cesium,
they will also get into water, which means that the water is not going to remain
safe for any operations, be it decentralization or even the marine life is going to be impacted over
there. For people, the very first thing is like those living near the reactor, they need to,
they will have to evacuate because the air will really become toxic, and if it starts spreading
further, like, you know, just talking about countries surrounding the Persian Gulf,
so if the leakage is really strong, then I would say there will be some impact,
but that would be mainly through water when it comes to countries like Qatar
and Kuwait because of the distance between Iran and these countries.
In Lebanon, the Israeli armies carried out new strikes on Beirut's southern suburb in a densely
populated residential area. At least four people have been killed, 39 others have been
injured in the strikes. It says as continuing attacks on Hezbollah military infrastructure,
more than a million people have been forcibly displaced across the country.
They hit a completely civilian area, it's mostly migrants here, Sudanese people, people were
home and they struck them. Are those military objectives? Where is the UN? No one says anything.
Aren't they human too? They're killing children and women. The whole world has to speak up.
It has to see and say something. Have we become nothing but numbers, a people of numbers? How is
that possible? We are devastated. Our morale is low. When you see your friends and neighbours
in pieces on the ground and blood everywhere and the house destroyed,
our house was destroyed. Where are we going to sleep? Where do we go?
Israel's forced evacuation orders have displaced hundreds of thousands of people in southern Lebanon.
Tire resident Salim Farhan says he won't leave his home despite repeated Israeli bombings.
Hello, where are we going? We're going to make a camp and stay in it.
We'll stay on the road. The whole world will show us where we're going.
One day, you'll get in and you'll leave your house and there's no answer.
You'll come and you'll hit the plane. That's the reason.
But we're going to stay on the ground. I want to get out of here. I won't get out.
This is our land. We won't leave it. Of course, we'll stay on the ground.
We'll stay on the ground. We'll stay on the ground. We'll stay on the ground.
Despite the damage, the crash, and the planes. And the weapons of the world.
We'll stay on the ground.
Disruption to shipping through the Strait of Hormuz is reshaping regional energy routes,
with Pakistan emerging as an alternative corridor. But higher costs, tighter fuel availability,
and peak summer demand are placing an increasing strain on energy systems.
Osama bin Javed reports from Karachi Port.
There's a rush to reach Karachi Port. The facility has handled more traffic in a month
than the whole of last year. That's because Pakistan, as Iran's neighbour,
offers some of the first safe seaports as ships exit the Strait of Hormuz.
The crisis comes as Pakistan's preparing for peak summer demand.
It's headed towards a deepening energy crunch across both the power sector
and fuel supply chain. The biggest challenge is liquefied natural gas or LNG,
which accounts for more than 21% of electricity generation.
Officials say supplies could fall to near zero from April.
At the same time, the global energy shock is feeding directly into domestic costs.
Pakistan is operating with just 24 days of gasoline and diesel stocks.
War risk insurance premiums for tankers have surged more than 10-fold.
Fate rates have quadrupled. To manage volatility,
the government has moved to weekly fuel price adjustments.
Industry analysts describe March as the moment Pakistan's energy system was stress test.
It's more severe external shock since the 1970s oil crisis.
Pakistan moved quickly on multiple fronts simultaneously.
Diplomatically, it secured rerouted cargoes through the Red Sea port of Janpo.
Naval escorts kept tankers moving through contested corridors.
Pakistani flag tankers have also passed the Strait with permission from Iran.
It was a very coherent institutional response that operated faster than most observers expected.
Now, a hybrid strategy is in the making to keep the lights on.
It includes limited daily load shedding, compulsory conservation measures,
and higher electricity tariffs.
The government is offering a $7 a month targeted relief
for motorcyclists and wickshaw drivers, even as it increases petroleum levees to manage
fiscal pressure. Oil tankers like these provide the nearly 80% of energy that Pakistan requires
coming from the Strait of Hormuz.
Pakistan says energy, security and diplomacy cannot be separated.
And what it is trying to do is to find common ground between the three spheres
so it can bring some sort of normalcy to the equation.
After hosting regional diplomats, Islamabad is also pushing for wider international engagement,
including with China, to build momentum for de-escalation.
At the same time, Pakistan is trying to turn crisis into opportunity.
Plans are underway for a maritime energy city and new deep-sea ports,
aimed at transforming the country into a regional hub for energy storage and
trans-shipment. But all of it depends on one thing and end to hostilities.
Because until then, Pakistan remains exposed to the conflict
and, as one energy expert stated, putting the oil genie back in the barrel.
Salman Minjavi, Delta Zira, Karachi Port in the Arabian Sea.
And the Middle East conflict is having far-reaching effects,
including having an impact on workers in Indian-administered Kashmir.
The region relies heavily on handicrafts, with thousands of people working in the industry.
But their livelihoods are at risk, because at least half of their goods are sold in the Middle East.
But the region stuck in a war, orders are being delayed or cancelled.
In Abu-Akhle reports.
The Kotas are one of thousands of families
who have been part of Kashmir's craft industry for generations.
They spin yarn from the wool of Himalayan
chang-thangi goats on traditional handlooms, creating Peshmina scarves.
Peshmina is not just work for us, it's our legacy and identity.
I am one of the thousands of women who hand-spin the yarn,
and this spinning is the backbone of our livelihood.
However, their income is in jeopardy.
The family has reduced production, using only two of their four handlooms.
That's because at least 50% of Kashmir's handicrafts
are sold to the Middle East.
And the regional conflict has led to cancellations.
This is impacting us a lot.
The work is minimal, about 90% less than usual.
Tausif Bhatt also comes from a family of Peshmina makers.
But now runs a company employing around 60 people.
If the situation remains the same and the conflict continues,
I think we may eventually have to shut down the business.
The Kashmir Chamber of Commerce says it's not only a lack of orders that is a problem,
but the cost of sending anything has risen astronomically.
That's a lot of families at risk of losing their livelihoods.
In France, rising oil and gas prices are disrupting the fishing industry,
with some boats staying in port, because they can't cover the costs.
The Daeshabata reports from Boulogne-sur-Mer on the north coast of France.
Early morning in the northern French port of Boulogne-sur-Mer.
Bruno Marcoulay and his sons prepare their boat before it heads back to sea.
But these are difficult times.
The price of marine diesel has almost doubled because of the war in the Middle East.
Sales barely cover costs. Bruno says he's never experienced anything like it.
I've seen crises before, but never this severe.
In my 40 years fishing, we've had highs and lows.
We've been resilient.
But today it's an unprecedented situation.
I can't say when it will end.
Bruno takes us to see the head of the port's fishmongers union.
Aymeric Chazan says if fuel costs and inflation keep rising,
the impact on the industry could be devastating.
If the war continues and energy prices get worse, it could destroy parts of the industry.
Some boats won't be able to return to sea.
It won't be worth it for them.
There'll be less fish, and some companies might have to shut down.
The weather is as gloomy as the mood here.
The war may be far away, but the ripple effect on the global economy
is being felt on these shores.
When the costs are going up for fishermen and women at sea
and the processing companies,
it inevitably pushes up the prices for consumers.
At this market, Zondreen says people are buying less,
forcing fishmongers to adapt.
Everything is getting more expensive,
so we try to offer cheaper fish varieties to attract customers.
It's true that when I'm shopping prices are higher.
I'm more careful than before.
The French government has announced some limited financial aid for the industry this month,
but unless costs come down,
Boulogne's fishing community says it will need more help
to keep boats at sea and livelihoods afloat.
Natasha Butler, Al Jazeera, Boulogne-sur-Mer, France.
Let's take a look at some of the world's other news.
Now in the Gaza Strip,
Hamas says it will not hand over its weapons.
Disarmament is part of the second phase of the Gaza ceasefire plan,
but the armed group says calls to lay down its weapons are unacceptable,
especially as Palestinians continue to be targeted by Israel.
More than 700 people have been killed
since the ceasefire came into effect in October.
As for raising the issue of weapons in this crude manner,
it is nothing but a scandalous attempt by the occupation
to continue killing and genocide against our people,
which we will not accept under any circumstances.
We affirm that what the enemy was unable to seize from us
with tanks and genocide,
it will not seize from us with politics or at the negotiation table.
The occupation's aggression against our people
and its continued closure of the blessed Al Aqsa Mosque
to worshipers in an unprecedented manner
and the approval of the law for executing Palestinian prisoners,
we call upon the masses of our Palestinian people
in the brave West Bank,
the blessed Jerusalem,
and the occupied interior to march toward Al Aqsa Mosque.
Moon Robani is a non-resident fellow
at the Center for Conflict and Humanitarian Studies.
He says Hamas' statement confirms that talks
to implement the second phase of the Gaza ceasefire plan
are deadlocked.
What Hamas informed the mediators
is that it will not discuss issues such as disarmament
relating to the second phase of the plan for the Gaza Strip
until the items of the first phase are implemented.
That includes a cessation of hostilities.
As you noted,
virtual daily Israeli attacks on the Gaza Strip
have resulted in more than 700 Palestinians killed.
Humanitarian aid continues to be restricted.
And most notably,
this National Committee for the Administration of the Gaza Strip,
which was established by the Board of Peace,
continues to be prohibited from entering the Gaza Strip
by the Israelis.
And the Board of Peace is doing absolutely nothing
to ensure its ability to get in.
And so I think Hamas is taking two positions.
A, it won't discuss the second phase
until the first phase is properly implemented.
And B, when those discussions do take place,
it's not going to simply surrender its weapons
unless Israel clearly meets its own obligations as well.
And those are obligations that have to be consistent,
not just with what the Board of Peace wants,
but with the international consensus
and the rulings of the International Court of Justice
that this is an illegal occupation that must end.
For hundreds of thousands of Palestinians
made homeless by Israel's war on Gaza,
every day is a struggle.
As bombed out neighborhoods are slowly cleared of rubble,
some families are collecting scrap metal to survive.
Ali Mahmoud reports from Gaza City.
Trucks arrive one after another,
offloading what remains of homes, shops and entire streets.
Across large part of Gaza,
rubble removal continues month after Israeli bombardment
flat an entire neighborhood.
But for some, these dumping grounds
are more than just fields of debris.
They are workplaces.
Children search the mountains of broken concrete
and twisted metal for anything they can sell.
Wood, copper wire, aluminum.
Each piece they collect means a few more coins.
Each truck brings another opportunity and another risk.
The ground is unstable.
Sharp edges just from broken walls.
Aid agents is worn.
Unexploded ordinance may still be buried beneath the debris.
Isan Abdelal lives in a tent near one of the dumping sites.
We come here hoping to earn 20 shakals, about six dollars.
But it comes at a cost.
Injuries, exhaustion, cuts everywhere.
You can see the wounds and the blood.
The war has left hundreds of thousands of families
without stable income.
Factories are shut, shops are gone.
Entire businesses reduced to dust.
Post-war recovery is measured by reconstruction in plans,
funding in pledges.
But here on the ground recovery looks different.
It looks like children navigating the rubble,
households depending on the fragments of what was destroyed.
As long as livelihood remains absent
and reconstruction uncertain,
the rubble will continue to serve two purposes.
One reminder of loss.
And for some people it is a means of survival.
Informal scrap collection has become one of the few ways to earn cash.
We come here to earn money for food.
My father has no work, so we have to come.
We come here hoping to find bits of wood or pieces of cable that we can sell.
Anything that may help us buy food for our children.
We know climbing onto the moving trucks is dangerous.
But when your family depends on it, you take the risk.
Parents say they don't want their children here.
But survival leaves little room for a choice.
And Mahmoud Al-Jazeera from Gaza City, Palestine.
Serbia says explosives have been found near a pipeline
that carries Russian gas to Hungary.
Authorities say the discovery was made outside a Serbian town near the Hungarian border.
It comes just a week before closely watched elections in Hungary.
Prime Minister Viktor Orban is fighting to extend his 16 years in power.
He's linked Ukraine to those explosives.
For years, Ukraine has been working to cut Europe off from Russian energy.
They blew up Nord Stream.
Shut down the gas pipelines supplying Hungary.
And this year placed Hungary under an oil blockade by closing the Družba pipeline.
The Russian section of the Turk Stream is also under continuous military attack.
Ukraine's efforts pose a life-threatening danger to Hungary.
Kyiv has rejected Orban's accusations.
Posting on X, the foreign ministry spokesman said,
Ukraine has nothing to do with this.
Most probably it's a Russian false flag operation
as part of Moscow's heavy interference in Hungarian elections.
It's been a subdued Easter in the occupied Palestinian territories
where ceremonies have been scaled back because of the Iran war.
A small Sunday Mass was held at the Church of the Holy Sepulcher in occupied East Jerusalem.
The site is revered by Christians as the traditional site
of Jesus Christ's crucifixion and resurrection.
Israeli authorities have limited access.
On Palm Sunday last week,
a Latin patriarch was blocked from entering the Church,
sparking international condemnation.
In Gaza, Orthodox Palestinian Christians who follow the Eastern calendar
have celebrated Palm Sunday.
It marks the beginning of the Holy Week leading to Orthodox Easter.
Worshippers attended Mass at the St. Porphyrios Church in Gaza City.
It came under Israeli attack several times before the ceasefire.
White scrups are warning about threats to media freedom
in Sahel countries that have seen military coups in recent years.
Junta leaders are using security concerns and cybercrime laws to silence criticism.
Reporters Without Borders has condemned the sentencing last week
of a Malian journalist convicted of insulting the military leader
of Niger, Imogen Kimber, reports.
Words can be life-changing.
They certainly were for Yusuf Sissoko,
the publishing director of the Malian newspaper L'Alternance or The Alternating.
This article accuses General Abdur Rahman Tieny,
the military leader of neighboring Niger,
of trying to distract people from his government's security failures.
Tieny had blamed the attacks on the international airport
in the capital Niami back in January on France,
the Ivory Coast and Benin without providing evidence.
The Islamic State claimed responsibility.
The article argues Tieny overlooked the threat posed by armed groups,
which he pledged to remove when he seized power in 2023.
It also accuses what he calls Tieny's military regime of economic suicide,
citing the closure of borders with Benin.
Niger is a landlocked country which relied on its neighbor's ports for trade.
Sissoko was convicted last week of spreading false news,
undermining the credibility of the state and insulting a foreign head of state.
He was fined $1,700 and sentenced to two years in prison.
This journalist would only speak anonymously for fear of reprisals.
It represents a setback for freedom of expression,
which is already under severe strain in Mali,
but we do not use hope that there is still the possibility of appeal.
Rather than the press law, Sissoko was charged under Mali's cybercrime law,
which allows journalists to be punished for criticizing not just their own state,
but others in the Sahel.
Which makes the situation even more complex.
Had it been handled as a press-related matter,
the sentence might not have been the same.
I see this ruling as a strong message to all media actors,
that things can go very far, so extreme caution is needed.
And this isn't just happening in Mali.
In Niger and Burkina Faso,
military-led governments are restricting freedom of expression
by suspending independent media outlets
and censoring and intimidating reporters.
They're also targeting social media activists and influencers.
In Burkina Faso, some journalists who criticize the military
have been forcibly conscripted without training to fight against armed groups.
With the widening crackdown on independent journalism,
the International Press Institute is warning of an information blackout in the Sahel,
which it says could have regional and global consequences.
Imogen Kimber, Al Jazeera.
a city with a huge gun violence problem.
It's just renewed a deal for a system of sensors
that detects gunshots and then sends drones to crime scenes.
But critics say they target black communities
and make little difference, as Phil LaValle reports.
I see anything like that.
Cherie and Rosalyn are two mums
with the most painful bond imaginable.
Imagine seeing your loved one shot over 12 or 13 times.
That picture would never go out my head.
Both received a heart-breaking call.
Their sons had been shot dead.
Different men, but same day, one year apart.
I remember that day like yesterday.
I remember pulling up on the scene
and seeing the vehicle shot up, blood on the car.
There are hundreds of stories like this
here in Birmingham, Alabama, all with the same ending.
Gun violence is rife.
Could AI have saved any of them?
It doesn't work, no.
And that is what this is all about
because AI is being used here
to try to combat gun violence.
There is this network of sensors dotted around
listening for the sound of gunshots.
They hear them and they dispatch police automatically,
but where those sensors are located,
that's what's controversial.
These devices are placed in predominantly poor neighborhoods.
They're placed in black and brown neighborhoods.
And what it means is more police presence.
Multiple sensors.
The technology has been used in cities
across the US for years,
yet many are rolling it back or cancelling it altogether.
But in this city, synonymous with the civil rights movement,
they have just spent millions of dollars
to extend the contract.
On top of that, they've added drones
which take off autonomously
and can get to the scene of any potential crime
long before the police can.
Birmingham saw a 44% drop in homicides last year.
That is a 10-year low.
Another statistic, 88% of victims were black.
It's evident that it's not working.
It's not the technology that's keeping us safe.
And it may be other reasons
why crime is not as prevalent.
The company behind the tech says
it has seen a reduction of 61% in gunfire incidents
over the last two years
and that it helps because up to 85% of gunshots
are never reported by residents.
There are some areas where we do respond to shootings,
but we don't get a 911 call.
We identify those areas as a priority.
And it is solely the police
who choose which neighborhoods to put sensors in.
The family members that won't forget, that's retaliation.
That's what worries these bums.
Shootings lead to revenge and more shootings.
They spend their lives now consoling other parents
and trying to break that cycle.
I'll never be healed until I make it up there.
That's my goal.
I'm gonna make it up there with him.
For these mums, it is not about the sounds
that are picked up, but the silence that follows
and the emptiness it leaves behind.
Phil Lavelle, Al Jazeera, Birmingham, Alabama.
My name's gonna be here in a couple of minutes
with more coverage of the Israel-U.S. and Iran war.
I'm Rob Matheson.
Stay with us on Al Jazeera.
The latest news as it breaks.
What this front from Yemen is going to represent to Israel
is a threat from air and a threat from sea.
With live coverage.
A clear message from Iran.
The straight-up for mums remains open,
just not to the United States or Israel
or other countries that Iran determines
is a threat to them.
And exclusive reports.
Human rights groups say emptying whole areas
may amount to a war crime
and a strategy to permanently depopulate the areas.
In-depth analysis of the day's headlines.
Diplomacy yet again was used as a ruse for war.
Critical debate.
Who betrayed the table?
Who attacked the negotiations for the second time?
For the third time during the talks
we should be attacked?
Who is talking about a greater country for itself?
Israel, not Iran.
Iran has been a huge supporter of terrorism over the years.
I really have to take exception to the idea
that Iran is innocent in this.
Inside Story on Al Jazeera.
This war is escalating and has become a story
in which propaganda can matter as much as military might does.
Censorship is taking place across the board.
Our focus, as always here at the listening post,
is on the journalism.
Hello, this is Al Jazeera live from Doha
with our continuing coverage of the war
between the US, Israel and Iran.
I'm Malin Said.
Coming up, Donald Trump sets a Tuesday deadline for Iran
to reopen the strait of Hormuz.
All the US will bomb its power plants, bridges and quote,
unleash hell.
We are determined to defend.
Iran's foreign ministry dismisses the US president's warning
and vows a swift retaliation to any US attacks.
US troops rescue a second airman
in a high stakes mission in Iran.
Two days after his fighter jet went down.
The rescuers in the northern Israeli city of Haifa
look for the missing after an Iranian strike
targets an apartment complex for people are injured.
And the Iran war squeezes global economies.
Workers are the worst hit.
Weavers in Indian-administered Kashmir say
orders for the famed Pashmina shawls have dried up.
US President Donald Trump has renewed threats
to destroy Iranian power plants and bridges
if it doesn't reopen the strait of Hormuz.
He shared what appears to be a deadline on social media.
Tuesday 8 p.m. Eastern time.
Well, earlier, Trump posted an expletive laden threat
to his truth social account.
He promised that Iranians would be quote,
living in hell if the strait isn't reopened.
Well, Tehran has emphasized it will retaliate if struck
Foreign Ministry spokesman Ismail Baghehi says
any US-related location in the Middle East would be a target.
Our armed forces have made it clear that
in case Iran's infrastructure is attacked,
we would react in kind.
They would, our armed forces would target
any similar infrastructure that is owned
or in any way or manner related to the United States
or contributes to their act of aggression against Iran.
Well, this comes as missile strikes pound areas
across the region and Iranian missiles struck
this residential building in the northern Israeli port city
of Haifa just hours ago.
And Israeli attacks are bombarding the southern suburbs
in the Lebanese capital of Beirut.
We'll be live from Tehran in a moment,
but first Al Jazeera's Mike Hanna has more
on President Trump's comments from Washington, DC.
The unusual use of an expletive by a national leader,
perhaps a symbol of President Trump's frustration
with the Iranian government and their refusal
to concede to the demands that he is making.
That reference as well was to the strait of Hamuz
which in recent days, President Trump had insisted
he did not care about saying the US did not need
the oil passing through the strait
and it was up to the countries who are reliant on that oil
to deal with the situation.
But now the demand about opening the strait of Hamuz
appears front and center of the President's new demands
of the Iranian government.
President Trump threatening to, and I use his words,
blowing everything and taking the oil
if Iran does not meet his new deadline
which has now been set at 8 p.m. Eastern time
on Tuesday evening.
He says in an earlier media post
that a power plant day and bridge day
all wrapped up on Tuesday.
But on the other hand, in addition to these threats,
President Trump is sending signals
that there's some kind of negotiation process underway.
He's indicated that his close confidants, Jared Kushner
and Stephen Whitcoff are in consultation
with either the Iranian government
and identified figures or some form of intermediary.
And speaking to US news outlets,
President Trump says that he is optimistic
that there can be an agreement very soon.
He says the agreement could come within a matter of days
rather than a matter of weeks.
So you've got this dichotomous approach
from the President on the one hand,
threatening obliteration to civilian targets
within Iran, which some observers
would contend to be a war crime.
But on the other hand, what he is saying is,
yes, we are talking, the talks are going well
and they could come to fruition
before that new deadline I set,
which is 8 p.m. Eastern time on Tuesday.
Mike Hannah, Al Jazeera, Washington.
Well, the Speaker of Iran's parliament
has also responded to Trump.
In a social media post,
Mohammed Baga Ghalibath wrote, quote,
your reckless moves are dragging the United States
into a living hell for every single family.
And our whole region is going to burn
because you insist on following Netanyahu's commands.
Make no mistake, you won't gain anything through war crimes.
Let's bring in Mohammed Vowell,
whose life was in Tehran.
So Iran standing firm Mohammed against President Trump's threat
to target its power plants
if the Strait of Hormuz is not reopened
and also accusing Washington of potential war crimes.
What else has Iran been saying?
Well, that's right.
And it is consistent here.
They are consistent in those statements
from even from the beginning of the war.
And today we just had more of that,
more explanation of why Iran is sticking to its approach
towards this war and the threats
that Donald Trump has expressed several times.
They are saying that this war is imposed on them,
that this war is illegal
because it's based on a series of lies.
That's what the spokesman
of the foreign ministry Ismail Baqai added
or so in those comments.
It's a series of lies,
the lie that Iran is pursuing nuclear weapons,
the lie that Iran presents an immediate threat
to the United States
and the lie that this war is meant
to liberate Iranians from a despotic regime.
So he is saying that all of these things are not true
and that while the US president
is threatening Iranians and thinking
that he can force them, intimidate them
and force them to a kind of deal
that is going to be bad for the future of Iran
for its sovereignty, for the benefit of its people,
the Iranians are not being phased by that
and they have what it takes to defend themselves
and they have proved every single day of this war
that they meant what they said
and that they can wage retaliatory strikes,
particularly regarding this threat
to destroy the civilian structure in the country,
particularly power plants,
they are reiterating that they will do the same in the region
and that that pain will not be limited to Iran
but it will be felt across the region.
And Mohamed, we're hearing of potentially more attacks
in Boucher province.
This is of course where the Boucher nuclear power plant is.
Tell us more about all the latest attacks
across the country.
Well, there is a long list of cities
that have been bombarded today.
I can mention some of them, Ahvaz, for instance.
In the Southwest, the airport of Ahvaz has been bombarded
and also Mahshahr city and Benderlinghe, Kong city,
where six people were killed and 17 were wounded.
You have Shiraz, Esfahan, Karaj and also Tehran
as usual every single day, but the most significant
or at least the most alarming among those is Boucher.
Boucher power plant has been also at the receiving end
of another strike today.
That's the fifth time since the beginning of this war
and that's the power plant, the nuclear power plant,
the only one that is functioning in the country.
It has a tremendous amount of radioactive material in it
and the fear is that if it gets hit directly
and if it explodes, it will be a catastrophe
not only for Iran but also across the region
because it is located not far from many of the Gulf countries
and the IAE and also Iranians here are warning
that if this power plant is destroyed and if it explodes,
then it is going to be a huge war crime
and also it's going to be very catastrophic
to the entire region.
Indeed, Mohammad Val, they're live in Tehran.
Thank you.
All the threat of escalation in Iran does indeed put
the Gulf region squarely in the crossfire.
The sites Iran is threatening to hit back
are almost entirely located in GCC countries
which are already coping with daily attacks.
Kuwait says it's been hit by a series of drone attacks.
Authorities report two major power
and desalination plants have been targeted.
Now, one of the facilities is in Al-Zur
which is nearly 90 kilometers south of Kuwait city.
Another attack hit the finance ministry complex.
That building is in central Kuwait city.
In Bahrain, Iran targeted an oil facility
sparking several fires.
Emergency response team said the blaze
has been fully extinguished.
Over the past few weeks,
Manama has come under repeated Iranian missile
and drone attacks.
Let's go to our correspondent Mohammad Jamjoon
who's here in the Qatari capital, Doha.
So I've been listing there some of the attacks
in Gulf countries in the last 24 hours.
And now, of course, they're preparing
for a possible escalation if Donald Trump
carries out his threats.
This is an incredibly worrying time.
It is, Malin, and I should mention
that over the course of the last couple of hours,
we've also seen new reports emerging from Kuwait.
The Kuwaiti Ministry of Defense saying
that they have been subjected to new missile
and drone attacks emanating from Iran.
That they are dealing with those attacks
a couple of hours ago, we had heard reports
that the sirens had been heard around Kuwait City
in the last hour.
We've also seen a statement from the Ministry of Defense.
We're waiting for more details as we get there.
We will, of course, bring them to you and our viewers.
Now, as you mentioned, lots of attacks
over the course of the last 24, 48 hours,
especially targeting petrochemical plants,
energy infrastructure facilities,
water desalination plants.
Some of the countries affected, of course,
Kuwait, Bahrain, UAE.
This is incredibly worrying
at a very critical juncture.
One of the reasons this is a critical juncture
is because we are on the eve of a deadline
that was imposed by U.S. President Donald Trump.
Now he's stating that as of 8 p.m. tomorrow, Tuesday night,
that that basically will be the limit for his patients
when it comes to Iran reopening the Strait of Hormuz.
And Donald Trump has essentially said
that he will go ahead and attack
energy infrastructure sites and bridges in Iran
if the Strait of Hormuz is not opened by that time,
which leaves the Gulf countries to ponder
what's going to happen next.
The reason for that being that in the past,
Iran has said that if the U.S. and Israel
attack energy sites, civilian infrastructure,
bridges and the like in Iran,
that Iran will retaliate by targeting facilities
of those natures in Gulf countries.
So that's why everybody right now really worrying
what exactly is going to happen next.
Now, the Gulf countries have been in a defensive posture
when it comes to their response to Iran as of yet,
but they've also said that their patience is not limitless.
What happens if the U.S. attacks
in a much harder way facilities in Iran
and then Iran retaliates by targeting energy infrastructure,
water and desalination plants
and civilian sites in Gulf countries?
Nobody knows at this hour, but everybody's worrying
because this deadline is very much looming.
Malin.
Meanwhile, Mohammed, when it comes to the Strait of Hormuz,
Iran is insisting it is open
and it's also been holding meetings with Oman
regarding the Strait of Hormuz and the operation of it.
What more do we know about those meetings?
So we've seen a statement from the Iranians
and the Omanis Malin in which they said
that there was a meeting that was held on Saturday
and that there were deputy foreign minister level
officials at that meeting
and that there were also experts at that meeting
and that the point of that meeting
was to try to figure out a way to simplify navigation
to make it easier for ships
to navigate the Strait of Hormuz.
They've also said that objectives are being discussed.
We don't know what those objectives are at this point
and that's really going to be the key
of what happens going forward
because the question becomes,
what if those objectives are acceptable to Oman and Iran
but they're not acceptable to the United States?
Will the United States then escalate its campaign
with Israel against Iran?
What does that do going forward?
Also the question being,
will whatever solution that the Iranians and Omanis
come up with be acceptable to other GCC countries?
Will it be acceptable to other countries
throughout the world?
We know that in the past 24, 48 hours
we've seen more reporting that vessels
from specific countries in Europe and Asia
have potentially been able to cross the Strait of Hormuz
that they've been able to navigate the Strait of Hormuz.
Will that continue?
All of these, again,
much more questions than answers at this hour.
People wondering what exactly is going to happen
and yes, it is a positive sign
that these discussions are going forward.
We know that the Omanis have been tirelessly trying
to de-escalate the situation in the Strait of Hormuz
but the question is what happens next?
Who is on board and what if certain players are not?
Malin.
Okay, thank you for that.
Mohammad Jamjou there for us
with the very latest from Doha.
Now a US Airman has been rescued in Iran
after an intense 48 hour search operation.
The weapons systems officer has been missing
since Friday when the fighter jet
he was in went down in the province of Kogilue
and Boya Ahmad.
Tehran said it shot down the F-15E, a two-seater aircraft.
John Hendren reports from Washington.
It was a daring and risky mission
to save an American airman
from becoming an Iranian prisoner of war.
Iranian forces search the mountainous areas
of southwestern Iran
after an F-15E fighter jet went down on Friday.
It was the first time a US aircraft
territory in the five-week-old war.
Two Blackhawk helicopters took fire as U.S. teams raced to find the missing crew member.
An A-10 Warthog, an air support aircraft, was also damaged, its pilot ejecting over the
Gulf.
Iran broadcast photos of what it said was debris from the fighter jet, including a jump seat.
Although the pilot had been rescued on Friday, the weapon specialist remained in
hiding, evading Iranian forces for two days.
Finally, early on Sunday, deep in Iranian territory, the U.S. search operation was successful.
President Donald Trump made the announcement on social media, posting, We Got Him, saying
the Colonel had been behind enemy lines in the treacherous mountains of Iran being hunted
by our enemies.
He said U.S. forces had been monitoring his location 24 hours a day and sent dozens
of aircraft armed with the most lethal weapons in the world to retrieve him.
Trump added he sustained injuries, but he will be just fine.
A U.S. official told Al Jazeera the rescue operation began in darkness but ended in an
intense firefight and daylight, before dozens of heavily armed aircraft and hundreds
of troops transported the airmen out of Iran.
A U.S. officer in Iranian custody could have given Iran leverage, as it had when Iran
took U.S. hostages in 1979.
With that crisis averted, attention now shifts to the U.S. deadline for Iran to open the
Strait of Hormuz.
John Hendren, Al Jazeera, Washington.
In Lebanon, the Israeli army has carried out new strikes on Beirut's southern suburb
in a densely populated residential area.
At least four people have been killed, 39 others injured in those strikes.
It says it's continuing attacks on his border military infrastructure.
So far more than a million people have been forcibly displaced across the country.
They hit a completely civilian area.
It's mostly migrants here, Sudanese people.
People were at home and they struck them.
Are those military objectives?
Where is the UN?
No one says anything.
Aren't they human too?
They're killing children and women.
The whole world has to speak up.
It has to see and say something.
Have we become nothing but numbers, a people of numbers?
How is that possible?
We are devastated.
Our morale is low.
When you see your friends and neighbours in pieces on the ground and blood everywhere
and the house destroyed, our house was destroyed.
Where are we going to sleep?
Where do we go?
OK, we can speak to our correspondent Heidi Pett, who is live for us in Beirut.
Hi, dear.
I believe you are live at that attack that's just taken place.
What are you learning about what was hit and were there any warning signs?
We are in the hills of eastern Beirut at the site of another Israeli airstrike that
occurred a couple of hours ago.
This appears to have been another attempted assassination strike.
That's where Israel, instead of levelling an entire building, they strike one particular
apartment.
In this case, in this residential building, this is a Christian neighbourhood.
In eastern Beirut, it's not an area that was warned about.
It's not an area that has been targeted.
It's an area where people thought that they would be safe.
It's caused a lot of concern speaking to neighbours and first responders here who
are confused and frightened by what has happened here this evening.
Now, from what we can tell, the apartment that the Israelis were going
after is the one on the third floor.
Speaking to people here, they say that at the time that apartment was empty.
However, the damage was severe enough that people have been killed who were in the
apartment on the second floor.
So what we know at the moment is that at least three people have been killed.
That's the official update from the Ministry of Health.
Among them, a local leader with the Lebanese forces and his wife.
Now, the Lebanese forces is a Christian political party on the
right wing of the political spectrum here in Lebanon.
And there's been a lot of concern and condemnation from his colleagues
this evening. His name was Pierre Mouawad.
And we've seen the local MP in this area saying that they need to be more
stringent checks on displaced people, calling for the setting up of roadblocks
and things like that.
And his other colleagues from his party, the Lebanese forces, also saying
that people should be sheltered, but they should be welcomed into official
shelters and there should be stringent checks before people are allowed
into other neighbourhoods, which gives you some level of the some
indication of the level of concern and consternation.
We're talking about a million people displaced across Lebanon.
It's a humanitarian crisis that the government is struggling to deal with.
Only about five percent of people are in official shelters, many others.
They're trying to stay with family and friends in overcrowded apartments
and they're seeking shelter in other parts of the country.
But they're not always being welcomed.
They're having trouble, you know, renting apartments.
And this is partly why speaking to neighbours here.
They say, you know, we want to welcome people with an open heart,
but we're afraid of the consequences if people come into our neighbourhoods
and we don't know who they are.
OK, thank you for that.
Heidi, pet there for us in Lebanon.
Rescue workers in Israel are searching for people
feared trapped under the rubble of a building hit by an Iranian strike
on Haifa, the residential structure partially collapsed after the attack on Sunday.
Israeli authorities say four people have been wounded.
One person is in critical condition.
Rob McBride has been following developments from the Jordanian
capital, Amman. So what more do we know about this attack, Rob?
Yeah, that's right.
This attack happened during the evening of Sunday
and the rescue workers are working through the nighttime hour,
still searching through the rubble for survivors.
It happened in the port city of Haifa in the north of Israel.
It is a very important strategic hub for transport,
also an industrial centre.
And it's also where a lot of the oil refinery refining for Israel
takes place because of that.
It is a target that has been repeatedly struck
by Iranian missiles since the start of this conflict.
It's also within rocket range, given its proximity in the north
close to the border with Lebanon of Hezbollah rockets,
which often coordinate their attacks with Syrian incoming missiles.
The authorities say that this was the result of one missile
with what they say was a fairly heavy warhead
which got past their missile defensive shield.
It struck this building and there is a danger
not only of the building being close to collapse,
but also that they say there could be unexploded parts of this warhead,
unexploded ordnance still in the rubble,
which makes it all the more complicated.
And it's partly because of that that this rescue operation
is now being assisted by Israel's National Special Rescue Unit.
It struck the lower floor of this building.
That partially then caused the apartments above it to collapse downwards.
And the four people are unaccounted for their belief
to have been from one of the apartments that has been one of the most heavily damaged.
This comes on a day when Israel saw four salvos of Iranian missiles.
One of those struck the Nayot Khavav Industrial Park.
This is a very important industrial centre close to the city of Bishiva in the south.
It struck near a toxic waste dump.
Now, the authorities say there was no danger of any environmental hazard.
But it does cause a concern because this this park has been hit now three times
since the start of this conflict.
The last time was about a week ago when a piece of shrapnel
caused an explosion of fire at a hazardous chemical plant.
Again, no hazardous leak, but it is of major concern.
OK, thank you for that update.
Rob McBride, there for us the latest from Aman.
Well, the Middle East conflict is having far reaching effects,
including having an impact on workers in Indian administered Kashmir.
The region relies heavily on handicrafts
with thousands of people working in the industry.
Their livelihoods are now at risk because at least half of their goods
are sold in the Middle East, where the region stuck in a war.
Orders are being delayed or cancelled.
Lena Blakke explains.
The Kotas are one of thousands of families
who have been part of Kashmir's craft industry for generations.
They spin yarn from the wool of Himalayan
chang-thangi goats on traditional hand looms, creating Peshmina scarves.
Peshmina is not just work for us.
It's our legacy and identity.
I am one of the thousands of women who hand spin the yarn.
And this spinning is the backbone of our livelihood.
However, their income is in jeopardy.
The family has reduced production, using only two of their four hand looms.
That's because at least 50% of Kashmir's handicrafts
are sold to the Middle East.
And the regional conflict has led to cancellations.
This is impacting us a lot.
The work is minimal, about 90% less than usual.
Tausif Bhatt also comes from a family of Peshmina makers.
But now runs a company employing around 60 people.
If the situation remains the same and the conflict continues,
I think we may eventually have to shut down the business.
The Kashmir Chamber of Commerce says it's not only a lack of orders
that is a problem, but the cost of sending anything
has risen astronomically.
That's a lot of families at risk of losing their livelihoods.
Let's take a look at some of the world's other news
in the Gaza Strip. Hamas says it won't hand over its weapons.
Disarmament is part of the second phase of the Gaza ceasefire plan,
but the armed group says calls to lay down its weapons are unacceptable,
especially as Palestinians continue to be targeted by Israel.
More than 700 have been killed since the ceasefire came into effect in October.
As for raising the issue of weapons in this crude manner,
it is nothing but a scandalous attempt by the occupation
to continue killing and genocide against our people,
which we will not accept under any circumstances.
We affirm that what the enemy was unable to seize from us
with tanks and genocide, it will not seize from us
with politics or at the negotiation table.
The occupation's aggression against our people
and its continued closure of the blessed al-Aqsa mosque
to worshipers in an unprecedented manner
and the approval of the law for executing Palestinian prisoners,
we call upon the masses of our Palestinian people in the brave West Bank,
the blessed Jerusalem and the occupied interior to march toward al-Aqsa mosque.
It's been a subdued Easter in the occupied Palestinian territories
where ceremonies have been scaled back because of the Iran War.
A small Sunday mass was held at the Church of the Holy Sepulchre
in occupied East Jerusalem.
The site is revered by Christians as the traditional site
of Jesus Christ's Crucification and Resurrection.
Israeli authorities have limited access.
On Palm Sunday last week, the Latin Patriarch was blocked
from entering the Church, sparking international condemnation.
In Gaza, Orthodox Palestinian Christians
who follow the Eastern calendar have celebrated Palm Sunday.
It marks the beginning of the Holy Week leading to Orthodox Easter.
Worshippers attended mass at the Saint Porifairos Church in Gaza City.
It came under Israeli attack several times before the ceasefire.
Serbia says powerful explosives have been found near a pipeline
that carries Russian gas to Hungary.
Authorities say the discovery was made outside a Serbian town
near the Hungarian border.
It comes just a week before closely watched elections in Hungary.
Prime Minister Viktor Orban is fighting to extend his 16 years in power.
He's linked Ukraine to those explosives.
For years, Ukraine has been working to cut Europe off from Russian energy.
They blew up Nord Stream, shut down the gas pipeline supplying Hungary,
and this year placed Hungary under an oil blockade
by closing the Družba pipeline.
The Russian section of the Turk Stream is also under continuous military attack.
Ukraine's efforts pose a life-threatening danger to Hungary.
OK, coming up next, inside story looks at how the war in Iran
is deepening the humanitarian crisis in Gaza.
I'll be back.
With your news out in about 30 minutes,
we're going to take a short break and stay with us.
For many parents, the court ruling came as a welcome recognition
of what they've long felt.
A jury found that major social media companies harmed a young user,
Kaylee, with addictive design features that damaged her mental health.
This was a conscious decision that they made.
It was not an accident, and parents are not to blame.
META was ordered to pay $4.2 million.
The companies say they will appeal.
If companies like Facebook change the way they offer their services to young people,
it could alter the experience of modern childhood itself.
That landmark case is expected to open the floodgates
for thousands of lawsuits.
On counting the cost, with higher oil prices and e-sanctions,
Russia is hoping to gain from the conflict in the Middle East
and further its war aims in Ukraine.
But those plans are at risk from Ukrainian attacks.
So can Russia help fill the global energy gap,
or is its capacity already under threat?
Counting the cost, on Al-Zazira.
The war in Iran is deepening the humanitarian crisis in Gaza
in violation of the ceasefire.
Israel has severely restricted aid and maintained its airstrikes.
The US-brokered deal is meant to be in phase two,
but appears to be in limbo.
So who could step in to help Palestinians?
This is Inside Story.
Welcome to the programme, I'm Imran Khan.
It's called The Forgotten Crisis.
Humanitarian conditions in Gaza remain dire,
despite a US-brokered ceasefire that came into effect in October.
For months, the Israeli military violated the agreement,
carrying out airstrikes,
limiting the entry of aid and building materials.
But it got worse when Israel and the US launched their joint offensive
on Iran at the end of February.
The RAFA border crossing, a lifeline in southern Gaza, was closed again.
Israel further restricted deliveries of food, fuel and humanitarian aid.
With the war in Iran disrupting global supply chains
and the UN warning of threats to food security,
one of the implications for Palestinians in Gaza
will discuss that with our guests in just a moment.
But first, this report from Michael Apple.
An Israeli airstrike targets a vehicle killing everyone inside.
There's a war going on, but this isn't Iran.
It's what a ceasefire looks like to Palestinians in Gaza.
We feel that we are in a state of war
and that the war is still raging in the region.
We witness bombardments and assassinations all the time.
Even though we are in a ceasefire, we do not feel it.
Israel is among the estimated 1.7 million people
forced from their homes in the strip.
With some plastic and a lot of prayer,
she tries to keep the reign at bay.
Her hopes that there's an end in sight to the misery is fraying,
much like her tent.
The UN says some Palestinians are only getting half
of the calories needed to sustain life.
Israel maintains a stranglehold on the border crossings.
Many here say they feel forgotten by the world.
Before the Iran war, the same people who forgot about us then
just keep on forgetting about us now.
Food supplies have decreased and prices have gone up.
The landscape is apocalyptic.
It bears the scars of war.
But the human cost cannot be ignored.
Israeli attacks have killed nearly 73,000 Palestinians
since October 7, 2023.
The vast majority of them women and children.
More than 172,000 people have been wounded,
many of them sustaining life-changing injuries.
Another 10,000 Palestinians are unaccounted for,
believed to be buried underneath the mountains of rubble.
Israel still controls nearly 60% of Gaza.
A so-called yellow line marking where its troops are meant to operate
came into effect with the ceasefire.
But it's regularly violated.
The killing hasn't stopped either.
More than 700 Palestinians have been killed
during the nearly six months of the ceasefire.
The UN estimates the Israeli military has dropped
around 200,000 tons of munitions on Gaza.
And up to 12% of those bombs haven't detonated.
Specialized teams find them and mark them.
UXO, unexploded ordinance.
A danger that will take decades to clear.
Palestinians are trapped in limbo,
enduring a fragile ceasefire
while the humanitarian crisis deepens.
And much of the world's attention is focused elsewhere.
Michael Appel, Al Jazeera for Inside Story.
Now, before we talk to our guests,
let's talk to our correspondent in Gaza City, Hind Khudri.
Hind, you've been a correspondent for us now
since almost the beginning of the war
and throughout the ceasefire.
But I don't want to speak to you as a correspondent today.
I want to talk about your family, your friends.
I want to talk about Palestinians
and how they're still suffering despite the ceasefire.
Life's just not got any easier for you, right?
Well, I'm done.
I remember talking to you the last time six months ago
and we were very...
Hopeful at that time for example, I was looking forward to see my family as we have been separated
Since October 2023, but still six months into the ceasefire
And I still didn't see my mom or meet my brothers and I'm not the only case
There are thousands of Palestinians that are still waiting for freedom of movement. It's not only that it's the
Continuous humanitarian situation, which is deteriorating every single day
I mean, I have been sick for the past week and I haven't been finding any
Medicine I have been going through pharmacies going through hospitals and the Israeli
Authorities are not letting in any medical supplies into the Gaza Strip and I'm talking about a normal flu and infection in the lungs
There's no antibiotics. There's no
Ventiline inhalers and this is the case and has been the case for the past
Six months there has been a lot of promises. Most of Gaza's population is literally still living on the streets
in very fragile torn out tents where shelter items are not entering and with the Iran
War now Palestinians feel more forgotten because there has been no
Progress in the ceasefire deal in the technocrat
Teams that were supposed to be coming into Gaza Strip more restrictions have been imposed on the Gaza Strip
And let me tell you very basic stuff where eggs for example are still a struggle for a lot of
Palestinians
Anything nutritious has been banned into the Gaza Strip and we all carry this amount of loss amount of
Homeliness the loneliness we're still feeling that yes, there is ceasefire, but we're still being killed
every couple of days where it last in the last couple of days there has been a
Vehicle that has been targeted where three people were killed
Police officers have been also been a target by the Israeli authorities and also the fact that
There are thousands of Palestinians still trapped under the rubble where families weren't even able to bury
Whatever is remained of their families and that's the story during the day
But when the night falls and it gets colder and people are living
Intense it just must be even worse. I mean just what's it like being a child?
Children and run are still queuing up on food kitchens on on water
Trucks because none of these
Struggles have been solved
also the fact that your mother is cuddling you because it's the only source of warmth the fact that
Rain is another nightmare other than airstrikes and I don't believe me. We are still
Literally sleeping every single day on very loud drone sounds as
Drones did not leave the sky of Gaza neither night or day
And it is the ongoing trauma of this sound where we used to hear it and we expected a
Airstrike over and over again most of Gaza's children are still deprived from
Medicine they're still deprived from education and also let me tell you that there are thousands of children
that were the only survivors and they're living without parents without family members and
children
Every child in Gaza carries a different story of struggle and all of these stories are heartbreaking
I mean hon. I really hope you get some medicine soon because I can hear it in your voice
Thank you for bringing us up today for what it's like for people just living in Gaza
Let's now bring in our guests from southern Lebanon. We're joined by dr. Mohammed Tahir a war surgeon who has worked extensively in Gaza
He's also the CEO of our Risala foundation Alex to all is in Boston, Massachusetts
He's the executive director of the world peace foundation and specializes in famine and in Ramallah
Javier abuid. He's a political analyst and former communications director for the Palestine Liberation
Organization a warm welcome to you all I want to start with dr. Mohammed in southern Lebanon
You just heard our correspondent there in hudley talking about the fact that you can't even get cold and flu tablets over the counter
Medications in Gaza. You can't get that and there's been a war on the medical sector this I mean
There's just no medicines in Gaza now. How does that make you feel given that you worked in that sector?
Yes, thank you first of all for having me
look what we know about the
Israeli regime is that
The killing never stops and the suffering never stops. It just transitions from phase to phase
sometimes the the killing is accelerated the suffering is
ever more and then when they turn direction to another part of the world and they
You know bring about suffering there. They slow the suffering elsewhere
And that's simply because they don't have the bandwidth to bring about so much suffering across the world
In in that the same intensity now Gaza, of course when I was there it was a killing. It was a killing field
It was an abattoir and actually now that I'm based in Lebanon
I can tell you that I'm in a war here today in Lebanon, but the Gaza was something completely different
That was an outright genocide and the suffering is
Unimaginable I often times think back to what we saw and it's unthinkable that this was ever allowed to happen
Today in Gaza. I was talking to my colleagues. In fact yesterday
They have no building material to reestablish hospitals. They have no access to
Materials to do interventional procedures. They're lacking in oncologists. They're lacking in pulmonologists
They're lacking in endoscopists. They're lacking in the plastic surgeons
And of course, you know, you heard simple medicines not being available bringing about the suffering for the average person on day to day
But the most vulnerable are also at most risk and you see every day people dying in front of our screens and
Pleads going up to the world for evacuation
Evacuation has come to a halt as well. So the suffering is really
Something that cannot be imagined
Have you I'm gonna bring you in in just a second because I want to talk to you about all the politics of this
But I want on the humanitarian front. I want to start with Alex of all Alex
This is a famine that's unfolding in front of our eyes on our cameras
But is not getting any attention
Regrettably tragically appallingly so
So exactly a year ago a year before the the the operation that
President Trump and Benjamin Netanyahu and unleashed on on Iran
There was the complete siege on Gaza
And that siege was tighter than the siege today
But the condition of the people entering into those siege conditions today is is as we've just been hearing
Utterly deplorable. These are people already at the brink
so
deprived of
So many of the essentials needed to sustain
Life living in the most miserable conditions really ground down by two and a half years
and
So what we I fear we will be seeing is a descent into famine conditions
Comparable to what we saw at the same time last year with the difference
That last year there was international attention and outcry which mounted over the months
And eventually by september october
pushed the united states to recognize what was happening and pushed israel to towards opening
The border crossings and so on and I didn't see any of that pressure now as as as
We've been hearing this is this is a crisis
Forgotten ignored by the world. Well, let's talk about that pressure
Javier, I don't need to ask you about the suffering the palestinians. You live it every single day
But there is a board of peace. There is you know a ceasefire. There's supposed to be a negotiation going on
This is not supposed to be happening phase two is supposed to be happening. That all seems to have disappeared
Am I right in thinking that
Certainly and running things from having me here. First of all the board of peace
It's unleashing its kind of attempt to set an alternative to the un by president donald trump his administration
The person they have in charge of the gaza reconstruction. Mr. Mladenov is a former
UN envoy here
He doesn't have words when palestinians are killed on a daily basis in gaza
Now when there is very limited access to water cooking gas and other
Important elements. So clearly what we are facing ember not only in gaza, but also in the occupied west bank
Is how the israeli?
Plans that talk about openly now about ethnic cleansing about annexation
Are coming out without any sort of significant international
Response and let's be very clear. This is not only about the trump administration
We are facing terror attacks by israeli settlers on a daily basis here in the occupied west bank
The european union response seems to be something like calling for more reforms
Within the palestinian authority and support and this is a way of getting closer to a state that is appearing on the ground
Because of the culture of impunity that israel continues to enjoy
So it's a situation of overall crisis. I would define
I mean have you I just want to follow up on that because
1500 palestinians have been killed in the occupied west bank since october the 7th 2023 that's more
than
That were killed
On october the 7th 2023 right that day that actually unleashed hell on gaza if gaza was the war that everybody concentrated on
It's a forgotten war
In the occupied west bank
Raids are going on every single day. I've been there. I've seen them
You know, I've been at the end of them
So, you know, why do you think the occupied west bank is the forgotten part of this war? Do you think?
It may be emblem perhaps because here there is no armed resistance against israeli occupation
And it seems an international community and particularly western powers only tend to care about what's happening in palestine
What when when there are israelis that are being affected?
By palestinian resistance and and and that's extremely unfortunate because it said it sends
A very wrong message just over the march the month of march
We have over 200 israeli settler terror attacks against palestinians
Not counting the actions of the israeli occupation forces not a single israeli settler has been arrested or prosecuted
For those attacks, but in return we have six palestinians killed by those israeli settlers
We have dozens if not hundreds of settler militias armed by the israeli government and the israeli in general
They are not really facing
Or meaningful consequences for their actions
So clearly what we are facing here in the occupied west bank is extremely dramatic
Why because here also it's a priority of of israel here is where they have over 200 settlements
700 000 settlers and the the campaign to annex more and more palestinian land
Alex i'm going to come to you now
The board of peace was set up to get to a place where they could get
food aid everything into the gaza strip and look for long-term solution
But there was an organization in place
That we could do that that had all of the knowledge and the infrastructure and that was the united nations
It was the united nations relief works agency the refugee agency for palestinians israel
Completely sidelined it so the gaza board of peace
Is a failure do you think?
I think you've really answered your
Your question in the way that you've framed it and i think that's absolutely correct
There was a workable infrastructure that could deliver the essentials with
The the professional proficiency the reach the partnership the experience and above all the humanity the fact that
onra and another international organizations present on the ground
In in in gaza also in the west bank have those routes those contacts with the community means that they can respond
with the sense of compassion with the the sense of
of humanity
To the people and and and and their real needs
All be it with very limited resources under extreme duress
And what we have with the board of peace is essentially a vacuum the the um
We have plans for more militarized forms of
Russian provision
We have plans for
building a reviera. This is a a
A performance populist piece combined with a
Claptocratic peace for profit formula
It is throwing away everything that we know has worked and everything that is founded on
The the basic principles of the of the charter of of the united nations and and international law
Mohammed doctors like you
Have been barred from going back in to gaza you yourself as i understand it are not allowed to go back in
To gaza israeli is restricting
Even volunteers getting in the border pieces clearly as we've heard
Isn't really doing the things it's supposed to be doing you a shirt
You are nodding your head in agreement there when they were talking about the fact that there was a mechanism that allowed people like you
In and that's been destroyed
Just talk us about the effect on the medical professionals like you when you can't get in to help
Uh, you're absolutely right. Look, um, my colleagues in gaza are phenomenal
doctors physicians nurses and so on
they've just been
constrained by the environment
Imposed upon them by the israeli regime in that they're not allowed for example to go outside for fellowship training
Pick up skills that otherwise other surgeons would be would have access to
And in addition to that, of course, they have a limitation on on technology and health care and so on
And so, uh, although they're talented surgeons, uh, there are certain areas or certain, you know areas of expertise that are missing there
Um, and they are reliant upon, uh, colleagues from the outside coming in and not only performing surgeries there
But also trying to fill the gap in the training that they've been denied
Um, and as a result lots of people simply don't have
Access to the usual sort of health care people around the world
In addition to that you have to remember you're dealing with the most
complex and severe injuries
On the face of this, uh, earth and i'm telling you this first hand because i was involved in the medical evacuation program where we
Took out, uh, the most complex cases to neighboring countries and we tried and we were treating them there and that involved
a multi-disciplinary team from from the from the globe to arrive at, you know, at decisions in the patient's best interest
And so when they deny us, they're basically not only cutting off a lifeline, uh, to the doctors there in terms of training
They're denying patients, you know, the the the they're right, you know, innocent people. They're right to health care
And this is of course all orchestrated. It's a it's a strangulation process
They don't want the people of reza to be there anymore. This is a you know, a a
You know, we are on a phase of genocide
And of course they're not going to allow people like me me coming on the show, for example
Means that I don't have access to reza anymore
Anyone who's outspoken anyone who describes the suffering they ban you
Alex, how much of what you've just heard dr. Mowick talk about constitutes a war crime
I it's it's worse than a war crime. I mean, this is you know, this is the the crime
That go it's a crime of extermination. It's a crime of genocide, but it's something more
It's a it's a crime against humanity in the most profound sense that it is trying to kill
The humanity of a people and and the sense of trauma that these people who have
Survived this will have for the rest of their lives that the extent to which the basic social fabric that makes us
More than simple animals
Has been destroyed is is is deeply profound and let me just add one sort of detail to this
Which is that
When we think of the number of people who are suffering from physical and mental disabilities
As a result of this just the number of child amputees is a very very
Straightforward visible tangible example. How are these young children going to be able to
Become food secure themselves? How are they going to have livelihoods?
How are they going to earn money? How are they going to be able to provide for families in in future the level of
vulnerability to to to
Destitution to food insecurity to hunger is so much higher as a result of this onslaught
Javier one of the words
That's always used for the Palestinians, whether it's in the occupied west bank, whether it's in Gaza
Whether it's abroad is resilience. We are the Palestinians. We are used to this
We will you know resist in our own little ways and there is a certain amount of that that is true
But I'm speaking to people now and everybody is getting much more and more
Frustrated at this idea that the world's ignoring us because we've been through
Since 1948
So everybody's just used to it. You've got to how would you kind of combat that?
If you were speaking to somebody from say the un who was like, you know, maybe we should give them some money
But maybe not they've been going through this for far too long
And then I think we should not romanticize resilience. We should be very proud of Palestinian resilience
Since 1948. However, this is not how a people should be living
We are in a constant state of
Struggling I mean today
People are celebrating Easter to give an example and even in order to get to a church people have to
Actually fight for the right even praying has become an act of persistence
Under Israeli occupation or to talk, of course about al-Aqsa mosque being closed during most of the holy month of ramadan
So in other words when we talk about Palestinian resilience
I think it involves all aspects of Palestinian life that people should not get used to it
People should get to act in order for Palestinians to be able to enjoy
The rights and here I think Imran what what's extremely important is as we've been talking about
this program, is to make clear that what's happening with Palestinians, it's not just
a situation between Israel and Palestine, but it has an international responsibility
element that's not being met, as we speak.
Alex, one of the things about attention, global attention, when it comes to a particular
genocide like Gaza is that you get money. Don't step forward. It's a thing that
pushes, that publicity almost pushes somebody to do something, but when the
spotlight disappears, that money also disappears, right?
That's correct. And we have the one, two terrible punch, not only is the publicity
vanishing and therefore the public funding, but also aid budgets are being cut and not just
in the United States. The United Kingdom is now giving a lower proportion of its GDP per capita
as international aid than at any time in the last 60 years, and that is absolutely shocking.
The funds for this are drying up and people are being left on their own and however resilient,
however steadfast they are, there comes a point at which human life simply cannot be
sustained under this pressure. I want to thank our guests, Alex DeWall, Javier
Abouid and Dr. Mohamed Tahir, and thank you too for watching. You can see the program again
anytime by visiting our website, aljazeera.com, and for further discussion,
go to our Facebook page, that's facebook.com forward slash AJ Inside Story.
And you can also join the conversation on X. Our handle is at AJ Inside Story.
That's it from me, Imran Khan, and the team here in Doha. Stay with us for more coverage
of the war between the US, Israel and Iran. Coming up in just a minute.
As the war continues, uncertainty hangs over everyday life, especially when it comes to
how long it will take. It's the very ordinary citizens who continue to pay the price.
And in-depth reports. Iranian officials are denying this,
the foreign minister, saying that they're not looking for a ceasefire. They want a
comprehensive end of this war. From the heart of the story.
We have a list here that the Iranians have published about the civilian facilities that
have been struck, that is for Iranians red line. Hard-hitting interviews.
Anyone could become a target. We have seen that they have no hesitation about targeting any
place. Facing realities. Does Qatar still trust Iran enough to mediate? Let's say that this
aggression brings a benefit for no one. Thought-provoking answers.
How many have been displaced inside Iran? I've heard three million. It could be more.
Hear their story on Talk to Al Jazeera. Police say the 98 people arrested will face
misdemeanor charges ranging from criminal trespass to resisting arrest. There's an
intense security presence outside of the federal courthouse where international media
are packing the sidewalks. So are demonstrators. Some of them celebrating Majuro's arrest.
Others calling for his release. Al Jazeera, wherever you are.
Hello, this is Al Jazeera live from Doha with our continuing coverage of the war
between the US, Israel and Iran. I'm Malin Said. Coming up in the next 60 minutes.
Donald Trump sets a Tuesday deadline for Iran to reopen the Strait of Hormuz.
All the US will bomb its power plant, bridges and quote, unleash hell.
We are determined to defend. Iran's foreign ministry dismisses the US president's warning
and vows a swift retaliation to any US attacks. US troops rescue a second airman
in a high-stakes mission in Iran two days after his fighter jet went down.
And we'll be live from the site of an Israeli airstrike on Lebanon's capital.
At least three people have been killed. Rescuers in the northern Israeli city of Haifa look for
the missing after an Iranian strike targets an apartment complex for people.
US President Donald Trump has renewed threats to destroy Iranian power plants and bridges
if it doesn't reopen the Strait of Hormuz. He shared what appears to be a deadline on
social media Tuesday 8 p.m. Eastern Time. Earlier, Trump posted an expletive
laden threat to his truth social account. It promised that Iranians would be quote,
living in hell if the Strait isn't reopened. Tehran has emphasized that it will retaliate
if struck the foreign ministry spokesman Ismail Baghe says any US related location
in the Middle East would be a target.
Our armed forces have made it clear that in case Iran's infrastructure is attacked,
we would react in kind. They would our armed forces would target any similar infrastructure
that is owned or in any way or manner related to the United States or contributes to their
act of aggression against Iran. Well that's all as missile strikes pound the region.
An Iranian missile struck this residential building in the northern Israeli port city of Haifa.
In Iran, a US Israeli attack has killed at least five people in the city of Qom south of Tehran.
And Israeli attacks have bombarded the southern suburbs in the Lebanese capital of Beirut.
We'll be live from Tehran in a moment but first Al Jazeera's Mike Hannah has more on
President Trump's comments from Washington D.C. The unusual use of an expletive by a national
leader perhaps a symbol of President Trump's frustration with the Iranian government and
their refusal to concede to the demands that he is making. That reference as well was to
the Strait of Hamouz which in recent days President Trump had insisted he did not care
about saying the US did not need the oil passing through the Strait and it was up to the countries
who are reliant on that oil to deal with the situation. But now the demand about opening
the Strait of Hamouz appears front and center of the President's new demands of the Iranian
government. President Trump threatening to and I use his words blowing everything and taking
the oil if Iran does not meet his new deadline which has now been set at 8 p.m. eastern time
on Tuesday evening. He says in an earlier media post that a power plant day and bridge day
all wrapped up on Tuesday. But on the other hand in addition to these threats
President Trump is sending signals that there's some kind of negotiation process underway.
He's indicated that his close confidants Jared Kushner and Stephen Whitcoff are in consultation
with either the Iranian government and identified figures or some form of intermediary. And speaking
to US news outlets President Trump says that he is optimistic that there can be an agreement
very soon. He says the agreement could come within a matter of days rather than a matter
of weeks. So you've got this dichotomous approach from the President on the one hand threatening
obliteration to civilian targets within Iran which some observers would contend to be a war
crime. But on the other hand what he is saying is yes we are talking the talks are going well
and they could come to fruition before that new deadline I set which is 8 p.m. eastern time
on Tuesday. Mike Hannah, Al Jazeera, Washington. Well the speaker of Iran's parliament has also
responded to Trump in a social media post. Mohammed Bagheh Gali Baf wrote quote your
reckless moves are dragging the United States into a living hell for every single family and
our whole region is going to burn because you insist on following Netanyahu's commands.
Make no mistake you won't gain anything through war crimes. Let's bring in Mohammed Val
who is life for us into Iran Mohammed. So Iran's standing firm against President Trump's threat
to target its power plants if the Strait of Hormuz is not reopened. He's also been accusing Washington
of potential war crimes. What else have we heard from Iran today? Well that's right many Iranian
leaders have been expressing the same ideas particularly over the last 24 hours as that
deadline approaches and we have more statements from the foreign minister,
ministry spokesman Ismail Bagheh aside from what you have mentioned in your intro here. So
talked about the foundational principles of Iran's approach and why Iran thinks that it has
the right to defend itself in this war and that it is waging a legal war an existential war.
On the other hand he described the American war as illegal and as a war that is imposed on everyone
and also as a war that is based on a series of lies including the lie that Iran has been pursuing
the production of a nuclear weapon also that Iran has been presenting an imminent threat to the
United States and also that this war is waged for the liberation of the Iranian people.
So basically the leaders here are reiterating the same thing that they have been saying from day one
that nothing no threats no amount of threats by the Americans is going to change the course of
action as Iranians have decided on it and that also the Strait of Hormuz by the way the commander
of the IRGC said once again that the Strait of Hormuz will not return to the status to the
situation that was before the war and that from now on it's not only going to be under the control
of Iran but it is also going to be a source of income for Iran Iran is going to and this is not
his statement today but they have been saying this many times during the last few days that
Iran is going to impose a new system a new approach on the state of Hormuz whereby Iran
can extract fees from ships that pass through the state to compensate for the for the loss
and the destruction that has been inflicted on the country since the beginning of this war.
So they are very clearly adamant that they are not going to change course they're not going to
be intimidated by the threats and that they can defend themselves also by way of retaliation
they're going to strike back on similar facilities across the region if the power plants in Iran
are destroyed by the Americans. Meanwhile Mohammed on the ground attacks on Iran have continued
we're hearing of attacks in Boucher province now this is of course where the Boucher nuclear
power plant is so what more can you tell us about those attacks and how serious they are?
Well in just a few moments ago there were blasts across the capital particularly the
outskirts of the city at the south and the west and the southeast big blasts reported by
people who are the eyewitnesses and so on we were not aware of specific targets that have been hit
but that has been happening just a while ago but also we have the longest series of cities
today that have been bombarded across the country particularly in the south we have
Mahshahr city we have we have Bandar Lenge we have Kung city where six people were killed in 17 were
wounded according to local sources Shiraz Isfahan Karaj and also Qom you have mentioned that five
people were killed in Qom so it's a relentless ongoing campaign across the country but most
importantly Boucher is drawing a lot of attention and a lot of concern because of this fifth
strike on Boucher power plant that's the only power plant that is it is functioning the country
it has a tremendous amount of radioactive material in it and there are fears not only Iran but also
in the world and particularly by the IAEA that if this this plant is if it is
exploded if it explodes then it will create a catastrophe not only Iran but also across
the Gulf region because it is very close to many of the countries in that region okay thank you for
that Mohammed Vow with the very latest from Tehran well the threat of escalation in Iran puts the Gulf
region squarely in the crossfire the site Tehran is threatening to hit back are almost entirely
located in GCC countries which are already coping with daily attacks Kuwait says it's been hit
by a series of drone attacks authorities have reported two major power and desalination plants
were targeted one of the facilities is in Al-Zur nearly 90 kilometers south of Kuwait city
and another attack hit the finance ministry complex which is a building in central Kuwait
city in Bahrain Iran targeted an oil facility sparking several fires there emergency response
team said the blaze has been fully extinguished over the past few weeks manama has come under
repeated Iranian missile and drone attacks let's go to Mohammed Jab June who's based here in the
Qatari capital Doha Mohammed so attacks in Gulf countries continuing in the last 24 hours and
now of course countries are preparing for a possible escalation if Donald Trump carries out
his threats what can you tell us yeah that's right Malin it's a very tense moment right now
in this region let me first bring our viewers up to speed on what we've heard from some of the
attacks that have taken place over the course of the last few hours there have been statements from
the Ministry of Defense in the United Arab Emirates as well as the Ministry of Defense
in Kuwait that both countries have been intercepting drones and missiles launched
toward them from Iran as we get more details about those series of attacks we will bring
them to you now in the meantime as you mentioned of course countries like Bahrain the UAE Kuwait
have all been dealing with severe attacks on critical infrastructure in those countries from
Iran the past few days including as you mentioned water facilities desalination plants energy
facilities energy infrastructure civilian infrastructure and one of the reasons people
are so on edge right now is because of the fact that we now are on the eve of this imposed
deadline by Donald Trump for Iran to reopen the Strait of Hormuz to open it fully as he says
the deadline that Donald Trump has put forth is 8 p.m. on Tuesday it would be about 24 hours from
now and Donald Trump has threatened that if the Strait of Hormuz is not open by then that
he will go ahead and bomb power plants bridges other sites in Iran and what we've heard
from Iran in the past is that if that goes ahead they will then retaliate by targeting
those types of facilities in this region and beyond so that's one of the reasons why
countries here are so concerned at this very perilous moment now the posture from these
Gulf countries when it comes to Iran has been a defensive one up until now but they've also
stated repeatedly in the past that their patience is not limitless so the question is
if the US goes ahead and starts attacking hard these types of targets in Iran in 24
hours or so from now what will Iran do how will that impact these countries if such vital
infrastructure sites are targeted and what will they do going forward Malin Mohammed meanwhile
the focus on the Strait of Hormuz continues Iran though insisting that it's open and it's
been holding meetings with Oman what more do we know about those meetings so Malin what we've
heard from both the Omani government and the Iranian government is that there were talks
between both countries that transpired on Saturday and that at those talks there were officials from
the deputy foreign ministry level of both countries and that there were also experts involved in
those talks as well that they were looking for a way to try to make it easier for ships to
navigate the Strait of Hormuz going forward we also know that both countries have discussed
trying to put in place some type of monitoring authority authority for ships that would be
passing through the Strait of Hormuz they say that there are objectives that are being
discussed but the fact of the matter is we don't know what those objectives are and even
if those objectives were to be agreed to by let's say Iran and Oman would they be agreed to
by other GCC countries would they be agreed to by the U.S. particularly if the U.S. is not happy
with what may have been accomplished or the timeline in which it might be accomplished
what would the U.S. do would they escalate their attacks with Israel on Iran and what would
Iran do when it comes to retaliation so many questions at this very critical juncture and
as you heard Mohammad volunteer on saying a few moments ago Iranian officials have said openly
that they are thinking about putting in place some type of tolling system when it comes to ships
trying to pass through the Strait of Hormuz that also begs a question as to what happens if
that were to be implemented how it would be implemented we're at a time right now when over
the course of the past 48 72 hours we've heard that several countries have been able to get
certain ships through the Strait of Hormuz does that mean that they are talking with the
Iranian officials does that mean they're coming up with agreements we just don't know at
this point but there is so much concern because that is a chokehold as you know 20 percent
the world's energy sources pass through the Strait of Hormuz.
The Iranians want to maintain that leverage over that critical area in the world
and what these talks may achieve, very much going to be also dependent upon
how the rest of the world reacts to whatever objectives are agreed to going forward.
Mali.
Okay, thank you very much for that update.
Mohamed Jamjoon, Leverus, in Doha.
While a U.S. airman has been rescued in Iran after an intense 48-hour search operation,
the Weapons Systems Officer had been missing since Friday
when the fighter jet he was in went down in the province of Kogi Lie and Boya Ahmad.
Tehran said it shot down the F-15E, a two-seater aircraft.
John Henry reports from Washington.
It was a daring and risky mission to save an American airman from becoming an Iranian prisoner of war.
Iranian forces searched the mountainous areas of southwestern Iran
after an F-15E fighter jet went down on Friday.
It was the first time a U.S. aircraft had crashed in hostile territory in the five-week-old war.
Two Blackhawk helicopters took fire as U.S. teams raced to find the missing crew member.
An A-10 Warthog, an air support aircraft, was also damaged,
its pilot ejecting over the Gulf.
Iran broadcast photos of what it said was debris from the fighter jet, including a jump seat.
Although the pilot had been rescued on Friday, the weapon specialist remained in hiding,
evading Iranian forces for two days.
Finally, early on Sunday, deep in Iranian territory, the U.S. search operation was successful.
President Donald Trump made the announcement on social media, posting,
We Got Him, saying the Colonel had been behind enemy lines
in the treacherous mountains of Iran being hunted by our enemies.
He said U.S. forces had been monitoring his location 24 hours a day
and sent dozens of aircraft armed with the most lethal weapons in the world to retrieve him.
Trump added he sustained injuries, but he will be just fine.
A U.S. official told Al Jazeera the rescue operation began in darkness
but ended in an intense firefight and daylight
before dozens of heavily armed aircraft and hundreds of troops transported the airmen out of Iran.
A U.S. officer in Iranian custody could have given Iran leverage,
as it had when Iran took U.S. hostages in 1979.
With that crisis averted, attention now shifts to the U.S. deadline for Iran to open the Strait of Hormuz.
John Hendren, Al Jazeera, Washington.
As reported in John's story, U.S. officials say the rescue mission involves several aircraft.
Iranian state media released these pictures reportedly showing the wreckage of a C-130 aircraft in Isfahan province.
American media reporting U.S. forces destroyed at least one of their own planes on purpose
because it had become stuck and unable to fly out.
Iranian armed forces dispute those series of events, claiming its soldiers destroyed two C-130 aircraft
and two Black Hawk helicopters in what it characterized as a failed U.S. rescue operation.
With God's help and support and through the vigilance and readiness of the fighters of Islam in the armed forces,
using electronic warfare, advanced new air defense systems, the implementation of a ground mosaic defense plan
and the creation of a military and security cordon,
a number of these aircraft including two C-130 military transport planes and two Black Hawk helicopters
were hit and forced to make emergency landings in an area south of Isfahan.
After Iranian Islamic fighters completed the operation to encircle the enemy
in order to prevent the disgrace of Trump, the President of the United States,
and the hollow prestige of the army was forced to carry out heavy bombing of its downed aircraft,
equipment, commanders and soldiers.
In Lebanon, the Israeli army has carried out new strikes on Beirut's southern southern
in a densely populated residential area. The death toll has now risen to at least five,
including three Sudanese nationals.
Fifty-two others were injured in those strikes.
Three others have been killed in an airstrike on the hills of Ain Sadi.
Israel says its continuing attacks on his bullet military infrastructure
so far over a million people have been forcibly displaced across the country.
They hit a completely civilian area. It's mostly migrants here, Sudanese people.
People were at home and they struck them. Are those military objectives?
Where is the UN? No one says anything. Aren't they human too?
They're killing children and women. The whole world has to speak up.
It has to see and say something. Have we become nothing but numbers,
people of numbers? How is that possible?
We are devastated. Our morale is low.
When you see your friends and neighbours in pieces on the ground
and blood everywhere and the house destroyed, our house was destroyed.
Where are we going to sleep? Where do we go?
Well, we can speak to Haidi Perch.
She's live from the site of the latest attack on Ain Sadi in East Beirut.
So Haidi, what are you learning about what was hit there?
Speaking to neighbours and first responders at the scene of this latest Israeli strike,
what we understand is that this residential building was hit on Sunday evening.
A projectile came in through the roof.
It then crashed through the third floor apartment
and exploded inside the second floor apartment.
You can see there's quite extensive damage there to that middle apartment.
That resulted in three deaths inside that apartment
and injuries to the people in the one below that.
Now, among the dead here tonight is a local leader from the Lebanese forces.
That's a right-wing Christian party with a long history in this area.
His name was Pier Mawad and among the other dead was his wife
and one person who was visiting them in their home.
Now, that has drawn concern and condemnation from his parliamentary colleagues.
And speaking to people here on the scene this evening,
there is a real atmosphere of fear and upset shock
but also a great deal of mistrust.
It's difficult to get a straight story about exactly what happened here
because many people assume that the target of this strike was in fact
the one on the top floor where the projectile first came in.
Now, what we're told is that that apartment was actually empty at the time
but as happens, a lot of the time when we see these attempted assassination strikes
from the Israeli military, when they come in, they target one particular floor
or one particular room in a residential apartment building
rather than these large strikes is that rumors start flying around about
well, who was in that building? Who were they going after?
And in this neighborhood, a Christian neighborhood in East Beirut,
people are confused about that and they're very, very suspicious
and so we're seeing these statements in the immediate aftermath from MPs
saying that there should be roadblocks, there should be further stringent conditions
on who is allowed into neighborhoods and while yes, people should,
the displays should be looked after, that they should be looked after
in official shelters rather than welcomed into neighborhoods.
Now speaking to people here, they say that apartment was empty.
The owner was on scene earlier and said that he hadn't rented it to anybody
but the fact that people jumped to this immediate conclusion
that someone displaced must have been sheltered here
and that's why the Israelis have struck this area where someone
felt that they should have been safe
gives you an indication of the level of tension and fear that these strikes
are creating across Lebanon. We've seen this increased pattern
of Israel striking outside areas where people would expect
which is, you know, sheer areas of the country and sheer parts of Beirut
and it's creating this real atmosphere of fear in mistrust
which we have absolutely seen here this evening in East Beirut.
Okay, thank you so much for that update.
Heidi Pat there for us live in Beirut.
Where Israel's forced evacuation orders have displaced hundreds of thousands
in southern Lebanon, Thai resident Jamal Saleem Farhan says
he won't leave his home despite repeated Israeli bombings.
Rescue workers in Israel are searching for people
who fear trapped under the rubble of a building hit by an Iranian strike on Haifa.
The residential structure partially collapsed after the attack on Sunday.
Israeli authorities say four people have been wounded.
One person is in critical condition.
Let's go to Rob McBride who's following developments
from the Jordanian capital Amman.
What more do we know about this attack?
Yeah, that's right. This search operation is continuing
during the hours of darkness according to the chief of Haifa's fire
rescue service.
This is, he says, the most severe single incident
they've had to deal with since the start of this conflict.
And now Haifa has found itself pretty much on the front line
since the start of fighting.
It's an important transport and industrial hub.
It's also a center for a lot of Israel's oil refining.
So as such it is a prime target for Iranian missiles
but also because of its proximity to the Lebanon border
in the north of Israel.
It is also within rocket range of Hezbollah unit
so often finds itself the target for coordinated attacks.
The authorities say that this was a single warhead
that got past the missile defenses
and quite a heavy warhead that struck this building.
Now, the building is in danger of collapse
which makes the search operation all the more difficult
and hazardous.
It's also, there is the possibility
of being reported from the scene of unexploded ordnance
of parts of this warhead that haven't gone off.
So that again is complicated things.
And so a specialist national search unit
has been brought in to help.
It struck the lower floor of this apartment block
which caused the apartments above it to partially collapse
and the four people who are still unaccounted for
are believed to be from one of the more heavily damaged apartments.
Meanwhile, Israel throughout Sunday found itself
the target of four separate missile salvos,
one of them on the Neot-Hovav industrial center.
This is an industrial area in the south of the country
near to Beersheba city.
It has been struck before three times,
the last time a week ago, which started a fire
in a chemical plant.
So there is a real concern about these vulnerable targets
as we get into this tit for tat between Israel and Iran,
attacking each other's infrastructure
such as petrochemicals and petrol production
and refining facilities.
Okay, thank you for that, Rob McBride.
Following developments from Israel out of Oman.
Thank you.
Now Russia's state nuclear company says
it's evacuated nearly 200 workers
from Iran's Boucher nuclear plant in the south.
It's after a strike near its vicinity,
killed a security guard and damaged a support building.
Russia partly constructed the Boucher nuclear plant in Iran
and helps operate it.
Iran says the plant has been attacked four times
since the war began.
The International Atomic Energy Agency
has expressed deep concern and has called for de-escalation.
The head of the World Health Organization
has also raised the alarm saying in a statement,
the latest incident involving the Boucher nuclear power plant
is a stark reminder, a strike could trigger
a nuclear accident with health impacts
that would devastate generations.
With every passing day of this escalating conflict,
the stakes and threats are raised higher and higher.
We must de-escalate now.
Peace is the best medicine.
Akshay Dhiras is a research scientist
at the University of Reading.
He says an attack on the Boucher power plant
would cause radioactive leakage.
I think it's very important to keep in mind
that nuclear reactors are designed to be safe
and this particular reactor in Boucher
has been hit four times in the past since two months,
but so far there has not been any major radiation leak as such.
If you assume a really worst-case scenario,
that strike is really bad and it starts creating problems.
The very first thing that's going to happen
is that areas around the nuclear power plant
will be impacted because the radioactive stuff
will start getting into the air.
It will also start getting into the water
and it will not be an area where people can live
because it will just create damage to their health
and eventually what really would matter
is how much this radioactive stuff is able to spread further,
but we don't know that at the moment.
The first thing that's just going to happen
is that radioactive stuff will get into the air
that could be isotopes of iodine or cesium.
They will also get into water,
which means that the water is not going to remain
safe for any operations, be it decentralization
or even the marine life is going to be impacted over there.
For people, the very first thing is like those living
near the reactor, they will have to evacuate
because the air will really become toxic
and if it starts spreading further,
just talking about countries surrounding the Persian Gulf,
so if the leakage is really strong,
then I would say there will be some impact,
but that will be mainly through water
and other countries like Qatar and Kuwait
because of the distance between Iran and these countries.
Disruption to shipping through the strait of Hormuz
is reshaping regional energy routes
with Pakistan emerging as an alternative corridor.
Higher costs, tighter fuel availability
and peak summer demand are placing
increasing strain on energy systems.
Osama bin Javed reports from Karachi Port.
There's a rush to reach Karachi Port.
The facility has handled more traffic in a month
than the whole of last year.
That's because Pakistan as Iran's neighbour
offers some of the first safe seaports
as ships exit the strait of Hormuz.
The crisis comes as Pakistan's preparing for peak summer demand.
It's headed towards a deepening energy crunch
across both the power sector and fuel supply chain.
The biggest challenge is liquefied natural gas or LNG
which accounts for more than 21% of electricity generation.
Officials say supplies could fall to near zero from April.
At the same time, the global energy shock
is feeding directly into domestic costs.
Pakistan is operating with just 24 days of gasoline
and diesel stocks.
War risk insurance premiums for tankers
have surged more than tenfold.
Rate rates have quadrupled.
To manage volatility, the government
has moved to weekly fuel price adjustments.
Industry analysts describe March as the moment
Pakistan's energy system was stress test.
It's more severe external shock
than the 1970s oil crisis.
Pakistan moved quickly on multiple fronts simultaneously.
Diplomatically, it secured rerouted cargos
through the Red Sea port of Janpo.
Naval escorts kept tankers moving through contested corridors.
Pakistani flag tankers have also passed
the strait with permission from Iran.
It was a very coherent institutional response
that operated faster than most observers expected.
Now, a hybrid strategy is in the making
to keep the lights on.
It includes limited daily load shedding,
compulsory conservation measures
and higher electricity tariffs.
The government is offering a $7 a month targeted relief
for motorcyclists and rickshaw drivers,
even as it increases petroleum levees
to manage fiscal pressure.
Oil tankers like these provide the nearly 80%
of energy that Pakistan requires
coming from the strait of Hormuz.
Pakistan says energy, security and diplomacy
cannot be separated.
And what it is trying to do is to find common ground
between the three spheres
so it can bring some sort of normalcy to the equation.
After hosting regional diplomats,
Islamabad is also pushing for wider international engagement,
including with China,
to build momentum for de-escalation.
At the same time, Pakistan is trying
to turn crisis into opportunity.
Plans are underway for a maritime energy city
and new deep sea ports,
aimed at transforming the country
into a regional hub for energy storage
and trans-shipment.
But all of it depends on one thing
and end to hostilities.
Because until then, Pakistan remains exposed
to the conflict and as one energy expert stated,
putting the oil genie back in the barrel.
You're watching Al Jazeera,
a reminder of our top stories this hour.
U.S. President Donald Trump has renewed his threats
to attack Iran's infrastructure.
If it doesn't reopen the strait of Hormuz,
he says U.S. forces will strike
Iranian power plants and bridges,
otherwise, if a deal is breached by Tuesday.
Iran, meanwhile, has vowed to retaliate if attacked.
It promises to launch reciprocal strikes
on U.S.-linked infrastructure in the Middle East.
Iran's parliament speakers also accuse
Trump of, quote, war crimes.
GCC states faced another day
of Iranian attacks in Bahrain
and oil tanker caught fire
following a drone strike on Sunday.
And in Kuwait,
two power and water desalination plants were damaged.
Qatar also intercepted several drone and missile attacks.
U.S. President Donald Trump
has given Iran shifting deadlines
to reopen the strait of Hormuz.
That's as Iran insists
the key waterway isn't actually closed,
and that only ships that belong to its enemies
are barred from passage.
Trump issued his first statement
about the strait back on March 21.
He threatened that the U.S.
would bomb Iran's power plants
if the strait wasn't reopened within 48 hours.
He later extended that deadline by five days,
claiming that negotiations with Iran were underway.
Trump then issued a new deadline on March 26.
The time he gave Iran 10 days,
or until the evening of April 6
to reopen the strait.
Trump has issued his last statement
that Trump has issued his latest Hormuz threat
on Sunday after vowing to bomb power plants
and bridges if Tehran doesn't comply.
He posted what appears to be
a Tuesday 8 p.m. deadline for a deal.
Okay, let's unpack this with our guests.
We've got Ross Harrison, a senior fellow
at the Middle East Institute,
author of Decoding Iran.
foreign policy. He joins us from Washington DC and we have Adam Weinstein, who is the Middle East
Deputy Director at the Quincy Institute. He is in New York for us. Thank you to both of you. Adam,
if I could start with you. So, you as President Donald Trump setting a new deadline for Iran to
reopen the Strait of Hormuz. So we now, he's now saying Tuesday 8 p.m. Eastern time, according
to his latest post on Truth Social. Given his track record of shifting ultimatums,
how seriously should we take this latest one? You know, look, it's always a what if with him.
I just don't know how seriously to take it because the way he crafts foreign policy is in a
impulsive manner. But for the Iranians, I don't think the calculus has changed all that much
because their goal here is survival. And they view a concession in the Strait of Hormuz without
some kind of reciprocal guarantee as a threat to their survival, even if it ends the war.
Ross, to you on the one hand, Trump is publicly taunting and threatening Iran. But in interviews,
we saw one he did on Fox News recently. He suggested a deal could be reached
within days. He said that before, from Tehran's perspective, how difficult does that make it
to interpret U.S. intentions? Well, I think they're accustomed to Donald
Trump's style at this point. I think they assume that what they're seeing in terms of
Donald Trump's, frankly, escalatory language and profane language is a sign of frustration
and a sign that there may be fewer options available to the United States to achieve the
goal of opening the Strait of Hormuz. So I think they're interpreting this as, to some degree,
success of their policy of sort of boxing Donald Trump in. And the fact that I think
that they assume that this kind of escalatory language is going to be followed by some
kind of escalation on the ground in the coming days. That would probably be their assumption
whether, in fact, that plays out what remains to be seen.
Adam, is there a coherent U.S. strategy here or is policy being made in real time?
No, I think policy is being made in real time. I don't think there's a
well thought out interagency process in terms of crafting policy. I think the policy that
comes out of the White House, like I said before, is extremely impulsive. And I think we
have to keep in mind the context of all of this, that now the stated end goal of this
war is to reopen the Strait of Hormuz, which was opened the day before the war began.
I mean, this is a circular foreign policy. It's a war that was launched without real
congressional approval, without a clear achievable end state.
Adam, you're a former U.S. Marine. How concerned are you about Mission Creep here?
I'm very concerned about Mission Creep. I mean, I think the idea that we're going
to launch a full-scale invasion of Iran, I think that's probably hyperbole at this point,
because there's simply not enough troops in the region or on the way to the region to make that
happen. But if the Trump administration were to decide to seize an island or to enter coastal
Iran for a brief period, I think things can get out of control very quickly, as we saw
over the last 48 hours. War is unpredictable.
Ross, how do the Iranian leadership feel about the prospect of American boots on the ground?
Well, I'm sure they're not, they don't anticipate it in any kind of a positive way,
though I think they're probably spent the last number of weeks preparing for it.
I think that they are recognizing that this boots on the ground approach may not have a
clear political objective, Maline, that if in fact the boots on the ground
will be used to try to open the Strait of Hormuz, it's likely to do the opposite.
I think they understand that, which is the way they're interpreting Donald Trump's tantrum
this morning, they're interpreting that I think to some degree as a recognition
of the fact that Donald Trump understands that a boots on the ground approach is not
going to achieve the objective that it's purported to have, which is to open the Strait,
because the minute the Strait becomes a combat zone, ships aren't going to go through.
So I think it's a recognition on the part of the Iranians that the United States might
not have a clear political objective and that there's really no way to achieve
the goal of opening the Strait with military means alone.
Adam, how does the US public factor into all this? Is this war beginning to hit Americans
directly, whether that be fuel prices or the unstable markets? To what extent is any
US decision making versus this war being driven by political pressure at home?
Well, anyone who's filled their car with gasoline knows that it's hitting Americans.
There's a long held attitude in Washington, I think, that Americans don't vote based on foreign
policy. It's a factor, but at the end of the day, they'll vote based on domestic policy,
and they don't always make the connection between things that are happening domestically
and their connection to foreign policy. So I think it's a factor. I don't think it's
an overwhelming factor, even though it's undeniable that this war is deeply unpopular
among the American public. But we also have to remember that the Iranians also have their own
politics. And again, I have to reiterate that I think what the Trump administration has miscalculated
about the Iranian regime is that its goal here is survival and it's willing to take
incredible losses to achieve that and not appear as if it's backing down to the United States.
I mean, we forget, historically, Iran was willing to take 200,000 losses
in the Iran-Iraq war before they finally agreed to bring an end to the war.
Of course, that was a war that was inflicted upon them, but the Iranian regime is not going
to negotiate at gunpoint in a way that looks like it's conceding to Trump's demands.
Ross, to you on that point, I mean, if Iran refuses to negotiate under threat of attack,
what options does it have to de-escalate without effectively surrendering key parts of its
economy, especially its energy sector? And as we heard there, there's also the
people of Iran to consider. You know, Malin, I think what Iran has done thus far in terms of
its war strategy over the last five weeks is it's expanded horizontally. And it has done that by
extending the war out to the Gulf Arab states, including Qatar. But I think if in fact there
is an attempt to escalate on the part of the U.S., I think you'll see even a further
escalation vertically. I think what the Iranians are calculating, Malin, is that if they see
facts on the graph, they see escalation on the ground and they see inflammatory language by
Donald Trump, that indicates to them that they have few options but to keep escalating or keep
fighting. I think what the signals they're going to be looking for in terms to de-escalate
are going to be a dialing back of the rhetoric, possibly an opening up of a real diplomatic
channel, not just with Steve Wittkopf and Jared Kushner, and some kind of actual de-escalation
on the ground. At that point, the Iranians are going to be faced with a decision. Do they de-escalate
or do they keep going? I think both parties are going to want to find an off-ramp, but I think
it's a matter of timing and which one leaves the battle the highest on the escalation ladder.
And on the off-ramp, Ross, we've been hearing about these discussions involving Oman in the
Strait of Hormuz, including ideas like transit fees tied to reparations. Is this Tehran
testing a diplomatic off-ramp? I don't think so. I think they're testing a possible regime
for after the war on how they manage transit and revenues after the war. But I think in terms
of signaling an off-ramp, I think they're going to be very careful about signaling an off-ramp
until they see some kind of de-escalation on the part of the United States. And the reason
for that, Malin, is very simple. They want to leave this war, they're determined to leave this war
having made the point that any kind of future attack will, that they will be able to exact a
price on the United States or on Israel or anybody that attacks them. And the way to do that is
to leave the war having re-established deterrence. If they're seen as de-escalating
prematurely, they will not have achieved their war objective. So it's a very
tricky tightrope over the next couple of days and weeks, I would say.
And Adam, to you finally, where do Gulf countries come into this? Because Iran has threatened to
attack more civilian infrastructure. That's already happening. We saw in Kuwait Iranian drone
attacks have damaged two power and water desalination plants. The worry is if the US attacks
Iran's energy sector further, the Gulf will continue to pay the price.
Well, first of all, I agree with everything that was just said by the other guest
in terms of Iran's calculation. Unfortunately, the Trump administration has shown that it
doesn't care about US partners. It doesn't care about the cost to US partners. I think the
strategy of Iran was to create chaos in the Gulf. And their hope was that they would
create enough pain for the Gulf countries, that those countries would go to Donald Trump and
say, hey, you need to find a resolution for this. We're your close friends and we're really hurting.
I don't know that the Trump administration really responds to that, which is unfortunate.
And the real tragedy of all of this is this shouldn't be taken out of context. We had a
nuclear deal. The Trump administration left that nuclear deal. We have to ask ourselves
why were hardliners inside Iran always so hostile towards diplomacy, but they don't seem
to have a problem with this kind of confrontation. It's because a war of choice by the United States
against Iran doesn't actually threaten regime survival. They're willing to take a lot of pain,
and they're very motivated to restore deterrence, as the other guest said.
The only time that we've seen real flexibility on the part of the Iranians is when a US
government was willing to work with the more pragmatic actors inside the Iranian government
towards a diplomatic solution, which is what the Trump administration should do. But I don't know
if they've realized that yet. Okay. Thank you to both our guests, Ross Harrison and Adam Weinstein.
Thank you. Let's take a look at some of the world's other news. In the Gaza Strip, Hamas says
it won't hand over its weapons. Disarmament is part of the second phase of the Gaza
ceasefire plan, but the armed group says calls to lay down its weapons are unacceptable,
especially as Palestinians continue to be targeted by Israel. More than 700 have been killed
since the ceasefire came into effect in October. As for raising the issue of weapons in this
crude manner, it is nothing but a scandalous attempt by the occupation to continue killing
and genocide against our people, which we will not accept under any circumstances.
We affirm that what the enemy was unable to seize from us with tanks and genocide,
it will not seize from us with politics or at the negotiation table. The occupation's aggression
against our people and its continued closure of the blessed al-Aqsa mosque to worshipers
in an unprecedented manner and the approval of the law for executing Palestinian prisoners,
we call upon the masses of our Palestinian people in the brave West Bank,
the blessed Jerusalem and the occupied interior to march toward al-Aqsa mosque.
The hundreds of thousands of Palestinians made homeless by Israel's worn Gaza every day as a
struggle. As bombed out neighborhoods are slowly cleared of rubble, some families
are collecting scrap metal in order to survive. Pani Mahmood reports from Gaza City.
Trucks arrive one after another, offloading what remains of homes, shops and entire streets.
Across large part of Gaza, rubble removal continues month after its raided bombardment,
flattening entire neighborhoods. But for some, these dumbing grounds are more than just fields
of debris. They are workplaces. Children searched the mountains of broken concrete and twisted
metal for anything they can sell. Wood, copper wire, aluminum. Each piece they collect means a
few more coins. Each truck brings another opportunity and another risk. The ground
is unstable. Sharp edges from broken walls. Aid agents is worn. Unexploded ordinance may
still be buried beneath the debris. Hassan Abdel-A'al lives in a tent near one of the dumbing sites.
We come here hoping to earn 20 shekels, about $6. But it comes at a cost. Injuries,
exhaustion, cuts everywhere. You can see the wounds and the blood.
The war has left hundreds of thousands of families without stable income.
Factories are shut. Shops are gone. Entire businesses reduced to dust.
Post-war recovery is measured by reconstruction in plans, funding and pledges. But here on the ground
recovery looks different. It looks like children navigating the rubble, household depending on
fragments of what was destroyed. As long as livelihood remains absent and reconstruction
uncertain, the rubble will continue to serve two purposes. One reminder of loss and for some people
it is a means of survival. Informal scrap collection has become one of the few ways to earn
cash. We come here to earn money for food. My father has no work, so we have to come.
We come here hoping to find bits of wood or pieces of cable that we can sell, anything that may help us
buy food for our children. We know climbing onto the moving trucks is dangerous, but when your
family depends on it, you take the risk. Parents say they don't want their children here,
but survival leaves little room for a choice.
Hany Mahmoud Al-Jazeera from Gaza City, Palestine
As Christians around the world mark the Easter holiday under the shadow of war,
religious leaders are calling for peace. Sonya Gago reports.
It is the most important date in the Christian calendar,
marked this year by both tradition and tension. Addressing more than a billion
Catholics worldwide from the Vatican, Pope Leo led his first Easter Mass as Pontiff,
and the message from St Peter's Square was shaped by events far beyond it.
Death is always lurking. We see it present in injustices, in partisan selfishness,
in the oppression of the poor, in the lack of attention given to the most vulnerable.
We see it in violence, in the ruins of the world, in the cry of pain that rises from every corner
because of the abuses that crush the weakest. An appeal for mercy as the conflict in the Middle
East loomed over what is meant to be a celebration of renewal, where despite air strikes and
destruction, many felt the need to commemorate the holiday. Over the weekend, the message
resonated in Germany in the annual Easter March in Cologne, not a religious procession,
but a demand for an end to hostilities. And in France, as the bells of Notre Dame in
Paris rang out, calling worshippers to mass. In Lyon, thousands of adults were baptized.
A sign said church leaders of the search for meaning in an evermore uncertain world.
Serbia says explosives have been found near a pipeline that carries Russian gas to Hungary.
Authorities say the discovery was made outside a Serbian town near the Hungarian border.
It comes just a week before closely watched elections in Hungary. Prime Minister Viktor
Orbán is fighting to extend his 16 years in power. He's linked Ukraine to those explosives.
Rights groups are warning about threats to media freedom in Sahel countries that have
seen military coups in recent years. Gender leaders are using security concerns and cyber
crime laws to silence criticism. Reporters Without Borders has condemned the sentencing
last week of the Marlion journalists convicted of insulting the military leader of Niger.
Imagine Kimber Reports.
Words can be life-changing. They certainly were for Yusuf Cisoko.
The publishing director of the Marlion newspaper, L'Alternance, or The Alternating.
This article accuses General Abdul Rahman Tieny, the military leader of neighbouring Niger,
of trying to distract people from his government's security failures.
Tieny had blamed the attacks on the international airport in the capital Niyami back in January
on France, the Ivory Coast and Benin without providing evidence.
The Islamic State claimed responsibility. The article argues Tieny overlooked the threat posed by armed
groups which he pledged to remove when he seized power in 2023. It also accuses what he calls
Tieny's military regime of economic suicide, citing the closure of borders with Benin.
Niger is a landlocked country which relied on its neighbours' ports for trade.
Cisoko was convicted last week of spreading false news, undermining the credibility of
the state and insulting a foreign head of state. He was fined $1,700 and sentenced to two years in prison.
This journalist would only speak anonymously for fear of reprisals.
It represents a setback for freedom of expression which is already under severe strain in Mali,
but we do not use hope that there is still the possibility of appeal.
Rather than the press law, Cisoko was charged under Mali's cyber crime law,
which allows journalists to be punished for criticising not just their own state,
but others in the Sahel.
Which makes the situation even more complex. Had it been handled as a press-related matter,
the sentence might not have been the same. I see this ruling as a strong message to
all media actors that things can go very far, so extreme caution is needed.
And this isn't just happening in Mali. In Niger and Burkina Faso, military-led governments
are restricting freedom of expression by suspending independent media outlets
and censoring and intimidating reporters. They're also targeting social media activists and
influencers. In Burkina Faso, some journalists who criticise the military have been
forcibly conscripted without training to fight against armed groups.
With the widening crackdown on independent journalism, the International Press Institute
is warning of an information blackout in the Sahel, which it says could have regional and
global consequences.
Imogen Kimber, Al Jazeera.
How much can AI be used to stop gun deaths?
That's the question being asked in Birmingham, Alabama, a city with a huge gun violence
problem.
It's just renewed a deal for a system of sensors that detects gunshots and then sends
drones to crime seats.
The critics say they target black communities and make little difference.
As Phil LaVell reports.
We'll see anything like that.
Cherie and Rosalyn are two mums with the most painful bond imaginable.
Imagine seeing your loved one shot over 12 or 13 times.
That picture would never go out my head.
Both received a heartbreaking call.
Their sons had been shot dead.
Different men, but same day, one year apart.
I remember that day like yesterday.
I remember pulling up on the scene and seeing the vehicle shot up blood on the car.
There are hundreds of stories like this here in Birmingham, Alabama.
All with the same ending.
Gun violence is rife.
Could AI have saved any of them?
It doesn't work now.
And that is what this is all about because AI is being used here to try to combat gun
violence.
There is this network of sensors dotted around listening for the sound of gun shots.
They hear them and they dispatch police automatically.
But where those sensors are located, that's what's controversial.
These devices are placed in predominantly poor neighborhoods.
They're placed in black and brown neighborhoods.
What it means is more police presence.
Multiple sensors.
The technology has been used in cities across the US for years.
Yet many are rolling it back or cancelling it all together.
But in this city, synonymous with the civil rights movement, they have just spent
millions of dollars to extend the contract.
On top of that, they've added drones which take off autonomously and can get
to the scene of any potential crime long before the police can.
Birmingham saw a 44% drop in homicides last year.
That is a 10 year low.
Another statistic, 88% of victims were black.
It's evident that it's not working.
It's not the technology that's keeping us safe.
And it may be other reasons why crime is not as prevalent.
The company behind the tech says it has seen a reduction of 61% in gunfire
incidents over the last two years.
And that it helps because up to 85% of gunshots are never reported by residents.
There are some areas where we do respond to shootings, but we don't get a 911 call.
We identify those areas as a priority.
And it is solely the police who choose which neighborhoods to put sensors in.
The family members that won't forget, that's retaliation.
That's what worries these mums.
Shootings lead to revenge and more shootings.
They spend their lives now consoling other parents and trying to break that cycle.
I'll never be healed until I make it up there.
That's my goal.
I'm going to make it up there with him.
For these mums, it is not about the sounds that are picked up, but the silence that follows
and the emptiness it leaves behind.
Phil Lavel, Al Jazeera, Birmingham, Alabama.
OK, we'll be back in just a moment.
More extensive coverage of the war between the US, Israel and Iran.
I'm Malin Sayid.
Stay with us.
On my left, you can see the thick column of the smoke.
That is the continuation of the American and Israeli strikes.
Women, children killed in an Israeli strike that targeted southern Lebanon.
Continuing to hear the sound of sirens, according to Israeli media, one drone has infiltrated
the Buddhist.
There is a move in Congress to basically tie Donald Trump's hands and end the conflict.
They say that's not America first, that's Israel first.
There is so much concern about what all this is going to do to energy markets, oil
prices, gas prices, not just in the region, but around the world.
Stay with Al Jazeera for the latest developments.
Can you really bomb a political future into existence?
I don't think that's what we're trying to do.
I think the objective here is to destroy the instruments of Iranian state power.
Up front tackles the big issues only on Al Jazeera.
Al Jazeera.
Hello, this is Al Jazeera live from Doha with our continuing coverage of the war
between the U.S., Israel and Iran.
I'm Malin Saeed.
Coming up in the next 60 minutes, Donald Trump sets a Tuesday deadline for Iran to reopen the
Strait of Hormuz.
All the U.S. will bomb its power plant's bridges and, quote, unleash hell.
We are determined to defend.
Iran's foreign ministry dismisses the U.S. president's warning and vows a swift
retaliation to any U.S. attacks.
U.S. troops rescue a second airman in a high-stakes mission in Iran two days after his
fighter jet went down and will be live from the site of an Israeli airstrike on Lebanon's
capital.
At least five people have been killed.
And rescuers in the northern Israeli city of Haifa look for the missing after an Iranian
strike, targets and apartment complex for people are injured.
U.S. President Donald Trump has renewed threats to destroy Iranian power plants and bridges
if it doesn't reopen the Strait of Hormuz.
He shared what appears to be deadline on social media Tuesday 8 p.m. eastern time.
Earlier, Trump posted an exclusive laden threat to his truth social account.
It promised that Iranians would be, quote, living in hell if the Strait isn't reopened.
Muntehran has emphasized that it will retaliate if struck.
The foreign ministry spokesman Ismail Baghe says any U.S. related location in the Middle
East would be a target.
Our armed forces have made it clear that in case Iran's infrastructure is attacked,
we would react in kind.
They would, our armed forces, would target any similar infrastructure that is owned
or in any way or manner related to the United States or contributes to their
active aggression against Iran.
Well, this comes as missile strikes pound the region and Iranian missiles struck
this residential building in the northern Israeli port city of Haifa.
In Iran, a U.S. Israeli attack has killed at least five people in the city of Qom
south of Tehran.
And Israeli attacks have bombarded the southern suburbs in the Lebanese capital of Beirut.
We'll be live from Tehran in a moment, but first Al Jazeera's Mike Hannah has more
on President Trump's comments from Washington, D.C.
The unusual use of an expletive by a national leader, perhaps a symbol of President Trump's
frustration with the Iranian government and their refusal to concede to the demands
that he is making.
That reference as well was to the Strait of Hormuz, which in recent days President Trump
had insisted he did not care about saying the U.S. did not need the oil passing through
the Strait and it was up to the countries who are reliant on that oil to deal with
the situation.
But now the demand about opening the Strait of Hormuz appears front and center of the
President's new demands of the Iranian government.
President Trump threatening to, and I use his words, blowing everything and taking the
oil if Iran does not meet his new deadline, which has now been set at 8 p.m. eastern time
on Tuesday evening.
He says in an earlier media post that a power plant day and bridge day all wrapped
up on Tuesday.
But on the other hand, in addition to these threats, President Trump is sending
signals that there's some kind of negotiation process underway.
He's indicated that his close confidants Jared Kushner and Stephen Whitcoff are in
consultation with either the Iranian government and identified figures or some form of
intermediary.
And speaking to U.S. news outlets, President Trump says that he is optimistic that
there can be an agreement very soon.
He says the agreement could come within a matter of days rather than a matter
of weeks.
So you've got this dichotomous approach from the President on the one hand threatening
obliteration to civilian targets within Iran, which some observers would
contend to be a war crime.
But on the other hand, what he is saying is, yes, we are talking.
The talks are going well and they could come to fruition before that new deadline
I set, which is 8 p.m. eastern time on Tuesday.
Mike Hanna, Al Jazeera, Washington.
The Speaker of Iran's parliament has also responded to Trump in a social media
post.
Mohamed Baga Ghalibath wrote, quote, your reckless moves are dragging the United
States into a living hell for every single family and our whole region is
going to burn because you insist on following Netanyahu's commands.
Make no mistake.
You won't gain anything through war crimes.
I spring in Mohamed Vahl, whose life for us in Tehran.
So Iran, standing firm there against President Trump's threat to
target his power plants if the Strait of Hormuz is not reopened, also accusing
Washington of potential war crimes.
What else has Iran been saying?
Well, that's right.
The spokesman of the Foreign Ministry, Ms. Ma'il Baqai, also said that Iran
has the legal foundations for what it is doing in this war because this war
is illegal and it is imposed on the Iranians and also on many other
people in the region and even on the United States.
He said that the war is based on a series of lies, the lie that Iran
has been pursuing the production of a nuclear weapon, the lie that Iran
has been presenting an imminent threat to the United States, and the
lie that this war is meant to liberate the Iranian people from their
despotic regime, as described by the United States.
For these reasons and for the aggression that is ongoing on Iran, Iran has
the right to defend itself and the Strait of Hormuz also is not going
to be subject to compromise or any other kind of giving in or so on.
By Iran, the commander of the IRGC has reiterated again that the Strait
of Hormuz will not return to the situation before this war and that
Iran is going to continue to control it.
There are also threats by Iranian officials that not only the Strait
of Hormuz but if this situation continues and the aggression on Iran
continues, maybe also the Strait of Bab-Mendab will be added anytime soon.
And that means Iran will have much more leverage in this war.
They are saying that Iran will defend itself no matter what and is not
going to surrender and it is not going to compromise on its national
sovereignty. The threats that are being repeated by the American
president are not causing Iranians, as they say here, to compromise or to be
afraid. And if their infrastructure is destroyed, they will do the same on
the other side across the region.
And meanwhile, Mohamed, we're hearing of attacks in Boucher province,
which is, of course, where the nuclear power plant is.
Tell us more about the attacks there and what else is happening across Iran.
Attacks are continuing as we speak.
Just a while ago, explosions in Tehran in many parts of Tehran, particularly
towards the outskirts, the south, the western, the southeast.
Huge explosions reported in those areas.
But not only Tehran, I can count at least 12 cities.
Most of them are in the south that have been hit today,
including Bandar Abbas and Ahfaz Airport.
Also, Mahshahr, also Bandar Lenge,
Kung City, where six people were killed, 17 were wounded.
Shiraz, Isfahan, Karaj to the west of Tehran.
And Qum, where five people were killed.
So many explosions, many raids on many cities in Tehran today.
But most alarming to many people here and even outside Iran
is the Bushar power plant that has been targeted for the fifth time in a row.
And people are concerned because that's the only functioning
nuclear power plant tension in the country.
And it is located very close also to many of the Gulf countries.
And if it explodes, then it will mean a nuclear catastrophe,
not only in Iran, but across the region.
OK, many thanks for that, Mohamed Vahl, with the very latest from Tehran.
The threat of escalation in Iran puts the Gulf region squarely in the crossfire.
The sites Iran is threatening to hit back are almost entirely
located in the GCC countries, which are already coping with daily attacks.
Kuwait says it's been hit by a series of drone attacks.
Authorities report two major power and desalination plants were targeted.
One of the facilities is in Al-Zor, nearly 90 kilometres south of Kuwait City.
Another attack hit the finance ministry complex.
That building is in central Kuwait city.
In Bahrain, Iran targeted an oil facility, sparking several fires.
Emergency response teams said the blaze has been fully extinguished.
Over the past few weeks, Manama has come under repeated Iranian missile and drone attacks.
Let's go to Mohamed Jamjoon, who was live for us in the Qatari capital, Doha.
So attacks across the Gulf in the last 24 hours.
And now they have the added pressure of preparing for an escalation
if Donald Trump carries out his threats.
What is the mood here?
Well, Malin, this is a critical juncture
and there is a huge amount of concern about what happens next.
Let me first just talk about the last attacks that we've heard about in the region.
In the last few hours, we've seen statements from the Ministry of Defense
in the United Arab Emirates, as well as the Ministry of Defense in Kuwait.
Both countries have said that their defense systems were intercepting missiles
and drones launched towards them.
So that's the latest we've heard.
As we get more details, of course, we will provide them to our viewers.
Now, as to the level of concern, we are at a juncture right now
wherein there is this latest threat from Donald Trump
that if by 8pm Eastern time on Tuesday,
if Iran has not reopened the Strait of Hormuz,
then essentially the U.S. will bomb energy sites,
power sites in Iran, and bridges amongst other potential targets.
The reason that is so concerning for Gulf countries
is because the Iranians have made it well known
that if targets like that are gone after in Iran,
then it is fair game for them to retaliate
by targeting similar sites in countries
in which they believe those sites are affiliated with the U.S.
And that means that potentially they could target energy sites,
civilian sites in Gulf countries.
And that is why people are so worried at this particular time.
Now, we've already seen over the course of this war,
desalination plants, energy infrastructure sites
in Gulf countries targeted, including the ones you mentioned
in Bahrain and Kuwait over the course of the last 48 hours.
So that is why people are so worried
about the rhetoric from Donald Trump,
who on one end is saying that they will go ahead
and attack all these sites in Iran,
and on the other end is suggesting
that perhaps negotiations are ongoing.
But it does not look as though de-escalation
is part of the equation at this point
when it comes to these countries.
They're very concerned.
And although these countries have maintained
a defensive posture when it comes to this conflict
up until now, they've also said
that their patience is not limitless.
And so it just leaves everybody wondering
as to what the next step will be.
If sites, civilian sites, energy infrastructure sites,
water desalination sites will continue
to be targeted in Gulf countries,
and what exactly comes next?
Malin.
Mohamed, Iran continues to insist
that the Strait of Hormuz is open.
It's been holding these meetings, hasn't it?
With Oman, what more do we know about what's being discussed?
What we know, Malin, is that there was a meeting
that was held on Saturday
between the Iranians and the Omanis.
You had, this was on the level
of the deputy foreign ministry.
And you had those officials from both countries
and you had experts from both countries.
And they were discussing, as it was laid out
in the statements that had been released thus far,
they were discussing how to try to put in place
a path forward for simplifying navigation
in the Strait of Hormuz.
It's known that these countries are considering
trying to set up some type of potential
monitoring mechanism for ships
that would go through the Strait of Hormuz
and that there are objectives that are being looked at.
But we don't yet know what those objectives are.
And here's where it gets complicated.
Is that even if those objectives may be agreed to
by the Omanis and the Iranians,
we do not yet know if other countries,
other countries in the Gulf, members of the GCC,
or if the US would agree to those objectives.
If the US does not agree, does that mean
that they escalate the conflict with Iran?
And then does Iran retaliate
against countries in the Gulf?
We do not yet know what other members
of the international community
might think of a potential deal.
We know that the Iranians have been discussing,
as we've heard from our correspondent
in Iran, Mohammed Vahl,
potentially trying to put some type of toll in place
for ships that would navigate the Strait of Hormuz.
We know, based on reporting we've heard the last few days,
that there are some ships from some countries
that have been potentially navigating
the Strait of Hormuz.
But where it all goes from here,
we just don't know and we don't yet know
if this will be a solution to this chokehold
that is currently going on in the Strait of Hormuz.
Okay, Mohammed.
Thank you for your reporting.
Mohammed Jam June there for us in Doha.
Now, a US airman has been rescued in Iran
after an intense 48-hour search operation.
The Weapon Systems Officer
had been missing since Friday
when the fighter jet he was in went down
in the province of Kogi Luye and Boya Ahmad.
Tehran said it's shot
down the F-15E, a two-seater aircraft. John Hendry reports from Washington.
It was a daring and risky mission to save an American airman from becoming an Iranian prisoner
of war. Iranian forces searched the mountainous areas of southwestern Iran after an F-15E fighter
jet went down on Friday. It was the first time a U.S. aircraft had crashed in hostile
territory in the five-week old war. Two Blackhawk helicopters took fire as U.S. teams raced to
find the missing crew member. An A-10 Warthog, an air support aircraft, was also damaged,
its pilot ejecting over the Gulf. Iran broadcast photos of what it said was debris from the
fighter jet, including a jump seat. Although the pilot had been rescued on Friday,
the weapon specialist remained in hiding, evading Iranian forces for two days.
Finally, early on Sunday, deep in Iranian territory, the U.S. search operation was successful.
President Donald Trump made the announcement on social media, posting,
We Got Him, saying the colonel had been behind enemy lines in the treacherous mountains
of Iran being hunted by our enemies. He said U.S. forces had been monitoring his
location 24 hours a day and sent dozens of aircraft armed with the most lethal weapons
in the world to retrieve him. Trump added, He sustained injuries, but he will be just fine.
A U.S. official told Al Jazeera the rescue operation began in darkness but ended in an
intense firefight and daylight before dozens of heavily armed aircraft and hundreds of
troops transported the airmen out of Iran. A U.S. officer in Iranian custody could have given
Iran leverage as it had when Iran took U.S. hostages in 1979. With that crisis averted,
attention now shifts to the U.S. deadline for Iran to open the Strait of Hormuz.
John Hendren, Al Jazeera, Washington. As reported in John's story, U.S.
officials say the rescue mission involves several aircraft. Iranian state media released
these pictures reportedly showing the wreckage of a C-130 aircraft in Isfahan Province. American
media reporting U.S. forces destroyed at least one of their own planes on purpose because it had
become stuck and unable to fly out. Iranian armed forces dispute those series of events,
claiming its soldiers destroyed two C-130 aircraft and two Black Hawk helicopters in
what it characterized as a failed U.S. rescue operation. With God's help and support and
through the vigilance and readiness of the fighters of Islam and the armed forces using
electronic warfare, advanced new air defense systems, the implementation of a ground mosaic
defense plan and the creation of a military and security cordon, a number of these aircraft
including two C-130 military transport planes and two Black Hawk helicopters were hit and forced to
make emergency landings in an area south of Isfahan. After Iranian Islamic fighters completed the
operation to encircle the enemy in order to prevent the disgrace of Trump, the president
of the United States, and the hollow prestige of the army was forced to carry out heavy
bombing of its downed aircraft, equipment, commanders and soldiers. Now to Lebanon,
where the Israeli army has carried out new strikes on Beirut's southern suburb
in a densely populated residential area, the death toll has now risen to at least five,
including three Sudanese nationals, 52 others were injured in those strikes. Three others have
been killed in an air strike on the hills of Ain Sadeh. Israel says its continuing attacks on
Hezbollah military infrastructure. More than a million people have been forcibly displaced
across the country. They hit a completely civilian area. It's mostly migrants here,
Sudanese people. People were at home and they struck them. Are those military objectives?
Where is the UN? No one says anything. Aren't they human too? They're killing children and women.
The whole world has to speak up. It has to see and say something. Have we become nothing
but numbers? Are people of numbers? How is that possible? We are devastated. Our morale is low.
When you see your friends and neighbors in pieces on the ground and blood everywhere and the house
destroyed, our house was destroyed. Where are we going to sleep? Where do we go? Let's go to
Heidi, parents whose life was in Beirut. What are you learning about what was hit
in these latest attacks? Yeah, we've just come back from the scene in Ain Sadeh,
which is a neighborhood in East Beirut up in the hills where there was an Israeli strike which hit
a residential building. Now the projectile came through the roof. It crashed through the third
floor apartment and exploded inside the second floor apartment. Now the official toll from the
Ministry of Health is that three people were killed in that apartment and then two others
were injured in the apartment below. It looks, it has all the hallmarks of what looks to be
another Israeli targeted assassination strike. This is where instead of leveling an entire
residential building as they have been doing regularly across the south of the country and
indeed in the southern suburbs, they target one specific apartment in a building or one room in
a hotel, but speaking to neighbors, speaking to the mayor, speaking to the head of the
neighborhood committee at that site in East Beirut, people were very confused. They couldn't
figure out why this particular building would have been targeted because they said that the
apartment on the third floor where the projectile first entered was empty at the time. There were
conflicting reports from the scene about whether anybody had been coming and going from that apartment
at the time, but the owner said no, it was empty. Nobody had been renting it, but the level of
fear and paranoia and mistrust in the streets there was very high because people now across
Beirut, when these areas are targeted outside of the southern suburbs, outside of
sheer areas or where Hezbollah supporters might live, people immediately jump to the conclusion
that, okay, well, maybe a displaced person or a displaced family who's fleeing those air strikes
and Israel is targeting them have moved into this neighborhood. And that was the fear and
the paranoia that was very, very present on the streets of that neighborhood this evening
when we went to visit. But the death toll across Lebanon continues to climb. The latest
numbers that we have from the Ministry of Health is that more than 1,400 people have been
killed in four weeks of war, 4,000 injured and among the dead 129 children.
Okay, Heidi, thank you for that. Heidi, pet their first live in Beirut. Israel's forced evacuation
orders have displaced hundreds of thousands in southern Lebanon as we were hearing there from
Heidi. Tire resident Jamal Saleem Tharan says he won't leave his home despite repeated Israeli
bombings.
Rescue workers in Israel are searching for people feared trapped under the rubble of a building
hit by an Iranian strike on Haifa. The residential structure partially collapsed after the attack
on Sunday. Israeli authorities say four people have been wounded and one person is in critical
condition. Rob McBride has been following developments from the Jordanian capital Amman.
Rob, what more do we know about this attack? Yeah, this search operation has been continuing
through the hours of darkness, the nighttime hours from Sunday now into the early hours
of Monday morning. According to Haifa's chief of fire and rescue, this is the most severe
single incident they've had to deal with, he says, since the start of this conflict.
And Haifa has found itself very much in the front line. It is a transport and industry hub.
It's also an important centre for the refining of oil for Israel. And given its proximity,
it's not only targeted by missiles from Iran, but also by rockets coming from Hezbollah in
Lebanon, given its proximity close to the border in northern Israel with Lebanon.
We understand from the authorities that this was a single heavy warhead which managed to
get past the missile defences and struck a single building causing the partial collapse.
And there's still a danger that the whole structure might collapse. There's also a danger
that there could still be some unexploded parts of the warhead beneath the rubble.
So this is requiring a specialist team to go through this search. They are looking specifically
for four people who are unaccounted for, who are all occupying one of the most severely damaged
apartments in this building. And as we've come on air, we've been learning about more missiles
coming from Iran. There has been new launches detected. The Israeli media is reporting three
separate launches of potentially 10 missiles coming heading towards Israel, with alerts
being raised in a number of different places, especially central parts of the country,
with at least one missile already being detected to have landed, they say, in open ground.
Okay. Many thanks for that. Rob McBride, the latest from Oman.
Russia's state nuclear company says it's evacuated nearly 200 workers from Iran's
brochure nuclear plant in the south. That's after a strike near its vicinity killed a
security guard and damaged a support building. Now Russia partly constructed the brochure nuclear
plant in Iran and it helps operate it. Iran says the plant has been attacked four times since the
war began. The International Atomic Energy Agency has expressed deep concern and called for de-escalation.
The head of the World Health Organization has also raised the alarm saying in a statement
the latest incident involving the brochure nuclear power plant is a stark reminder a strike could
trigger a nuclear accident with health impacts which would devastate generations. With every passing
day of this escalating conflict, the stakes and threats are raised higher and higher. We must
de-escalate now. Peace is the best medicine. Akshay Diras is a research scientist at the
University of Redding. He says an attack on the brochure power plant would cause radioactive leakage.
I think it's very important to keep in mind that nuclear reactors are designed to be safe
and this particular reactor in the brochure has been hit four times in the past since
it's two months but so far there has not been any major radiation leak as such. If you
assume a really worst-case scenario that the strike is really bad and it starts creating
problems the very first thing that's going to happen is that areas around the nuclear power plant
will be impacted because the radioactive stuff will start getting into the air it will also start
getting into the water and it will not be an area where people can live because it will just
create damage to their health and eventually what really would matter is how much this
radioactive stuff is able to spread further but we don't know that at the moment.
The first thing that's just going to happen is that radioactive stuff will get into the air that
could be isotopes of iodine or cesium they will also get into water which means that the water
is not going to remain safe for any operations be it desalination or even the marine life
is going to be impacted over there. For people the very first thing is like those living near
the reactor they need to they will have to evacuate because the air will really become toxic
and if it starts spreading further like you know just talking about countries surrounding
the Persian Gulf so if the leakage is really strong then I would say there will be some impact
but that will be mainly through water when it comes to countries like Qatar and Kuwait because
of the distance between Iran and these countries. Disruption to shipping through the straits of
Hormuz is reshaping regional energy routes with Pakistan emerging as an alternative corridor
at higher costs diet of fuel availability in peak summer demand and placing increasing strain on
energy systems. Osama bin Javed reports from Karachi port. There's a rush to reach Karachi port.
The facility has handled more traffic in a month than the whole of last year.
That's because Pakistan as Iran's neighbour offers some of the first safe seaports as ships
exit the strait of Hormuz. The crisis comes as Pakistan's preparing for peak summer demand
it's headed towards a deepening energy crunch across both the power sector and fuel supply chain.
The biggest challenge is liquefied natural gas or LNG which accounts for more than 21% of electricity
generation. Officials say supplies could fall to near zero from April. At the same time the
global energy shock is feeding directly into domestic costs. Pakistan is operating with
just 24 days of gasoline and diesel stocks. War risk insurance premiums for tankers have
surged more than tenfold. Freight rates have quadrupled. To manage volatility the government
has moved to weekly fuel price adjustments. Industry analysts describe March as the moment
Pakistan's energy system was stress test. It's more severe external shock since the 1970s oil
crisis. Pakistan moved quickly on multiple fronts simultaneously. Diplomatically it secured
rerouted cargoes through the Red Sea port of Yanbu. Naval escorts kept tankers moving through
contested corridors. Pakistani flag tankers have also passed the strait with permission from Iran.
It was a very coherent institutional response that operated faster than most observers expected.
Now a hybrid strategy is in the making to keep the lights on. It includes limited daily
load shedding, compulsory conservation measures and higher electricity tariffs. The government
is offering a $7 a month targeted relief for motorcyclists and rickshaw drivers even as it
increases petroleum levies to manage fiscal pressure. Oil tankers like these provide the nearly 80%
of energy that Pakistan requires coming from the strait of Kormuz. Pakistan says energy,
security and diplomacy cannot be separated. And what it is trying to do is to find common
ground between the three spheres so it can bring some sort of normalcy to the equation.
After hosting regional diplomats Islamabad is also pushing for wider international engagement
including with China to build momentum for de-escalation. At the same time Pakistan is
trying to turn crisis into opportunity. Plans are underway for a maritime energy city
and new deep-sea ports aimed at transforming the country into a regional hub for energy
storage and trans-shipment. But all of it depends on one thing, an end to hostilities.
Because until then Pakistan remains exposed to the conflict and as one energy expert stated
putting the oil genie back in the barrel.
You're watching Al Jazeera, mind if our top stories. This hour US President Donald Trump has
renewed his threats to attack Iran's infrastructure if it doesn't reopen the
strait of Kormuz. He says US forces will strike Iranian power plants and bridges
otherwise if a deal is enraged by Tuesday. Iran has vowed to retaliate if attacked it promises
to launch reciprocal strikes on US-linked infrastructure the Middle East. Iran's parliament
speakers also accused Trump of quote, war crimes. GCC states faced another day of Iranian
attacks in Bahrain and oil tanker caught fire following a drone strike on Sunday.
And in Kuwait, two power and water desalination plants were damaged.
Also intercepted several drone and missile attacks.
Now US President Donald Trump has given Iran shifting deadlines to reopen the
strait of Hormuz. That says Iran insists that the key waterway isn't actually closed and
that only ships that belong to its enemies are barred from passage. Now Trump issued his
first ultimatum on March the 21st. He threatened to bomb Iran's power plants if the strait wasn't
reopened within 48 hours. He later extended that deadline by five days claiming that negotiations
were underway. He then issued a new deadline on March the 26th giving Iran 10 days or until
the evening of April 6th to reopen the strait. And then he issued his latest Hormuz threat
on Sunday after vowing to bomb power plants and bridges if Tehran doesn't comply. He posted
what appears to be a Tuesday 8 p.m. deadline for a deal. Okay, let's unpack this with our
guests in Washington DC is Stephen Worthy, my senior fellow in the American Statecraft
program at the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace. And in Ottawa, we have
Marzi Khaliliyan, an Iranian political analyst and academic researcher with a focus on US
Middle East relations. Thank you to both of you for joining the program.
Stephen, if I could start with you. So President Donald Trump issuing a new deadline for Iran to
reopen the strait of Hormuz, given his history of shifting ultimatums, how seriously should
this threat be taken? Well, you're right to ask the question, given the history.
But I'm afraid I find it pretty credible that President Trump will indeed escalate
and attack civilian infrastructure in Iran. He's pointed several times now to power plants,
in particular, if the strait isn't opened or some other deal isn't made. And I say that in part
because in recent days, the United States and Israel have ramped up attacks against
civilian infrastructure in Iran, including research centers, pharmaceutical plants,
as well as some power plants. So it would constitute a kind of escalation
of what the United States and Israel are already doing. Marzi, to you from Tehran's perspective,
when messages from Washington alternate between threats and then talk of a deal,
how are U.S. intentions actually being read there?
From the Iranian side, this is mostly read as psychological warfare and extreme inconsistency
during this time of high tension.
So what Iranians are seeing is ultimatum and threats, and if we look at the history
and culture of the Iran, we need to understand that this type of rhetoric and this kind
of language will not result in something fruitful and will not give the result that the Americans
are hoping.
So it seems that the Americans are trying to find an exit for this war, and what we are
seeing from the Iranian side, this type of language, this kind of threatening rhetoric
will not result in that.
Masi, is there... Apologies for interrupting you, but in your perspective, is there a unified
strategy coming from the Iranian side?
If we look at the pattern and see what is coming from the Iran, we are seeing that Iranians
are united in continuation of this war, and even if it turns into a war of attrition
which we are seeing, Iranians are prepared, Iranians have been ready for this war, and
at least, if not for years, for decades, Iranians were anticipating this based on what was
coming from the US and Israel.
So yes, there is that sort of unified reaction from the Iranians that we should continue
this war until they get to the point that there is some sort of guarantee that this
type of attack, this kind of war is not happening again in six months.
So the Iranians don't want to ceasefire today, and then another war happening in six months
which was happening, which is the same thing that happened in June last year, and then
we saw a war happening again.
So this is what the Iranians are trying to get, a guarantee that a war is not happening
again.
A stop to the assassination of their political leaders, yes, these are the united voices
that we are hearing from Iranians.
And Stephen, when it comes to US strategy, how does the US public factor into this, whether
it's fuel prices or unstable markets, is any of the US decision making happening regarding
this war being driven by political pressure at home?
I think President Trump is well aware that his war is deeply unpopular.
It began as a war that had only minority support, which is very rare historically, and support,
if you look at the trend line, has only been dropping from there.
And that's why President Trump seems to be flirting with multiple conflicting pathways
in this war, threatening escalation, but also repeatedly claiming that he's just about
to wrap things up.
He's accomplished his objectives and maybe he's going to end the war in two to three
weeks.
He basically said all of the above in his speech last Wednesday.
So I think President Trump has to be very concerned about the risk of escalation causing
more damage to the American economy, to have higher gas prices at the pump.
This is one of the most obvious things that Americans don't like politically, and it now
seems to be translating into dropping overall approval numbers for President Trump himself.
The tragedy is, though, that President Trump, in his desire to end this conflict, may
resort to some kind of dramatic escalation that he thinks will cause the Iranian regime
to capitulate, to give in to all of his demands, or theatrically allow President Trump to say,
I can stop the war now.
I have ended it on my terms.
And it just simply may not work out the way that he would calculate in that circumstance.
Mazi, on that point, is there a point when it comes that the attacks are too much,
if you like, on Iran?
I mean, if Iran refuses to negotiate under this threat of attack, what options does it
have left when it comes to de-escalation?
So you mentioned that it's going to be too much for Iranians.
I think Iranians have already lost too much.
We saw the assassination of the Iranians to pre-leader.
We saw the assassination of the many of the Iranians political leaders.
We are seeing missiles attacking schools in Iran, which resulted in the death of schoolgears.
So we have a lot of civilian casualties and research centers, pharmaceutical research
centers, but what we're seeing is Iranians have already lost too much.
So what we're seeing from Iran is that we've come this far.
There has been this amount of loss.
So what is the point of stopping today if we know six months from now, then we are just
going to see the same exact loss, the same exact situation happening.
So by escalating this more, I don't think it will make Iranians do as Trump likes to
put it to surrender.
Surrender is not a language that Iranians like to speak at the moment.
I want to ask you, Marzi, about these discussions involving Oman and the
Strait of Hormuz, these ideas being discussed about transit fees tied to reparations.
How do we interpret these discussions?
Could this be seen as Tehran testing some sort of diplomatic off-ramp?
So one of the first statements that came from the Iranian new supreme
leader Mojtaba Khamenei was emphasizing on the fact that Iran will get
reparation one way or another.
It was one of the most clear messages that came from his one of the few statements.
So Iran is looking for a way to find a reparation, because as we mentioned,
the country has already lost too much economically.
So this is one way for the Iranians to compensate for that loss.
And this is not just about reparation.
This also shows who is going to control the state of Hormuz and about the
neighbors losing their autonomy on this trade and what they can trade and what
countries can't trade.
And Iran has been very clear on the way they're going to allow the movement
in the state of Hormuz.
If a country is hostile to Iran, they're going to lose what Iranians
are calling the privilege.
And if a country is showing the type of language that even condemns the US
attack, then we see their ships moving.
So at the moment, this is what the state of Hormuz is.
And I don't think this is some sort of an exit for Iranians.
This is just for Iran to assert its power over the state of Hormuz and
to its in a way, a continuation of what has been so far.
And again, to the Iranians, the state of Hormuz is not closed.
The Iranian Foreign Minister has repeatedly said that the state of
Hormuz is not closed, it's open to Iranian allies and the countries
that are hostile to Iran don't get, again, as Iranians, I put it,
the privilege to move through that.
So I don't think this is this is an exit.
This is just the way Iranians are continuing with their with their
actions of the war.
Stephen, where do Gulf countries come into this?
Because we've heard Iran threatened to attack even more civilian infrastructure
that is already happening in Kuwait.
Iranian drone attacks have damaged two power water desalination plants.
And the worry is if the US attacks Iran's energy sectors further,
the Gulf will pay the price an even higher price.
Well, that worry is entirely justified.
And so I think this is a moment for leaders in the Gulf to pick up
the phone and tell President Trump what the ramifications will be for US
interests if he goes ahead with what he's threatened to do.
And, you know, as it is, even if the war ends tomorrow, it's going to
take a lot of time for the global economy to get back to something
like normal and that's bracketing the question of what will happen
with the Strait of Hormuz.
But if a lot more devastation occurs throughout the Gulf, you know,
those consequences could be much more severe and long lasting.
And one hope something is going to get through to to President Trump here.
But he has proven that, you know, in a decision making so far
that the main person he's listening to internationally is the
Prime Minister of Israel, and then he's listening to some advisors
both inside and outside of his administration who told him it'd be
a good idea to attack Iran and that the war could be over pretty
quickly with a new regime that certainly hasn't happened.
OK, many thanks to both our guests, Stephen Wertham and Marzi
Kalalian joining us there from Ottawa.
Thank you.
OK, let's take a look at some of the world's other newsmaking
headlines in the Gaza Strip. Hamas says it won't hand over weapons.
Disarmament is part of the second phase of the Gaza ceasefire plan.
The armed group says calls to lay down its weapons are unacceptable,
especially as Palestinians continue to be targeted by Israel.
More than 700 have been killed since ceasefire came into effect in October.
As for raising the issue of weapons in this crude manner,
it is nothing but a scandalous attempt by the occupation to continue
killing and genocide against our people, which we will not accept
under any circumstances.
We affirm that what the enemy was unable to seize from us with
tanks and genocide, it will not seize from us with politics
or at the negotiation table.
The occupation's aggression against our people and its continued
closure of the blessed Al Aqsa Mosque to worshipers in an unprecedented manner
and the approval of the law for executing Palestinian prisoners.
We call upon the masses of our Palestinian people in the brave West Bank,
the blessed Jerusalem and the occupied interior to march toward Al Aqsa Mosque.
Mouin Rabani is a non resident fellow at the Centre for Conflict
and Humanitarian Studies.
He says Hamas's statement confirms the talks to implement
the second phase of the Gaza ceasefire plan are deadlocked.
What Hamas informed the mediators is that it will not discuss issues
such as disarmament relating to the second phase of the plan
for the Gaza Strip until the items of the first phase are implemented.
That includes a cessation of hostilities.
As you noted, virtual daily Israeli attacks on the Gaza Strip
have resulted in more than 700 Palestinians killed,
humanitarian aid continues to be restricted and most notably
this National Committee for the Administration of the Gaza Strip,
which was established by the Board of Peace continues to be prohibited
from entering the Gaza Strip by the Israelis and the Board of Peace
is doing absolutely nothing to ensure its ability to get in.
And so I think Hamas is taking two positions.
A, it won't discuss the second phase until the first phase
is properly implemented and B, when those discussions do take place,
it's not going to simply surrender its weapons
unless Israel clearly meets its own obligations as well.
And those are obligations that have to be consistent,
not just with what the Board of Peace wants,
but with the international consensus and the rulings
of the International Court of Justice,
that this is an illegal occupation that must end.
Hundreds of thousands of Palestinians made homeless
by Israel's war on Gaza every day is a struggle.
As bombed out neighborhoods are slowly cleared of rubble,
some families are collecting scrap metals to survive.
Harry Mahmood reports from Gaza City.
Trucks arrive one after another,
offloading what remains of homes, shops and entire streets.
Across large part of Gaza,
rubble removal continues month after its raided bombardment
in a flat and entire neighborhood.
But for some, these dumping grounds are more than just fields of debris.
They are workplaces.
Children search the mountains of broken concrete
and a twisted metal for anything they can sell.
Wood, copper wire, aluminum.
Each piece they collect means a few more coins.
Each truck brings another opportunity and another risk.
The ground is unstable.
Sharp edges from broken walls.
Aid agents is worn, unexploded ordnance
may still be buried beneath the debris.
Hussana Abdel-A'al lives in a tent near one of the dumping sites.
We come here hoping to earn 20 shekels, about six dollars.
But it comes at a cost.
Injuries, exhaustion, cuts everywhere.
You can see the wounds and the blood.
The war has left hundreds of thousands of families
without stable income.
Factories are shut, shops are gone.
Entire businesses reduced to dust.
Post-war recovery is measured by reconstruction in plans,
funding in pledges.
But here on the ground, recovery looks different.
It looks like children navigating the rubble,
households depending on the fragments of what was destroyed.
As long as livelihood remains absent
and reconstruction uncertain,
the rubble will continue to serve two purposes.
One reminder of loss.
And for some people, it is a means of survival.
Informal scrap collection has become one of the few ways to earn cash.
We come here to earn money for food.
My father has no work, so we have to come.
We come here hoping to find bits of wood or pieces of cable that we can sell.
Anything that may help us buy food for our children.
We know climbing onto the moving trucks is dangerous.
But when your family depends on it, you take the risk.
Parents say they don't want their children here.
But survival leaves little room for a choice.
An Mahmoud Al-Jazeera from Gaza City, Palestine.
Serbia says explosives have been found near a pipeline
that carries Russian gas to Hungary.
Though it is say the discovery was made outside a Serbian town near the Hungarian border.
It comes just a week before closely watched elections in Hungary.
Prime Minister Viktor Orban is fighting to extend his 16 years in power.
He's linked Ukraine to those explosives.
Orkiva's rejected Orban's accusations,
posting on X, the foreign ministry spokesman said,
Ukraine has nothing to do with this.
Most probably a Russian false flag operation as part of Moscow's heavy
interference in Hungarian elections.
It's been a subdued Easter in the occupied Palestinian territories
where ceremonies have been scaled back because of the Iran war.
A small Sunday mass was held at the church of the Holy Sepulchre in occupied East Jerusalem.
The site is revered by Christians as the traditional site
of Jesus Christ's crucification and resurrection.
Israeli authorities have limited access in Gaza.
Orthodox Palestinian Christians who follow the Eastern calendar
have celebrated Palm Sunday.
It marks the beginning of the Holy Week leading to Orthodox Easter.
Worshipers attended mass at the Saint Peripherous Church in Gaza City.
It came under Israeli attacks several times before the ceasefire.
Rights groups are warning about threats to media freedom in Sahel countries
that have seen military coups in recent years.
Junta leaders are using security concerns and cybercrime laws to silence criticism.
Reporters without borders has condemned the sentencing last week
of a Malian journalist convicted of insulting the military leader of Niger.
Midden Kimber reports, words can be life changing.
They certainly were for Yusuf Cisoko,
the publishing director of the Malian newspaper, L'Alternance, or The Alternating.
This article accuses General Abdul Rahman Tieny,
the military leader of neighboring Niger,
of trying to distract people from his government's security failures.
Tieny had blamed the attacks on the international airport
in the capital Niyami back in January on France,
the Ivory Coast and Benin without providing evidence.
The Islamic State claimed responsibility.
The article argues Tieny overlooked the threat posed by armed groups,
which he pledged to remove when he seized power in 2023.
It also accuses what he calls Tieny's military regime of economic suicide,
citing the closure of borders with Benin.
Niger is a landlocked country which relied on its neighbor's ports for trade.
Cisoko was convicted last week of spreading false news,
undermining the credibility of the state and insulting a foreign head of state.
He was fined $1,700 and sentenced to two years in prison.
This journalist would only speak anonymously for fear of reprisals.
It represents a setback for freedom of expression,
which is already under severe strain in Mali,
but we do not use hope that there is still the possibility of appeal.
Rather than the press law,
Cisoko was charged under Mali's cybercrime law,
which allows journalists to be punished for criticising not just their own state,
but others in the Sahel.
Which makes the situation even more complex.
Had it been handled as a press-related matter,
the sentence might not have been the same.
I see this ruling as a strong message to all media actors,
that things can go very far, so extreme caution is needed.
And this isn't just happening in Mali.
In Niger and Burkina Faso,
military-led governments are restricting freedom of expression
by suspending independent media outlets
and censoring and intimidating reporters.
They're also targeting social media activists and influencers.
In Burkina Faso, some journalists who criticise the military
have been forcibly conscripted without training
to fight against armed groups.
With the widening crackdown on independent journalism,
the International Press Institute
is warning of an information blackout in the Sahel,
which it says could have regional and global consequences.
Imogen Kimber, Alger Zira.
How much can AI be used to stop gun deaths?
That's the question being asked in Birmingham, Alabama,
a city with a huge gun violence problem.
It's just renewed a deal for a system of sensors
that detects gunshots and then sends drones to crime scenes
to live out.
We'll see anything like that.
Cherie and Rosalyn are two mums
with the most painful bond imaginable.
Imagine seeing your loved one shot over 12 or 13 times.
That picture would never go out my head.
Both received a heartbreaking call.
Their sons had been shot dead.
Different men, but same day, one year apart.
I remember that day like yesterday.
I remember pulling up on the scene and seeing the vehicle
shot up, blood on the car.
There are hundreds of stories like this
here in Birmingham, Alabama,
all with the same ending.
Gun violence is rife.
Could AI have saved any of them?
It doesn't work.
And that is what this is all about
because AI is being used here
to try to combat gun violence.
There is this network of sensors dotted around
listening for the sound of gunshots.
They hear them and they dispatch police automatically,
but where those sensors are located,
that's what's controversial.
These devices are placed in predominantly poor neighborhoods.
They're placed in black and brown neighborhoods
and what it means is more police presence.
The technology has been used in cities across the US
for years, yet many are rolling it back
or cancelling it altogether.
But in this city, synonymous with the Civil Rights movement,
they have just spent millions of dollars
to extend the contract.
On top of that, they've added drones
which take off autonomously and can get to the scene
of any potential crime long before the police can.
Birmingham saw a 44% drop in homicides last year.
That is a 10-year low.
Another statistic, 88% of victims were black.
It's evident that it's not working.
It's not the technology that's keeping us safe
and it may be other reasons why crime is not as prevalent.
The company behind the tech says it has seen a reduction
of 61% in gunfire incidents over the last two years
and that it helps because up to 85% of gunshots
are never reported by residents.
There are some areas where we do respond to shootings
but we don't get a 911 call.
We identify those areas as a priority.
It is solely the police who choose which neighborhoods
to put sensors in.
The family members that won't forget, that's retaliation.
That's what worries these mums.
Shootings lead to revenge and more shootings.
They spend their lives now consoling other parents
and trying to break that cycle.
I'll never be healed until I make it up there.
That's my goal.
I'm going to make it up there with him.
For these mums, it is not about the sounds
that are picked up, but the silence that follows
and the emptiness it leaves behind.
Philaville, Al Jazeera, Birmingham, Alabama.
That's it for this hour.
Extensive coverage of the war between the US,
Israel and Iran continues after the break.
The United States military began major combat operations
in Iran.
We are not joined by the US
and Israeli offensive stripes.
The position of the Spanish government can be summed up
in four words, no to the war.
I have condemned the massive military strikes
by the United States and Israel
and I also condemn the subsequent attacks by Iran.
The attacks on energy facilities that have happened
on both sides is a dangerous precedent
that will cause repercussions throughout the world.
We can now see a regional conflict
with unintended consequences.
Stay with us for the latest developments on Al Jazeera.
Hard-hitting interviews.
Aren't you afraid that you might be one of the targets?
Anyone could become a target.
We have seen that they have no hesitation
about targeting any place.
Facing realities.
Does Qatar still trust Iran enough to mediate?
Let's say that this aggression brings a benefit for no one.
Thought-provoking answers.
How many have been displaced inside Iran?
I've heard three million.
It could be more.
Hear their story on Talk to Al Jazeera.
The world's top business stories.
How high could prices go for oil?
Also, how quickly can this feed into the inflation picture?
Counting the cost on Al Jazeera.
No, this is Al Jazeera live from Doha
with our continuing coverage of the war
between the U.S., Israel and Iran.
I'm Malin Said.
Coming up, Donald Trump sets a Tuesday deadline
for Iran to reopen the Strait of Hormuz.
All the U.S. will bomb its power plants, bridges
and, quote, unleash hell.
We are determined to defend.
Iran's foreign ministry dismisses the U.S. president's warning
and vows a swift retaliation to any U.S. attacks.
U.S. troops rescue a second airman
and a high-stakes mission in Iran
two days after his fighter jet went down.
These five people have been killed
in an Israeli strike on Lebanon's capital
while live in Beirut's southern suburb.
And rescuers in the northern Israeli city of Haifa
look for the missing after an Iranian strike
targets an apartment complex for people who are injured.
U.S. President Donald Trump has renewed threats
to destroy Iranian power plants and bridges
if it doesn't reopen the Strait of Hormuz.
He shared what appears to be a deadline
on social media Tuesday, 8 p.m. eastern time.
Earlier, Trump posted an explicit laden threat
to his truth social accounts.
It promised that Iranians would be, quote,
living in hell if the Strait isn't reopened.
Tehran has emphasized it will retaliate if struck.
Foreign Ministry spokesman Ismail Baghe
says any U.S.-related location in the Middle East
would be a target.
Our armed forces have made it clear
that in case Iran's infrastructure is attacked,
we would react in kind.
They would, our armed forces,
would target any similar infrastructure
that is owned or in any way or manner
related to the United States
or contributes to their act of aggression against Iran.
We'll be live from Tehran in just a moment.
First, Al Jazeera's Mike Hanna
has more on President Trump's comments from Washington, D.C.
The unusual use of an expletive by a national leader,
perhaps a symbol of President Trump's frustration
with the Iranian government
and their refusal to concede to the demands that he is making.
That reference as well was to the Strait of Hamouz,
which in recent days President Trump had insisted
he did not care about saying
the U.S. did not need the oil passing through the Strait
and it was up to the countries who are reliant on that oil
to deal with the situation.
But now the demand about opening the Strait of Hamouz
appears front and center of the President's new demands
of the Iranian government.
President Trump threatening to, and I use his words,
blowing everything and taking the oil
if Iran does not meet his new deadline,
which has now been set at 8 p.m. eastern time on Tuesday evening.
He says in an earlier media post
that a power plant day and bridge day
all wrapped up on Tuesday.
But on the other hand, in addition to these threats,
President Trump is sending signals
that there's some kind of negotiation process underway.
He's indicated that his close confidants, Jared Kushner
and Stephen Whitcoff, are in consultation
with either the Iranian government
and identified figures or some form of intermediary.
And speaking to U.S. news outlets,
President Trump says that he is optimistic
that there can be an agreement very soon.
He says the agreement could come within a matter of days
rather than a matter of weeks.
So you've got this dichotomous approach from the President
on the one hand threatening obliteration
to civilian targets within Iran,
which some observers would contend to be a war crime.
But on the other hand, what he is saying is,
yes, we are talking, the talks are going well,
and they could come to fruition
before that new deadline I set,
which is 8 p.m. Eastern time on Tuesday.
Mike Hanna, Al Jazeera, Washington.
Well, the Speaker of Iran's parliament
has also responded to Trump in a social media post.
Mohammed Bagger Gali Ba'af wrote,
quote, your reckless moves are dragging the United States
into a living hell for every single family.
And the whole region is going to burn
because you insist on following Netanyahu's commands.
Make no mistake, you won't gain anything
from these war crimes.
Let's bring in Mohammed Val, who's live in Tehran.
Mohammed, so Iran's standing firm
against President Trump's threat to target its power plants
if the Strait of Hormuz is not reopened.
It's also been accusing Washington
of potential war crimes.
That's right.
They have been very vocal and very clear
about what they want to do here
in case President Trump
executes those threats.
It's new. Iran has been saying from the very beginning
that it's not going to be intimidated
with regards to what it wants to do
by way of defending itself and defending the nation.
We have seen several officials
over the last few days, particularly yesterday,
including the spokesman of the Foreign Ministry,
saying literally that Iran is going
to inflict the same type of pain,
the same kind of retaliation,
the retaliation of in-kind
against targets in the region,
in Israel and across the region,
if its power plants are struck.
And also, I mean, the Foreign Ministry
spokesman has been trying to explain
both to the Americans and to anyone
who is following this war,
that this war is illegal,
this war has been imposed on Iran,
it did not initiate it,
and that it is based on a series of lies,
including the lie that Iran has been pursuing
the production of nuclear weapons,
the lie that Iran has been presenting
an imminent threat to the United States,
and the lie that this war has been waged
in the name of the Iranian people
and in order to liberate the Iranian people.
So for all these considerations, Iran,
now looking at this as an existential threat
on its sovereignty, on its independence
and its interests, it's not going to hesitate
and it is not going to be intimidated
and it has the means, the military means
and it has proved that it has the military means
to retaliate and to defend itself.
And Mohamed, in terms of attacks on the ground,
we're hearing of attacks in Bashar province in Qum.
Talk us through the latest attacks.
Well, you can see a smoke behind me in the horizon
and that's one of the latest attacks
on the Iranian Caps or Tehran,
that's in the vicinity of the Mehrabad airport.
And also there is a university, Sharif University
that has been not directly hit,
but there was a near miss of that university.
We remember that many universities
have been directly targeted over the last few days.
So Sharif University almost hit in that strike
that apparently, as we understand,
it has targeted a gas substation
in this area behind me that you see.
There is a lot of smoke rising in the horizon.
So that's just one of the strikes,
but there have been many across Tehran during the night.
And also I can count almost 12 cities that were targeted
over the last several hours, including Bandar Abbas,
Ahuaz, where the airport was hit
and also Shahar city and Bandar Lenge, Qung city,
Shiraz, Isfahan, Karaj, Tehran, Qum.
Qum, where five people were killed.
And also Qung city where six were killed
and 17 were wounded.
So civilians also were falling, were dying these strikes
and they are only intensifying
and the number of cities also is increasing,
the number of cities that are being targeted.
Okay, thank you for that update.
Mohammad Val there for us in Tehran with the latest.
Well, the threat of escalation in Iran
puts the Gulf region squarely in the crossfire.
The sites Iran is threatening to hit back
are almost entirely located in GCC countries
which are already coping with daily attacks.
Kuwait says it's been hit by a series of drone attacks.
Authorities report two major power
and desalination plants were targeted.
One of the facilities is in Al-Zor,
nearly 90 kilometers south of Kuwait city.
Another attack hit the finance ministry complex,
which is a building in central Kuwait city.
In Bahrain, Iran targeted an oil facility
sparking several fires.
Emergency response team said the blaze
has been fully extinguished.
Over the past few weeks,
Manama has come under repeated Iranian missile
and drone attacks.
Let's go to Mohammad Jamjoon,
who is in the Qatari capital Doha for us.
Mohammad so attacks across the Gulf
in the last 24 hours.
Bring us up to date.
Amalina, aside from the attacks you just mentioned,
over the course of the last three or four hours
we've seen statements from the ministries of defense
in both the UAE and in Kuwait saying
that their air defense systems
have been intercepting missiles and drones
headed towards both of those countries.
That's what's happening at this hour.
We're still awaiting more details about those specific attacks.
Beyond that, of course, this is a very perilous moment.
People are very concerned about
what's going to be happening next.
What's on the table now is the fact that
Donald Trump has now threatened Iran
if Iran does not reopen the Strait of Hormuz
by Tuesday, 8 p.m. eastern time.
He says essentially power plants
and bridges and other sites
will be targeted massively by the U.S.
The reason that's so concerning in this region
is that Iran has made it well known
over the course of the past few weeks
that if the U.S. and the U.S. and Israel
were to target infrastructure sites
in particular,
after an F-15E fighter jet
went down on Friday.
It was the first time a U.S. aircraft
had crashed in hostile territory
in the five-week-old war.
Two Blackhawk helicopters took fire
as U.S. teams raced to find the missing crew member.
An A-10 Warthog, an air support aircraft,
was also damaged,
its pilot ejecting over the Gulf.
Iran broadcast photos of what it said
was debris from the fighter jet
including a jump seat.
Although the pilot had been rescued on Friday,
the weapon specialist remained in hiding,
evading Iranian forces for two days.
Finally, early on Sunday,
deep in Iranian territory,
the U.S. search operation was successful.
President Donald Trump made the announcement
on social media, posting,
We Got Him, saying the Colonel
had been behind enemy lines
in the treacherous mountains of Iran
being hunted by our enemies.
He said U.S. forces had been monitoring
his location 24 hours a day
and sent dozens of aircraft
armed with the most lethal weapons
in the world to retrieve him.
Trump added, he sustained injuries,
but he will be just fine.
A U.S. official told Al Jazeera
the rescue operation began in darkness
but ended in an intense firefight
and daylight before dozens
of heavily armed aircraft
and hundreds of troops
transported the airmen out of Iran.
A U.S. officer in Iranian custody
could have given Iran leverage
as it had when Iran took U.S. hostages
in 1979.
With that crisis averted,
attention now shifts to the U.S.
deadline for Iran to open
the Strait of Hormuz.
John Hendren, Al Jazeera, Washington.
As reported in
Don Story, U.S. officials say
the rescue mission involved several aircraft.
Iranian state media
released these pictures
reportedly showing the wreckage
of a C-130 aircraft
in Isfahan province.
American media reporting U.S. forces destroyed
at least one of their own planes
on purpose because it had become
stuck and unable to fly out.
Iranian armed forces
dispute those series of events
claiming its soldiers destroyed
two C-130 aircraft
and two Black Hawk helicopters
in what it characterised
as a failed U.S. rescue operation.
With God's help and support
and through the vigilance and readiness
of the fighters of Islam in the armed forces
using electronic warfare,
advanced new air defence systems,
the implementation of a ground mosaic defence plan,
and the creation of a military
and security cordon,
a number of these aircraft including
two C-130 military transport planes
and two Black Hawk helicopters
were hit and forced to make
emergency landings in an area south
of Isfahan.
After Iranian Islamic fighters
completed the operation to encircle the enemy
in order to prevent the disgrace of Trump,
the President of the United States
and the hollow prestige of the army
was forced to carry out heavy bombing
of its downed aircraft, equipment,
commanders and soldiers.
In Lebanon the Israeli army
has carried out new strikes
on Beirut's southern suburb
in a densely populated residential area.
The death toll has now risen
to at least five including
three Sudanese nationals,
52 others
were also injured in those strikes.
Three others have been killed
in an airstrike on the hills of Ansade.
As Raul says it's
continuing attacks on Hezbollah military infrastructure.
More than a million people
have been forcibly displaced
across the country.
They hit a completely civilian area.
It's mostly migrants here, Sudanese people.
People were at home and they struck them.
Are those military objectives?
Where is the UN?
No one says anything.
Aren't they human too?
They're killing children and women.
The whole world has to speak up.
It has to see and say something.
Have we become nothing but numbers, a people of numbers?
How is that possible?
We are devastated.
Our morale is low.
When you see your friends and neighbours in pieces on the ground and blood everywhere and
the house destroyed, our house was destroyed.
Where are we going to sleep?
Where do we go?
Heidi Peters live for us in Beirut.
So Heidi, what are you learning about these latest attacks across Lebanon?
Yeah, so it's been a heavy day for Lebanon in the last 24 hours.
There were multiple airstrikes on the southern suburbs, eight of them starting just after
midday, including that one that you mentioned in Jena where the death toll has risen now,
as you mentioned, to five.
But a couple of hours after that, we had another airstrike in an area in the eastern
hills of Beirut.
It's a Christian neighbourhood.
It's not somewhere where people would have expected to be targeted.
We went to the scene of that site and it appears to be another Israeli attempted
assassination strike.
So a projectile came through the roof of a residential apartment building.
It crashed through the third floor apartment, but exploded inside the second,
killing three people.
Now, among them was a local leader for the Lebanese forces, which is a right-wing
Christian party that is fairly strong in the area.
His name was Pierre Mouad and his wife and a visitor to their home were also killed.
Now, in the aftermath of that, an MP from his party put out a statement saying that
displaced people should only be welcomed into official shelters,
that restrictions should be made, checks should be made, because what happens
when these strikes occur in areas outside of the southern suburbs,
outside of south Lebanon, which are predominantly Shia areas where
his bullet supporters live, when they hit Christian areas or Sunni or Druze,
people immediately jumped to the conclusion that Israel was targeting
somebody who might have moved into the area recently, fleeing strikes
in other parts of the country.
And that is exactly what happened, speaking to neighbors in the street
after that attack that rumors were flying around.
You know, was there somebody in that building?
Who was there?
Why would Israel target our neighborhood?
But speaking to the local mayor and also the head of the
neighborhood committee there, they said that that third floor apartment,
which appears to have been the actual target of that strike,
was empty at the time.
And the owner said that he hadn't been renting it out to anybody either.
But what it has done is heightened the level of fear
and tension in that neighborhood, which is something that has been
occurring across Lebanon throughout the last four weeks of war,
is Israel continues to expand the area that they're targeting,
meaning people just can't make the calculus anymore of where they might
feel safe and they're becoming, you know, they want to welcome in the
more than one million people who have been displaced in this country,
but they are fearful of any strangers coming to their neighborhood
because these Israeli strikes just continue to expand.
OK, thank you for that Heidi Perth reporting there from Beirut.
Israel's forced evacuation orders have displaced hundreds of thousands
in southern Lebanon, as we've been hearing.
Tire resident Jamal Saleem Farhan says he won't leave his home
despite repeated Israeli bombings.
I have two things to deal with.
One is to leave my home.
I'll make a camp and stay in it.
I'll stay on my own.
I'll show the world where I'm staying.
One of them is to leave my home.
I'll go back to my house and there's no other option.
You'll come and hit the plane.
For what reason?
But I'll stay in my home, I don't want to leave.
I won't leave.
This is our land.
We won't leave it.
Of course, we'll stay in our homes.
We'll stay in our homes.
Despite the bombings and the bombings
and the weapons of the world,
we won't leave it.
Rescue workers in Israel are searching for people
feared trapped under the rubble of a building
hit by an Iranian strike on Haifa.
The residential structure partially collapsed
after the attack on Sunday.
Israeli authorities say four people have been wounded.
One person is in critical condition.
Rob McBride has been following developments
from the Jordanian capital, Amman.
Rob, what more do we know about this attack?
Yeah, that's right.
This search has been continuing
through the hours of darkness Sunday
through now into the early hours of Monday morning
looking for people unaccounted for.
Haifa is no stranger to this conflict.
It has found itself pretty much since the start
on the front lines, given its importance
as an industrial center, also its importance
in refining oil for much of Israel.
And it often is the target for Iranian missiles
and sometimes in conjunction with rockets
fired by Hezbollah, given its proximity
to the border in northern Israel
with Lebanon.
This was, according to authorities,
a single heavy warhead which managed
to get past the missile defenses hitting a building.
Because of structural damage to the building,
there's been this constant fear of collapse.
So they have been bringing in overnight specialist teams
to conduct this search.
There are four people still unaccounted for.
It's understood that they could all be
from the same one apartment,
which is one of the more damaged in this building.
And that continues.
Meanwhile, in the early hours of Monday,
there were new salvos being launched from Iran
in the direction of Israel.
Three separate salvos were detected.
Alerts were put out through much of central Israel.
The number of missiles has been estimated
anywhere up to around 10,
with some of them being cluster missiles.
Most have now been intercepted
and others falling in open ground.
Meanwhile, four salvos were fired in total Sunday.
One of them landing again in this chemical-industrial area
in the south of Israel,
raising concerns just about the targeting
of infrastructure by Israel and Iran
as this war of missiles seems to be escalating.
Rob McBride, there in Amman.
Let's take a look at some of the world's other news.
In the Gaza Strip, Hamas says it won't hand over its weapons.
Disarmament is part of the second phase of the Gaza ceasefire plan,
but the armed group says calls to lay down its weapons
are unacceptable, especially as Palestinians
continue to be targeted by Israel.
More than 700 have been killed
since the ceasefire came into effect in October.
As for raising the issue of weapons in this crude manner,
it is nothing but a scandalous attempt
by the occupation to continue killing and genocide
against our people,
which we will not accept under any circumstances.
We affirm that what the enemy was unable to seize from us
with tanks and genocide,
it will not seize from us with politics
or at the negotiation table.
The occupation's aggression against our people
and its continued closure of the blessed al-Aqsa mosque
to worshipers in an unprecedented manner
and the approval of the law
for executing Palestinian prisoners,
we call upon the masses of our Palestinian people
in the brave West Bank, the blessed Jerusalem
and the occupied interior to march toward al-Aqsa mosque.
Mu'in Rabani is a non-resident fellow at the Center
for Conflicts and Humanitarian Studies.
He says Hamas's statement confirms
that talks to implement the second phase
of the Gaza ceasefire plan are deadlocked.
What Hamas informed the mediators
is that it will not discuss issues
such as disarmament relating to the second phase
of the plan for the Gaza Strip
until the items of the first phase are implemented.
That includes a cessation of hostilities.
As you noted, virtual daily Israeli attacks
on the Gaza Strip have resulted
in more than 700 Palestinians killed.
Humanitarian aid continues to be restricted.
And most notably this national committee
for the administration of the Gaza Strip
which was established by the Board of Peace
continues to be prohibited
from entering the Gaza Strip by the Israelis
and the Board of Peace is doing absolutely nothing
to ensure its ability to get in.
And so I think Hamas is taking two positions.
A, it won't discuss the second phase
until the first phase is properly implemented.
And B, when those discussions do take place,
it's not going to simply surrender its weapons
unless Israel clearly meets its own obligations as well.
And those are obligations that have to be consistent
not just with what the Board of Peace wants
but with the international consensus
and the rulings of the International Court of Justice
that this is an illegal occupation that must end.
For hundreds of thousands of Palestinians
made homeless by Israel's war on Gaza
every day is a struggle.
As bombed out neighborhoods
are slowly cleared of rubble
some families are collecting scrap metals to survive.
Annie Mahmood reports from Gaza City.
Trucks arrive one after another
offloading what remains of homes, shops and entire streets.
Across large part of Gaza
rubble removal continues month after
Israeli bombardment flat an entire neighborhood.
But for some these dumping grounds
are more than just fields of debris.
They are workplaces.
Children search the mountains of broken concrete
and a twisted metal for anything they can sell.
Wood, copper wire, aluminum.
Each piece they collect means a few more coins.
Each truck brings another opportunity and another risk.
The ground is unstable.
Sharp edges from broken walls.
Aid agents is worn unexploded ordinance
may still be buried beneath the debris.
Hassan Abdel-A'al lives in a tent near one of the dumping sites.
We come here hoping to earn 20 shakals, about $6.
But it comes at a cost.
Injuries, exhaustion, cuts everywhere.
You can see the wounds and the blood.
The war has left hundreds of thousands of families
without stable income.
Factories are shut, shops are gone,
entire businesses reduced to dust.
Post-war recovery is measured by reconstruction in plans,
funding, and pledges.
But here on the ground recovery looks different.
It looks like children navigating the rubble,
household depending on the fragments of what was destroyed.
As long as livelihood remains absent
and reconstruction uncertain,
the rubble will continue to serve two purposes.
One reminder of loss
and for some people it is a means of survival.
Informal scrap collection has become one of the few ways to earn cash.
We come here to earn money for food.
My father has no work, so we have to come.
We come here hoping to find bits of wood or pieces of cable
that we can sell,
anything that may help us buy food for our children.
We know climbing onto the moving trucks is dangerous,
but when your family depends on it, you take the risk.
Parents say they don't want their children here,
but survival leaves little room for a choice.
Hani Mahmoud Al-Jazeera from Gaza City, Palestine.
Serbia says explosives have been found
near a pipeline that carries Russian gas to Hungary.
Authorities say the discovery was made outside
a Serbian town near the Hungarian border.
It comes just a week before closely watched elections in Hungary.
The Prime Minister Viktor Orbán is fighting
to extend his 16 years in power.
He's linked Ukraine to those explosives.
For years, Ukraine has been working to cut Europe off
from Russian energy.
They blew up Nord Stream,
shut down the gas pipeline supplying Hungary,
and this year placed Hungary under an oil blockade
by closing the Družba pipeline.
The Russian section of the Turkstream
is also under continuous military attack.
Ukraine's efforts pose a life-threatening danger to Hungary.
Well, Kiev has rejected Orbán's accusations
and instead suggested that Russia is to blame.
In a statement posted to social media,
Ukraine's Foreign Ministry spokesman
wrote that his country had nothing to do with the situation.
He also claims that it was, quote,
most probably a Russian false flag operation
as part of Moscow's heavy interference
in Hungarian elections.
It's been a subdued Easter
in the occupied Palestinian territories
where ceremonies have been scaled back
because of the Iran War.
A small Sunday mass was held
at the Church of the Holy Sepulchre
in occupied East Jerusalem.
The site is revered by Christians
as the traditional site of Jesus Christ's
Crucification and Resurrection.
Israeli authorities have limited access.
On Palm Sunday last week,
the Latin Patriarch was blocked from entering the church,
sparking international condemnation.
In Gaza, Orthodox Palestinian Christians
who follow the Eastern calendar
have celebrated Palm Sunday,
marks the beginning of the Holy Week
leading to Orthodox Easter.
Worshipers attended mass
at the St. Peripherious Church in Gaza City.
It came under Israeli attack several times
before the ceasefire.
Okay, our coverage of the war between
the U.S., Israel and Iran continues
with Riley Carlson at the top of the hour.
Coming up next is Up Front. Stay with us.
As the U.S.-Israel war on Iran rages on,
its impact has spread far beyond the battlefield.
Energy prices are soaring
as facilities and supply routes are targeted.
Vital shipping lanes choked.
We strongly encourage other nations
whose economies depend on this trade
to come and help us.
Stay with Al Jazeera for extensive coverage
and expert analysis as shockwaves
continue to shape the global economy.
In-depth analysis of the day's headlines.
Diplomacy yet again was used as a ruse for war.
Critical debate.
Who betrayed the table?
Who attacked the negotiations for the second time?
For the third time during the talks
which should be attacked,
who is talking about a greater country for itself?
Israel, not Iran.
Iran has been a huge supporter
of terrorism over the years.
We really have to take exception to the idea
that Iran is innocent in this.
Inside Story on Al Jazeera.
Is Israel's new death penalty law
further entrenching apartheid?
That conversation is coming up.
But first, Israel continues its attacks in Iran
and its ground invasion of southern Lebanon
with civilian casualties mounting
and the targeted destruction
of key civilian infrastructure ramping up.
Is Israel trying to apply
the Gaza playbook to Lebanon and Iran?
I'll ask Israel's former Deputy Foreign Minister,
Danny Ayalon.
Danny Ayalon, welcome to Up Front.
Thank you very much, Ridi.
Thank you.
So after more than a month of war,
the Iranian government has not collapsed.
It is still standing.
US intelligence assessments are telling us
that it is unlikely to collapse anytime soon.
Even your Prime Minister, Benjamin Netanyahu,
has conceded that regime change
cannot happen via airstrikes.
It must happen internally.
Yet Israel continues to escalate its attacks,
killing the very people it claims to help.
What exactly is the point of this war?
Yes, well, really best that I can tell.
The idea was not immediately to
get rid of this murderous regime
of the Ayatollahs in Tehran,
but maybe to create the conditions.
Whether it will happen in weeks or months,
no one can tell.
But the purpose of the airstrikes
of Israel, and then I believe also of the United States,
is actually to degrade Iran
to take out the capability that they have built
of long-range missiles
that now we are on the receiving end of it.
By the way, not just Israel.
It's the entire Gulf countries.
It's even Turkey and even Cyprus.
But that's as a result.
That's as a result of Israel's attack.
And they were already at the negotiation table.
All the retaliatory attacks are happening
because of Israel's attacks.
Well, unfortunately, we have been watching
this Iranian regime since 1979.
And we have seen that they do not live up
to their promises, not in the nuclear issues,
that they did everything against their own commitments
on the non-proliferation treaty
and also on the missiles.
We have heard them say time and again
that they do not have missiles
which are more than 1,000 or 1,500 kilometers.
Only two weeks ago, really.
They fired two ballistic missiles
towards the island of Diego Garcia
in the Indian Pacific,
which is at the range of 4,000.
So you cannot take them at their word on the contrary.
This is why we have to watch them very carefully
and also, they were building
a massive infrastructure of missiles
and in their plan was to build 10,000 ballistic missiles
with a longer range, bigger warheads,
more accuracy.
10,000 missiles to be launched on any country
could be devastating
and it could be akin to almost a nuclear bomb.
Iran reportedly removed its limits on ballistic missiles
only after Israel's bombing campaign
during the war last year.
Now, as a result of this new threat,
hard-line voices within Iran
are pushing for withdrawal
from the nuclear non-proliferation treaty.
It seems as if Israel has in fact succeeded
in bombing its way into the very scenarios
that it claimed it wanted to avoid.
Well, I would say that whether they
belong to the non-proliferation or not, it was beside the point, because no matter what
they declared or what they signed on, they did things completely differently.
And we saw it with the 60% enriched uranium, which was a total breach of all the agreements
and the NPT.
We saw it with a weaponization program that they have.
Not only the enriched uranium, but how to launch it or how to mount it on a ballistic missile.
Very, very dangerous.
A top advisor to Donald Trump, David Sacks, says there was a scenario where you would
have to, quote, worry about Israel escalating the war by contemplating using nuclear
weapons.
So my question to you, would you support Israel using its nuclear weapons?
Well, again, this is a very wild speculation.
Israel has never, ever committed to any nuclear activities quite the contrary.
We have said all along, and this is still the policy of every government of Israel, that
Israel will not be the first to introduce nuclear weapons to the Middle East.
So certainly we are not looking that way.
And also, Israel has never, ever threatened any other country for total annihilation.
So this is a totally different case.
Are you denying that Israel has nuclear weapons?
Yes, I am denying, but I'm not in a position of government right now, so I can say whatever
I say.
But Israel has never said whether it has or it doesn't have.
But that ambiguity, that ambiguity is a problem.
Why won't you say and why won't you let inspectors in and why won't you be a part of the nuclear
nonproliferation treaty?
Okay.
So this is a fair question.
Ambiguity is a fundamental, I would say, basis for our national security.
If you look at the map, Israel, a very small country, we are less than one third of one
percent of the entire Middle East.
You see all the threats we have around us.
So ambiguity is the only way we can assure that our security and our future are, I would
say, are solid.
Isn't it hypocritical?
I mean, it sounds like jaw-dropping hypocrisy that you as Israel would bomb another country
because it's allegedly pursuing nuclear weapons.
And despite contrary suggestions and counterarguments from the UN and others, you insist that
they have nuclear weapons.
I mean, the only country that actually may have nuclear weapons is Israel.
That's hypocrisy.
I don't think so.
Again, we never said that we have a nuclear weapon.
We never said, for sure, that we're going to use nuclear weapons or to threaten any
other countries, which is not the case of the Ayatollahs.
And they're trying to submit and subjugate all the people in the countries to their
rule, like they did in Lebanon, in Yemen, in Syria, in Iraq.
And they will not stop there until they're stopped by somebody who has to stop them.
And I'm very proud and happy that Israel has the wherewithal to be able to stop it.
And by the way, by doing that, we defend not only ourselves, but we defend all the countries
in the Middle East.
Netanyahu recently expanded the invasion into southern Lebanon.
You mentioned that as well, which he says it is to create a security buffer against
Hezbollah.
At the same time, Israeli officials have openly called for extending Israel's borders.
How does Israel justify its illegal territorial expansion to Lebanon?
Well, the justification is on both Article 55 of the Charter of the United Nations, which
is called self-defense, and in order to save lives of civilians in our northern border.
We see Hezbollah.
Again, Hezbollah would not be in existence without Iran.
Iran is giving the Hezbollah $1 billion a year.
By the way, you look at the abject conditions of the Iranian population, you wonder why the
money is not going to them.
And this is also part of the instigation of a regime change over the population.
Well, you are spending a lot of money on defense as well.
The US is also doing the same.
But Article 55 does not allow you to annex territory.
In fact, the UN Charter, Article 2.4, all members shall refrain in their international relations
from the threat or use of force against the territorial integrity or political independence
by any state.
What do you say to that?
You are violating international law?
All I say is, yeah, I do not negate that.
And Israel does not have any ambitions or any territorial claims from Lebanon.
So this is why we are very careful to say this is a security zone which will last only
as long as Hezbollah is armed.
By the way, Hezbollah is the one breaching the international law because all the agreements,
whether it's the UN Security Council 1701, whether it's internal Taif Agreement of all
the sections in Lebanon, whether it's the ceasefire.
No, but Israel violates it.
The November 2024 ceasefire with Lebanon on a near daily basis, Hezbollah had not fired
rockets at Israel for almost a year before this war.
But the one, the principle idea of the ceasefire was that the Hezbollah will disarm.
So Hezbollah since November, since the ceasefire, not only they did not disarm, but also they
were getting much more building their military capabilities.
And we see it now.
We see it now as they launch hundreds of rockets over Israel.
And the range of these rockets covers almost the entire country.
No country really can live under these threats of either missiles or nuclear threat from
Iran or rockets from Lebanon, which is not the Lebanese government.
The Lebanese government, we support the Lebanese government.
We would like very much to see the Lebanese government regain sovereignty over the entire
territory of Lebanon.
Hezbollah is the one that actually is undermining Lebanon.
And guess what?
It's hard to believe you support the Lebanese government when we are seeing that Israel is
again, as with the genocide in Gaza, Israel is again bombing hospitals, in public infrastructure,
killing civilians, children, healthcare workers, journalists, that doesn't sound like support.
But you said earlier that Israel has no ambitions of territorial expansion into Lebanon.
Your own defense minister, Israel Katz, said, and I quote here, he ordered an acceleration
in the destruction of Lebanese homes in accordance with the model of Beta Nun and Rafa in Gaza.
So is Israel applying the same Gaza playbook to Iran and Lebanon?
Really, I am no spokesman of minister Katz nor of its life to be.
You are defending Israel's position.
So I'm challenging you on a claim you made that Israel has no ambitions for territorial expansion.
And here's the defense minister saying exactly the opposite.
Well, I again, I do not explain, I do not what he says, but I know that this is, he
is not the one to decide to make such a move.
It's the entire cabinet and the entire cabinet and the prime minister said that we are,
we have no ambitions about Lebanon.
But look at Lebanon now.
It's not run by the government, but by Iran and their proxy, Hezbollah.
This is where we have to defend ourselves.
And this is the cornerstone of our entire policy towards Lebanon in self-defense.
And I can guarantee you really that if Hezbollah lives up to its commitments and
this arm, you will not see one soldier, one foot soldier of Israel in on Lebanese territory.
So Israel strikes in Lebanon have killed 124 children.
That doesn't sound like self-defense when you are killing children.
So to that, I have a few answers.
First of all, it is, it is deplorable and it's unfortunate.
And every civilian killed as a collateral damage, certainly kids is very
unfortunate and we should all be very sorry for that.
But first of all, the numbers you mentioned are disputed.
I'm giving you numbers from UNICEF.
So again, who is responsible for that?
If Hezbollah positions its missiles and its bases
inside civilian centers, whether it's schools, whether it's offices, whether it's buildings,
you know, private buildings, you are, I'm sure there are reels.
There are footage that is the Israeli government has never provided any
evidence to prove that Hezbollah is using civilians as human shields.
But Israel's repeated use, repeated use of Palestinians as human shields has been
widely documented.
Again, there is ample evidence.
And I have seen footage.
I'm sure that really if you request it, I'm sure the idea of spokesman can
give you a lot of evidence.
And if I can intervene in supply that I'll be very happy to,
although I'm not a member of the government.
But we have here an enemy who does not really care about human
lives, not their own and certainly not ours.
So when you have to defend yourself against such an enemy, then you have to do
what you have to do.
And Israel has been very careful before attacking different areas.
We called.
We are until now the idea of spoken says to civilians, this specific area,
this coordinates, please leave the area because this area is a where Hamas or
Well, we've seen we've seen in Gaza, even aid workers who had sent
coordinates to the IDF, they were bombed.
They were killed despite doing that.
So we could conclude then that you believe the version of the IDF.
But what we have seen the sheer magnitude of the destruction says otherwise.
Well, war is a war is confusion.
War is destruction.
War is not clean action.
It's not laboratory.
And we can be very sorry for every loss of life, which was not involved.
But again, who is responsible?
The one who positions their weapons inside embedded inside a civilian population,
even though there is no evidence, even though there is no evidence
that has been provided to that effect.
We're going to have to leave it there.
Thank you for joining me on up front.
Thank you, really.
A controversial new law was approved in Israel this week that rights groups
say would deepen apartheid and kill Palestinian detainees faster and with less scrutiny.
The law imposes the death penalty by hanging forward.
A military court deems terrorist acts.
So what does this mean for Palestinians under Israeli occupation?
Joining me to discuss this is human rights lawyer Deanna Butu.
Thank you very much for joining us on up front.
Welcome.
Thank you. Thanks for having me.
So Deanna, this law imposes the death penalty by hanging on anyone who kills,
quote, with the intent to deny the existence of the state of Israel.
What does that even mean in legal terms to deny the the existence of the state of Israel?
Well, in lay terms, what it means is that it's anybody
who is not Jewish.
That's effectively what it means.
So in practice, what it has meant is that if a person who is Jewish does the killing
and they kill somebody who is Palestinian, they will not be anywhere close
to receiving the death penalty, whereas if it's a Palestinian, then they will.
And I think it's important to keep in mind that this isn't the question of murder.
This isn't the death penalty that we see in other countries around the world,
such as in the United States, where it's a question of prosecuting murder.
But this is only in relation to, as they would put it, denying the existence
of the state of Israel, meaning that anybody who wants to seek Palestinian freedom.
And so so far, just since the start of this year,
there have been eight Israelis who have killed eight Palestinians.
And we don't see that any of these Israelis are going to be prosecuted,
much less if they were prosecuted, get the death penalty, because they're not
killing with the intent to deny the state of Israel.
They're killing with with the with the for the sole purpose of the state of Israel.
They're they're committing murder for the sake of the state of Israel.
And that's going to be the difference.
So one member of the Knesset recently said there are no innocent civilians
and children in the Palestinian West Bank city of Jenin.
When you have a law that mandates execution and you have lawmakers,
parliamentarians speaking this genocidal language,
are you worried that the law will be applied indiscriminately?
So in the land that is from the river to the sea,
there are two different military systems in place.
The first military system is what most people would refer to as a civilian
military system.
And that military system is only in place for people who are Israeli.
The second system that is in place is the system that exists in the West Bank
and used to exist in the Gaza Strip.
And that's a military system that is only applicable to Palestinians.
It's a court system that has a conviction rate of over 90 percent.
Most of the convictions are the result of torture
or the result of, again, confessions through secret evidence or through torture.
And in those circumstances, we're seeing that that's going to be a mandatory
death penalty for those Palestinians.
You know, just staying with that, the impunity with which this has happened,
Israel's Channel 13 says that the country has already started
building an execution facility that is cynically dubbed Israel's Green Mile.
Executions will be done by hanging.
What do these preparations actually tell us about how imminent
the executions are under this new law and how they're going to be normalized?
I think they're going to start very quickly.
What they're going to do is I think that they're going to finish up trials
very, very, very quickly so that they can go ahead and carry out these hangings.
And and it's important to remember that there will not be an appeal process.
So unlike in other places around the world, there is no appeals process.
They must be carried out within 90 days.
And the other thing that's important to keep in mind is that we've already seen
that this Minister of National Security, the man who was promoting this law,
he was walking around carrying wearing a pin that was in the shape of a noose.
He was doing social media videos in front of, you know, gallows, a set of gallows,
a noose, and and he even had somebody within his own political party
dress up as an executioner for the Jewish holiday of Purim.
The Israeli public is very much behind this.
If they weren't, then we would have seen some level of outrage,
but it just doesn't exist.
And so I think that they're going to very much fast track this.
Again, because they can under international law,
Israel is actually not permitted to legislate on the West Bank
since this area is not part of Israel's sovereign territory.
UN Human Rights Chief Volker Turk also called for the law to be repealed,
saying that it is a violation of international law.
So my question is, if it is even illegal, can it be successfully challenged?
Well, here's the problem with the international legal system
is that it requires that you first use the domestic system
and then use any international mechanisms.
And Palestinians have done both under Israel's domestic system.
They have effectively legalized the imposition of Israeli military law.
They've done this since 1967.
And so since 1967, we've seen that that the Israelis have been
passing all sorts of military rules when it comes to Palestinians.
This is the essence of apartheid is that Palestinians don't get to choose
the very people who are instituting laws against them.
And so we've seen that on the domestic side,
where the Israeli Supreme Court has upheld this in the past.
The second part of it is that Palestinians have taken these types of cases
to international courts, in particular the International Court of Justice
and the International Court of Justice also said that Israel's actions
in the West Bank and in the Gaza Strip are illegal and that they must be stopped.
Again, however, it goes back to the issue of political will
and whether anybody is going to stop Israel.
And once again, it's important to point out that
if they haven't stopped Israel when it's come to genocide,
the worst of the worst of international crimes,
I don't think that they're going to do anything to stop Israel
when it comes to this death penalty law.
And just talking about the double standards here,
I mean, Israel is currently imprisoning
nine thousand five hundred, about nine thousand five hundred Palestinians
and has been accused of torturing detainees.
I mean, just last month, I think the world was a gust
when five Israeli soldiers walked free either were accused of gruesome
sexual violation that left a Palestinian detainee with extensive injuries.
How does this lack of accountability contrast with this new law?
When it comes to that Palestinian who was very brutally raped
raped and almost lost, almost died from it,
he ended up not ever being charged with anything because he didn't do anything.
And so again, you see that that these prisons are just
a mechanism for freely torturing Palestinians
and for these for these soldiers to be able to get away with it.
We have seen over time, it's not just October of 2020.
but over time, since 1967, even earlier, that less than 3% of Israelis who carry out crimes
against Palestinians actually face any form of conviction. This very same minister once served
as the lawyer for a man who burned an 18-month-old Palestinian child and his parents to death.
President Trump launched the war in Iran a month ago, but does he know how to end it?
Now European leaders say they'll help Trump on the Strait of Hormuz, but how much damage
will be done to U.S.-European relations long after Trump's epic fury subsides?
Your weekly take on U.S. politics, the bottom line.
Iran's foreign ministry dismisses the U.S. President's warning and vows a swift retaliation
to any U.S. attacks. That's as airstrikes slam into Tehran. At least 13 people have been killed
in the latest attacks. U.S. troops rescue a second airman in a high-stakes mission in Iran
two days after his fighter jet went down, and more Iranian attacks target Israeli cities.
Two people are killed in Haifa as the search continues in the rubble of a destroyed apartment
building. U.S. President Donald Trump has renewed threats to destroy Iranian power plants and
bridges if it doesn't reopen the Strait of Hormuz. He shared what appears to be a deadline
on social media Tuesday, 8 p.m. Eastern Time. Earlier, Trump posted an expletive-laden threat to
his true social account. It promised that Iranians would be, quote, living in hell if the Strait
isn't reopened. Tehran has emphasized that it will retaliate if struck. Foreign ministry
spokesman Ismail Bagawi says U.S.-related locations in the Middle East would be targets.
Our armed forces have made it clear that in case Iran's infrastructure is attacked,
we would react in kind. They would, our armed forces would target any similar infrastructure
that is owned or in any way or manner related to the United States or contributes to their
active aggression against Iran. Overnight, U.S.-Israeli attacks on and near the Iranian capital
have killed more than a dozen people. Strikes on a residential area south of Tehran have left at
least 13 dead. A separate attack on a residential area in the city of Qom has also killed five
people. We'll be live from Tehran in just a moment, but first Al Jazeera's Mike Hanna
has more on President Trump's comments from Washington D.C.
to deal with the situation. But now the demand about opening the Strait of Hamuz
appears front and center of the president's new demands of the Iranian government.
President Trump threatening to, and I use his words,
blowing everything and taking the oil if Iran does not meet his new deadline,
which has now been set at 8 p.m. Eastern time on Tuesday evening.
He says in an earlier media post that power plant day and bridge day all wrapped up on Tuesday.
But on the other hand, in addition to these threats, President Trump is sending signals
that there's some kind of negotiation process underway. He's indicated that his close confidants
Jared Kushner and Stephen Whitcoff are in consultation with either the Iranian government
and identified figures or some form of intermediary. And speaking to US news outlets,
President Trump says that he is optimistic that there can be an agreement very soon.
He says the agreement could come within a matter of days rather than a matter of weeks.
So you've got this dichotomous approach from the president on the one hand threatening
obliteration to civilian targets within Iran, which some observers would contend to be a
war crime. But on the other hand, what he is saying is, yes, we are talking,
the talks are going well, and they could come to fruition before that new deadline I set,
which is 8 p.m. Eastern time on Tuesday. Mike Hannah, Al Jazeera, Washington.
The speaker of Iran's parliament has also responded to President Trump.
In a social media post, Mohammed Begur Ghalibov wrote,
your reckless moves are dragging the United States into a living hell for every single
family, and our whole region is going to burn because you insist on following Netanyahu's commands.
Make no mistake, you won't gain anything through war crimes.
Let's bring in Mohammed Val now who joins us live from Tehran.
Mohammed, it's another firm stance that Tehran is taking against these threats.
What else is Iran saying?
Well, there is a lot of statements to the same effect, aside from those statements given by
the spokesman of the foreign ministry, and by way he added some explanation of why Iran is
sticking to its stance towards this war. He said this war is an illegal war that has
been imposed on Iran and many other countries. He said it is based on a series of lies,
including the lie that Iran was pursuing nuclear weapons production,
and the lie that Iran was presenting an imminent threat to the United States,
and the lie that this war is waged in the name of the Iranian people to liberate them.
And he basically made it clear that Iran is not going to be intimidated
by those threats by Donald Trump because it has the means to defend itself,
and because it considers that it is wronged in this stance.
We have also another statement by former Foreign Minister Mohammed Javad Zarif just a while ago.
Iran will defend itself, but heed this warning for your own good.
This aggression began with a war crime targeting and murdering 170 school children.
Yesterday, in desperate and vulgar outbursts, Trump openly threatened further war crimes,
complicity equals international criminal responsibility.
Very strong statements by several leaders here in Iran that this war is a series of war crimes
against Iran, and that threats are not going to intimidate Iran from defending itself,
and also, by the way, also the commander of the IRGC has made it clear again that Iran is not
about to relinquish its hold on the state of Hormuz, and that it is even going to utilize
its leverage in the future to extract fees from ships that are going to use this state,
because Iran has undergone a lot of destruction and loss in this war,
and it is going to compensate that loss via future control over the state of Hormuz.
And also, there are threats by other field commanders here in the army,
and that if the situation continues and if the threats continue, Iran may also consider
closing the Babel-Mendem Strait.
Okay, Mohammed, in the meantime, rescue crews are searching for survivors near Tehran
after deadly strikes. There's been, I think, almost a dozen strikes around the country overnight.
Do you have any more details about those?
Yes, the latest of those was in a town south of Tehran. 13 people were killed according to
local authorities, but we have a series of cities, more than a dozen cities that have been hit
during the last several hours, including Bandar Abbas, most of them in the south,
Bandar Abbas, Ahvaz, particularly Atiyah Airport, and Mahshahr City.
We have also Bandar Lenge. We have Kung City, where six people were killed and 17 were wounded.
We have Shiraz, Isfahan, Karaj, and also Qum, where five people were killed according to
also government sources. So a series of strikes, probably more than any other day in this war,
now the scope of this bombardment by the Israelis and Americans is widening,
and also civilians are dying according to reports we are receiving.
Okay, Mohammed Vahl reporting live for us from Tehran. Mohammed, thank you.
The threat of escalation in Iran puts the Gulf region squarely in the crosshairs.
The sites Iran is threatening to hit back at are almost entirely located in GCC countries,
which are already coping with daily attacks. Kuwait says it has been hit by a series of drone
attacks. Authorities report that two major power and desalination plans were targeted.
One of the facilities is in Al-Zur, nearly 90 kilometers south of Kuwait City.
Another attack hit the finance ministry complex. That building is in central Kuwait City.
And in Bahrain, Iran targeted an oil facility, sparking several fires.
Emergency response teams says the blaze has been fully extinguished.
Over the past few weeks, Minama has come under repeated Iranian missile and drone attacks.
Mohammed Jam Joom is here in the Qatari capital of Doha and joins us now live.
Mohammed, we know the Gulf countries are bracing for this escalation
if Donald Trump carries out his threats, but is there anything conceivably they can do
except be defensive? Well, that's right. There's a huge amount of concern right now.
We're at a critical juncture as the populations and the governments in these Gulf countries
worry about what exactly is to come next. Let me first just mention the latest we're hearing when
it comes to attacks emanating from Iran against some of those Gulf countries. In the last few
hours, we've heard different statements from the ministries of defense in both the UAE
and in Kuwait that their air defense systems were intercepting missiles and drones that
have been launched towards them. We're also hearing now the last few minutes reports
that the sirens in Kuwait have been activated once more. So it seems as though perhaps more
interceptions happening right now will get you more details as they emerge.
When it comes to what exactly the Gulf countries can do, look, they're very concerned
because they understand that if Donald Trump carries through with this threat
that he's made that as of Tuesday, 8 p.m. Eastern time, if Iran has not reopened the
trade of Hormuz and if the U.S. in conjunction with Israel go ahead and start bombing energy sites
and power plants and bridges and civilian infrastructure sites in Iran, they understand
that to mean that Iran will retaliate by targeting similar sites throughout these Gulf
countries. And already, as you mentioned, we've seen the targeting of desalination plants,
energy infrastructure sites, power plants, as well as civilian infrastructure sites
in these Gulf countries since the beginning of this war. So a lot of worry right now
as to what exactly is to come next. And as you mentioned, you know, these countries,
they have maintained a defensive posture since the war began, but they've also continued to insist
that their patients can only last so long. So what does that mean going forward?
Nobody really knows at this point, but everybody is worried.
Yeah, that is the concern. Meanwhile, Mohammed Iran insists continually that the
Strait of Hormuz is actually open, of course, that it's closed only to the United States
and Israel and their allies. It's also been holding meetings with Oman about the Strait.
Do we know much about what's happening in those meetings?
So Riley, all we've heard is that there was a meeting that was held on Saturday.
This came via a statement that was confirmed via the Omanis and the Iranians.
You had the deputy foreign ministry level officials meeting and also accompanied by
experts. And what we've heard is that what was discussed at that meeting was a way to formulate
a plan whereby there would be some sort of mechanism to monitor shipping in the Strait of Hormuz
going forward and that perhaps they could come up with an agreement by which it would
simplify the way that ships would go through the Strait of Hormuz in the future.
They've said that there were objectives that were discussed, but we don't yet know
what those objectives are. And therein lies the complication because even if Iran and Oman were
to agree to objectives, were to come up with some sort of mechanism, that does not mean that any
other countries in this region would agree to it. That does not mean that the U.S. would agree to
that plan. If the U.S. does not agree, does that mean that the U.S. would then escalate again
attacks against Iran? We don't know. This is riddled with complications. The fact of the
matter is we've also heard Iranian officials over the course of the last several days
say that they're considering putting forth some sort of tolling structure in the Strait
of Hormuz. That complicates things further as well. So basically at this moment,
yes, it seems positive that this meeting took place, but still far more questions than answers
as of today. Mohamed Jamjoum reporting for us from Doha. Mohamed, thank you.
A U.S. airman has been rescued in Iran after an intense 48-hour search operation.
The weapons system officer had been missing since Friday when the fighter jet he was in
went down in the province of Kogilie and Boyar Ahmed. Tehran said it shot down the F-15E,
a two-seater aircraft. John Hendren reports from Washington, D.C.
It was a daring and risky mission to save an American airman from becoming an Iranian prisoner
of war. Iranian forces searched the mountainous areas of southwestern Iran after an F-15E fighter
jet went down on Friday. It was the first time a U.S. aircraft had crashed in hostile
territory in the five-week-old war. Two Blackhawk helicopters took fire as U.S. teams raced to
find the missing crew member. An A-10 Warthog, an air support aircraft, was also damaged,
its pilot ejecting over the Gulf. Iran broadcast photos of what it said was debris
from the fighter jet, including a jump seat. Although the pilot had been rescued on Friday,
the weapons specialist remained in hiding, evading Iranian forces for two days.
Finally, early on Sunday, deep in Iranian territory, the U.S. search operation was successful.
President Donald Trump made the announcement on social media, posting,
We Got Him, saying the Colonel had been behind enemy lines in the treacherous mountains of
Iran being hunted by our enemies. He said U.S. forces had been monitoring his location 24
hours a day and sent dozens of aircraft armed with the most lethal weapons in the world to retrieve
him. Trump added, He sustained injuries, but he will be just fine. A U.S. official told Al Jazeera
the rescue operation began in darkness but ended in an intense firefight and daylight,
before dozens of heavily armed aircraft and hundreds of troops transported the airmen
out of Iran. A U.S. officer in Iranian custody could have given Iran leverage,
as it had when Iran took U.S. hostages in 1979. With that crisis averted,
attention now shifts to the U.S. deadline for Iran to open the Strait of Hormuz.
John Hendren, Al Jazeera, Washington. In Lebanon, the Israeli army has carried out new
strikes on Beirut's southern suburb in a densely populated residential area.
The death toll has now risen to at least five, including three Sudanese nationals.
Fifty-two others were injured in those strikes. Three other people have been killed in an air
strike in the hills of Ainsadeh. Israel says it's continuing attacks on Hezbollah military
infrastructure. More than a million people have been forcibly displaced across the country.
Heidi Pett is live for us now from Beirut. Heidi, what are we learning about what was
hit and whether or not there were warnings for all of these strikes?
Yeah, so in the last 24 hours there's been a number of significant air strikes
across Beirut. The majority of those starting at midday on Sunday were in Beirut's southern
suburbs, which were subject to a renewed forced evacuation order by the Israeli military.
But one in the middle of the afternoon, Targaryenah, which is a very densely populated
residential area. It's close to one of the main hospitals here in Beirut, in fact.
The toll for that one was very significant. Overnight, the Ministry of Health has updated
its figures. Five people were killed, including a 15-year-old girl and three Sudanese nationals,
and more than 50 people were injured in that strike. Now, MSF doctors working at the hospital nearby
described a mass casualty event, people carrying the wounded in their arms. I'm here
at the headquarters of one of the local civil defense organizations who headed down to that
strike, and they said they pulled multiple injured people from the rubble with significant
shrapnel injuries. Now, shortly after that, a couple of hours earlier into Sunday evening,
we had another strike, what appears to have been an attempted Israeli assassination attempt
in a Christian neighborhood in East
Beirut. Now heading to the scene of that attack, neighbours were left absolutely bewildered
and frightened about why Israel was targeting someone in their neighbourhood. The projectile
came through the roof of a residential apartment building. It crashed through the third floor
and exploded in the second floor, killing three people there. One of them is a local leader
with the Lebanese forces, which is a right-wing Christian party. Now speaking to
people in the area, they were just they were devastated by this but also confused and fearful.
We had statements from MPs from his party saying that precautions needed to be taken when sheltering
the displaced who should only be put into official shelters because what happens now when we see
these strikes and particularly these assassination strikes outside of the areas where Israel says
that it's targeting Hisbola, people assume that these strikes are targeting, you know,
perhaps somebody who's recently moved into the area. But on the scene, the head of the
neighbourhood committee confirmed that the third floor apartment was empty. The owner of that
apartment speaking to local media confirmed he wasn't renting it to anybody but it gives you
some indication of the level of fear in Lebanon right now, this feeling that nowhere is safe
and the level of suspicion that is being driven by this Israeli policy of escalating
airstrikes across the country, including in areas where people would not expect them.
Heidi Pat reporting live for us from Beirut. Heidi, thank you.
At least two people have been killed in an Iranian strike on a building in the city of Haifa according
to Israeli media. The residential structure partially collapsed after the attack on Sunday.
At least four other people have been wounded. Rob McBride is following these developments
for us from the Jordanian capital Amman. Rob, do we have any more information about
what happened in this strike? Yeah, that's right. This search has been conducted through
the hours of darkness from Sunday night through now into the early hours of Monday morning here,
mainly looking for four people who are undercounted for, believed to be from the same one
apartment in this block that was probably the most heavily damaged. And we got confirmation from
one of the rescue teams that they recovered now two bodies with two people still remaining
missing. The authorities say that this building was hit by one heavy incoming missile because of the
damage done to the building, basically destroying half of it. The part that was left standing was
very unstable. There's been the risk of collapse as this search has been conducted, which has
made it all the more harder. But Haifa often finds itself on the front line being both targets
of Iranian missiles because of its strategic importance, but also within range of Hezbollah
rockets from across the border in nearby Lebanon. And in fact, while the search was going on,
another missile alert was issued because of fear of an incoming missile from Iran that has
since been lifted. During the early hours of Monday, three salvos were detected coming from
Iran. Alerts were issued throughout central parts of Israel. Most of those were intercepted,
others falling in open ground. The missile in Haifa was one of four that was fired
for salvos that were fired during Sunday. And the concern for authorities is that one of
those hit a very important industrial and chemical park down in the south of Israel in
near Beersheba. And the concern is that if this does escalate this week and in critical infrastructure,
including chemical works and petrochemical plants become now targets, then all of these
places now become on the front line in this escalating war of missiles between Iran and
Israel. Rob McBride reporting live for us from Amman, Jordan. Thank you, Rob.
Now let's take a look at some of the day's other news. Cuba is facing an unprecedented public health
emergency caused by an acute fuel shortage. It's the result of a near total U.S. blockade on fuel
imports that's now in its fourth month. Human rights organizations have condemned the ban as
an extreme form of collective punishment. Our Latin America editor Lucia Newman reports from Havana.
At Cuba's largest pediatric hospital, the emergency room is unusually empty,
not for lack of emergencies, but of public transport to get here, and not just for patients,
but doctors and nurses, too. Dressing us in oversized surgical robes that were recently
donated, anesthesiologist Anjot Ferdinandes takes us to the recovery room. It's almost
barren because surgeries have been reduced to the bare minimum.
We used to carry out 10,000 surgeries a year. I don't think we'll reach 1,000 this year.
After COVID, we went progressively downhill, but the public health system prioritizes
pediatrics, so we may do. But now our reserves are hitting rock bottom because of the power
crisis. Our laboratories can't produce medicine or anesthesia either.
More than three months of a near total U.S. fuel blockade on Cuba
are having deadly consequences, especially in hospitals and clinics,
where conditions are rapidly deteriorating. Even mortality, once the lowest in the Americas,
is rising steadily. And these are two very modern regimes. This one is much older,
but it's essential, and it doesn't have a battery. So if the light goes out, it's off.
Dr. Ferdinandes says it's like operating blind. Acute fuel shortages and constant
blackouts are also impacting life-saving treatments, like kidney dialysis.
At the Carlos Finley Hospital, patients say they're under extreme stress.
We have to come three times a week, and if you don't have transportation to get here,
you can die. So some of us can't leave the hospital at all.
In this salon, there are six patients receiving dialysis right now. But if there is a power
blackout, this machine, all of these machines have a battery, but they only last for 15 minutes.
That means that if the power generator of this hospital isn't working or it runs out of fuel,
the staff tell me that they've had to manually pump the blood back into the patient's body.
The Trump administration seems to believe the fuel blockade will speed up the fall
of its socialist neighbor. Yet even critics of the Cuban government acknowledge that this
latest act of collective punishment is harming not helping ordinary Cubans who are not responsible
for this decade's old dispute. Lucia Newman Al Jazeera, Havana.
In the Gaza Strip, Hamas says it will not hand over its weapons. Disarmament is part of the
second phase of the Gaza ceasefire plan. But the armed group says calls to lay down its
weapons are unacceptable, especially as Palestinians continue to be targeted by Israel.
More than 700 people have been killed since the ceasefire came into effect in October.
As for raising the issue of weapons in this crude manner, it is nothing but a scandalous
attempt by the occupation to continue killing and genocide against our people,
which we will not accept under any circumstances. We affirm that what the enemy was unable to
seize from us with tanks and genocide, it will not seize from us with politics or at
the negotiation table. The occupation's aggression against our people and its continued closure of
the blessed Al Aqsa Mosque to worshipers in an unprecedented manner and the approval of the
law for executing Palestinian prisoners, we call upon the masses of our Palestinian people in
the brave West Bank, the blessed Jerusalem and the occupied interior to march toward Al Aqsa Mosque.
Muin Rabani is a non-resident fellow at the Center for Conflict and Humanitarian Studies.
He says Hamas' statement confirms that talks to implement the second phase of the Gaza
ceasefire plan are deadlocked. What Hamas informed the mediators is that it will not discuss issues
such as disarmament relating to the second phase of the plan for the Gaza Strip until
the items of the first phase are implemented. That includes a cessation of hostilities,
as you noted, virtual daily Israeli attacks on the Gaza Strip have resulted in more than
700 Palestinians killed. Humanitarian aid continues to be restricted and most notably this
National Committee for the Administration of the Gaza Strip which was established by the
Board of Peace continues to be prohibited from entering the Gaza Strip by the Israelis
and the Board of Peace is doing absolutely nothing to ensure its ability to get in.
And so I think Hamas is taking two positions. A, it won't discuss the second phase
until the first phase is properly implemented and B, when those discussions do take place,
it's not going to simply surrender its weapons unless Israel clearly meets its own
obligations as well. And those are obligations that have to be consistent not just with what
the Board of Peace wants but with the international consensus and the rulings of the International
Court of Justice that this is an illegal occupation that must end. It's been a subdued
Easter in the occupied Palestinian territories where ceremonies have been scaled back because
of the Iran War. A small Sunday Mass was held at the Church of the Holy Sepulchre
in occupied East Jerusalem. The site is revered by Christians. Israeli authorities have limited
access to it. In Gaza, Orthodox Palestinian Christians who follow the Eastern calendar
have celebrated Palm Sunday. It marks the beginning of the Holy Week leading to Orthodox
Easter. Worshipers attended a Mass at the St. Poriferous Church in Gaza City.
As Christians around the world mark the Easter holiday under the shadow of war,
religious leaders are calling for peace. Sonya Gallego reports.
It is the most important date in the Christian calendar,
marked this year by both tradition and tension. Addressing more than a billion Catholics worldwide
from the Vatican, Pope Leo led his first Easter Mass as Pontiff. And the message from
St Peter's Square was shaped by events far beyond it.
Death is always lurking. We see it present in injustices, in partisan selfishness,
in the oppression of the poor, in the lack of attention given to the most vulnerable.
We see it in violence, in the wounds of the world, in the cry of pain that rises
from every corner because of the abuses that crush the weakest.
An appeal for mercy as the conflict in the Middle East loomed over what is meant to be
a celebration of renewal, where despite airstrikes and destruction,
many felt the need to commemorate the holiday. Over the weekend the message resonated
in Germany in the annual Easter March in Cologne, not a religious procession,
but a demand for an end to hostilities. And in France as the bells of Notre Dame
in Paris rang out, calling worshippers to mass. In Lyon, thousands of adults were baptized.
A sign said church leaders of the search for meaning in an evermore uncertain world.
Serbia says explosives have been found near a pipeline that carries Russian gas to Hungary.
Authorities say the discovery was made outside a Serbian town near the Hungarian border.
It comes just a week before closely watched elections in Hungary.
Prime Minister Viktor Orban is fighting to extend his 16 years in power.
One of China's leading arts universities has scrapped degrees in subjects such as
translation and photography. It says there are waste of national resources in the age
of artificial intelligence. The decision is fueling debate online about how far technology
could reshape education. Katrina Yu has this report from Beijing.
After graduating with a degree in English translation and interpreting,
but qualifications like hers could soon disappear. As some of China's biggest universities,
cut courses they say are being overtaken by artificial intelligence.
Alex says the move risks overlooking the broader skills behind translation,
from communication to critical thinking.
When you translate for sure, yes AI could probably get the accuracy up to
almost close to perfection, but there's still that personal style that's always been essential
in translation and when it comes to interpreting. It's not just translation, degrees in photography,
illustration and fashion design are also being scrapped, with universities saying the
future lies in human machine cooperation. The changes are part of a broader government
push to steer students towards industries it considers critical to the country's future,
including robotics, semiconductors and artificial intelligence.
The pressure is growing. More than 12 million students graduated in China last year,
a record number, and many are struggling to find jobs, highlighting a mismatch between skills
and demand. But AI is also creating new opportunities. In the film and creative
sectors, new roles are emerging like prompt engineers and AI animators.
Before AI, it could take a month just to design characters or scenes.
Now we can complete an entire project in a month.
Universities are trying to adapt, launching new programs that combine creative training
with AI skills. Alex says it's more important than ever for young people to diversify their
skills. She cites stand-up comedy among her own.
It's just a case that we're in this ever-changing and ever-changing, faster
time period of human history and we just have to be ready. It's just not those days anymore.
We can put our all of our eggs in one basket. But she says one thing still matters, the human
touch. Katrina Yu, Al Jazeera, Beijing. We'll be back at the top of the hour with more
coverage of the war between the US, Israel and Iran. The bottom line is next.
Because of Israel's insistence on striking oil facilities inside Iran.
This is one of the oil facilities of the country that has been targeted.
You can see the puff of cloud. Once those interceptors take out those
missiles and rockets and drones. Hezbollah rockets have reached this far into Israeli
territory in Israel. Consider this a serious escalation. Lebanon's government is struggling
to meet the demand for emergency shelter. This stadium is being converted into a mini-tent city.
Stay with Al Jazeera for the latest developments.
On counting the cost with higher oil prices and east sanctions, Russia is hoping to gain from
the conflict in the Middle East and further its war aims in Ukraine. But those plans are at risk
from Ukrainian attacks. So can Russia help fill the global energy gap or is its capacity
under threat? Counting the cost on Al Jazeera.
Iran has been able to absorb wave after wave of Israeli and US bombings,
which are also killing civilians as in the case of 168 schoolgirls killed on the very first day
of the conflict and destroying the country's industrial and energy infrastructure. Iran
has hit back at Israel and US military bases across the Arab world and shaken the global
economy by blocking access to the Strait of Hormuz. So are we heading to a quick resolution
or are we heading to a long war of attrition? And is the war on Iran triggering something much
bigger, a very new and different global world order? Today we're talking with US political
scientist John Mirsheimer, professor of international relations at the University of
Chicago and he's author of How States Think, The Rationality of Foreign Policy. John,
it's great to be with you again. This is one of those moments again where the world is
watching the tit for tat between the United States and Israel on one side, Iran on the other.
That's one way to cover it. Another way to cover it is ask what this moment means to the global
order, to American power, you know, to the super states in the world. And I'd love to get your
take on the temperature of the global order as you see it and what Iran means to that.
Well, I think a lot of people talk about how this is going to affect the global balance
of power or the distribution among the most powerful states on the planet and that would
include, of course, China, Russia and the United States. And I don't think that this war is going
to have any effect on the distribution of power in the international system. Where this war
really matters is in terms of how the United States uses the power that it has. And I think that
under the Trump administration, what we have seen is that the United States has pursued a set of
policies that undermine our ability to project all of that power that we have around the globe.
Now, what exactly am I saying here? I think if you're a great power like the United States and
you're interested in using all that power you have, it's very important that you pay attention to
international institutions, which you, by the way, have created. You pay attention to
international law, which you, by the way, have largely written. And you also get great lengths
to foster good relations with your allies. Because institutions, international law and
allies are important for projecting power. And what the Trump administration has done,
and it is doing very clearly in the case of the Iran War, is that it's undermining international
law. It's undermining international institutions, both of which it needs. And it's doing great
damage to its relations with allies in Europe, in Asia, and certainly in the Persian Gulf.
So this war in Iran is disastrous for the United States. It's not
It's going to undermine our basic power structure.
We have lots of power.
But what it's going to undermine, and of course this is consistent with what President Trump
has been doing since he first returned to the White House in January 2025, is undermine
our ability to project power.
I think you framed it really in such a fascinating way that when I think about it listening
to you, you know, I think about UN rapporteurs, I think of prosecutors of the International
Criminal Court, they're the ones being punished in this moment.
They're the ones that are being sanctioned and pushed, and it kind of raises this kind
of question about the solvency of institutions, the solvency of international law.
But I'm interested in the equation that you said after this is over, the distribution
of power remains the same.
But doesn't America basically suffer at all in a world where it has tossed out its own systems?
Well, the point here that you want to keep in mind, Steve, is that the power that any
country has is largely dependent on the material capabilities that has.
The two building blocks of power are wealth and population size.
And you use that wealth and you use that population size to build powerful military forces.
And the fact is that the United States is able to behave in a rather cavalier and one
could argue reckless way, and that will not have any effect on those material factors.
To give you a good example, the United States lost the Vietnam War.
Between 1965 and 1975, we engaged in this war in Vietnam and suffered a devastating defeat.
But it had no effect on the balance of power.
The United States was not less powerful.
We didn't have less people, less wealth, and a weaker military as a result of the
war.
And that's the same basic argument that I'm making here.
This foolish foreign policy that President Trump is pursuing as evidenced by what's going
on in Iran is not weakening American power.
What it's weakening is our ability to project power because it's undermining institutions.
Just think about NATO.
NATO is an international institution.
The United States has depended heavily on NATO for many, many years since 1949 to be specific.
Is it in our interest to undermine NATO?
Is it in our interest to undermine international law?
Is it in our interest to undermine the International Court of Justice?
I think the answer is no.
We need these institutions.
We need allies.
But President Trump, who is a unilateralist at heart, doesn't think that you need multilateral
institutions.
He doesn't think you need international law.
And he's contemptuous of our allies.
And in many ways, he treats our allies worse than he treats our adversaries.
Well, let's listen to President Trump, who has something to say about exactly this.
Let's listen.
We're now totally independent of the Middle East, and yet we are there to help.
We don't have to be there.
We don't need their oil.
We don't need anything they have, but we're there to help our allies.
He's basically saying, I agree with John Mearsheimer in that.
We don't need our allies.
We don't need this.
We can walk through the world as a single actor and be arbitrary one way or the
other.
But your thoughts, John?
Well, I mean, to argue that we're totally independent of the Middle East is ridiculous.
The fact is there are three areas of the world that the United States cares greatly about.
This is where our vital strategic interests are engaged.
One is obviously Europe.
The other is East Asia.
And then the final one is the Persian Gulf because of the oil.
It is a vital strategic area of the world for the United States.
And to argue that we're independent of it, it doesn't matter to us, is a foolish argument
to make.
You know, President Trump often talks about leaving the war.
What is he saying here, that we're going to leave the Middle East?
We're just going to forget the Persian Gulf.
We're going to forget that oil.
Of course, we're not going to do that.
We're going to remain there because it is a vital strategic area of interest to us.
So I don't know what he's talking about.
And with regard to allies, as I said, we need allies.
We need allies in the Gulf.
We have allies in the Gulf.
We need allies in Europe.
The idea that we are an independent actor that doesn't depend on allies is a foolish
argument to make.
The United States is a great power that tries to project power all across the globe.
How do you project power all across the globe without allies?
And the answer is you don't.
And when you start slapping him around the way he does, you're going to find yourself
in a well of a lot of trouble.
And as is clear, we are in a well of a lot of trouble in Iran.
So my guess, my question is, if you saw Iran as a nefarious actor in the world, why
not take this kind of action now and use it at a moment to reorder those relations?
So pick that apart.
First of all, this argument that Iran is a great threat to stability in the Middle East
and a serious threat to the United States is nonsense.
The greatest threat to stability in the Middle East is the United States working closely
together with Israel.
Iran has not started a war in centuries.
As best I can tell, it's not a highly aggressive country.
The country in the Middle East that is highly aggressive is Israel.
The country that has committed genocide in Gaza is not Iran.
It's Israel.
And we were complicit.
We meaning the United States were complicit in that genocide twice once last year in
June of 2025.
And again, on February 28th of this year, the United States and Israel launched
unprovoked attacks against Iran.
So the idea that Iran is this great destabilizer in the Middle East is a myth that the United
States and Israel purvey.
This is not to say that Israel doesn't, I'm assuming that Iran doesn't present
some problems in the Middle East that the United States has to be concerned about.
But the idea that this is a serious threat, much less an existential threat, is not a serious
argument.
That's point number one.
Point number two is if you look at what the Israelis and the Americans are now doing
to deal with this purported Iranian threat, what you see is we've taken measures that
have made the situation much worse.
In fact, one could argue that we are going to crash the international economy as a result
of this war that Israel and the United States started.
I would make the argument that we are on the edge of the precipice in terms of the state
of the world economy because of this war.
This war shows no signs of ending anytime soon.
Then already great damage has been done to the international economy and more damage will
be done the longer the war goes on.
So this idea that number one, Iran is a great threat to the United States is bogus.
And number two, the idea that President Trump and his friends in Israel are making a safer
and more stable Middle East is a ludicrous argument.
In fact, what they're doing is they're putting the entire world on the precipice of a disaster.
One of the things that I find interesting is when you kind of talk to war planners,
strategists, cross-Republican and democratic circles, it's hard to find anyone that
wouldn't have expected that Iran would shut down and use the Strait of Hormuz as
a choke point, that in fact the Strait of Hormuz was really Iran's nuclear bomb.
That if you wanted to create something that they thought was deterrents, I'm just interested
in why you think this White House had none of that input or just disregarded that element.
I actually think it's quite clear.
President Trump has said that he was forewarned that the Iranians were likely to shut
down the Strait, but he said that it didn't matter.
And the reason that it didn't matter is that the administration thought that they could win a quick
and decisive victory.
They thought that they could launch, and when I say they, we're talking about the United States
and Israel, which I like to refer to as the TAG Team.
The TAG Team thought that they could launch a shock and awe strategy against Iran,
which would involve decapitating the regime.
And because that regime had so little support in the general population in Iran,
the decapitation or the shock and awe strategy would lead to a revolution,
the regime would be overthrown.
And the new regime would either submit to our demands or the old regime
would remain in place and just surrender.
Those were the two things that they thought might happen.
But the point is that this shock and awe strategy would produce a quick and decisive
victory, and therefore you wouldn't have to worry about the Iranians closing the
straits. But what happened here, obviously, is that the shock and awe
strategy failed and we're now in a war of attrition.
And in this war of attrition that we now find ourselves in, the Iranians
hold almost all the cards, not us.
And that's why we are in desperate straits.
It is interesting that President Trump said the opposite.
We have all the cards and Iran has none.
So I take your point.
But another element here is other big global powers, China, Russia.
How are they looking at this moment?
Is China fearful of a more muscular United States willing to deploy power
like this? Or is it basically applauding this moment as an opportunity for itself?
Well, I think from a Chinese point of view, one could argue that what's
happening is mana from heaven.
That this is a case of the United States, which says that its
principal threat in the world is China and that its principal mission is to
pivot to Asia and contain China is now enmeshed in self, itself,
in a war in the Persian Gulf that is causing it to pivot away from East
Asia and weaken its containment strategy towards China.
You want to remember that the United States is moving Patriot and
Thad missile batteries out of East Asia.
This marine expeditionary unit that has just been moved to the Middle East
came from Japan.
So what you see, Steve, is that the United States is actually
weakening its military capability in East Asia.
Again, we're pivoting away from East Asia and this is mana from
heaven for the Chinese.
Furthermore, Chinese influence around the world is increasing.
You remember I talked before about the ability of a state to project
power around the world to have an effective diplomatic strategy.
If you look at the United States and you compare it to China
in terms of state behavior, in terms of which state looks like
a responsible stakeholder in the international system.
It certainly looks like China is the responsible stakeholder.
The Chinese look like they are the adults in the room.
The United States certainly does not look like a responsible stakeholder.
The Gulf States, the Europeans, our Asian allies are all questioning
whether or not the United States is playing with a full deck.
All of our allies around the world can't believe what we're doing.
They fully understand that we are threatening
the international economy.
We're threatening to take the international economy off a cliff,
which is going to have devastating consequences for every state on the planet.
So when you think about where China stands versus where the United States
stands in the eyes of the world, the Chinese have benefited enormously from this conflict.
UAE Ambassador to the United States Yusuf Otaiba just published an op-ed
recently in the Wall Street Journal, we said you can't just a ceasefire is not
enough because you will leave Iran not defeated, not crippled, able to do various things.
There I just be interested to get your take on this because, you know,
I think you said America has opened a Pandora's box of messes.
Now many people in the region say, well, you've you've got to continue
what you're doing. Don't leave it like this. Where what are your thoughts?
I think this is remarkably foolish.
Both the Saudis and the UAE have indicated that what they'd like to see
the United States do is finish the war, go full bore and defeat Iran once and for all.
First of all, we're not going to defeat Iran once and for all.
And if we march up the escalation ladder, as they would like us to do,
there is a very good chance that the UAE and Saudi Arabia will be
destroyed as functioning societies.
You want to understand that these countries depend heavily on desalinated water
and they're a handful of desalination plants in each of these countries
that are big fat targets that the Iranians can go after.
And not only can the Iranians go after those desalination plants,
they can go after their energy infrastructure.
They can go after their oil and gas infrastructure.
They can destroy those countries.
And if the United States begins to attack a broader set of targets in Iran,
the Iranians who have been playing tit for tat all along
have made it clear that they will destroy or they will attempt to destroy.
And I think they will destroy countries like the UAE and Saudi Arabia.
So if anything, Steve, what the UAE and Saudi Arabia should be doing
is telling the Americans to back off and to work over time to come up
with some sort of negotiated settlement to put an end to this war.
These countries, the Gulf States, that is, have absolutely no interest
in seeing this war continue.
They had no interest in seeing this war start.
In the beginning, and I just don't know what they're thinking
when they're talking about getting America and Israel to up the ante.
You know, other parts of the dashboard of this conflict right now
or what's happening in Lebanon, Israel's commitment to essentially occupy
parts of Lebanon, what's going on in Gaza.
And I'm just interested in how you see the other dimensions
of the Middle East beneath the Iran conflict that are also parts
of the puzzles that are moving right now.
Well, let's start with Lebanon and there are two dimensions to the war in Lebanon.
One is the ground war where the Israelis are attempting to take more territory.
And I think many Israelis, especially on the right hand side
of the political spectrum, want to annex the southern part of Lebanon
from the northern border of Israel up to the Latani River.
And in fact, if you look carefully at what's happening in southern Lebanon
at this point, the Israelis are suffering a series of tactical defeats.
They are having one whale of a lot of trouble fighting against Hezbollah
on the ground in southern Lebanon.
And the idea that they're going to conquer all of southern Lebanon,
I think, is wrong.
And I think they're going to suffer a lot of casualties trying to do that.
And they already are, of course.
Second point I'd make is that by the end of 2025, it looked like Hezbollah
had been defanged and that the Israelis had done egregious damage
to Hezbollah's ability to fire rockets and missiles into Israel.
So as you moved into this year, it looked like Hezbollah had been defanged
and couldn't cause Israel any problems with its rockets and missiles
because it had hardly any left.
Israel had destroyed all of them.
That has clearly not happened.
And not only is Hezbollah firing rockets and missiles into northern Israel
and even as far as into Tel Aviv on a daily basis, but the Iranians
are coordinating with Hezbollah and the Iranians are firing missiles
into northern Israel and into Lebanon itself.
So the Hezbollah threat is there in spades with regard to Gaza and the genocide.
There's no question that the Israelis have slowed down the genocide.
But if you look at their behavior, they're very interested for sure
in cleansing all of Gaza, of Palestinians, and they're pursuing a genocide
in hopes that that will allow them to get all of the Palestinians out of Gaza.
And if they don't get them out, murder them while they're in Gaza.
And we don't want to lose sight of the fact, Steve, that on the West Bank,
the Israelis are launching pogroms on an almost daily basis
because they're interested in ethnically cleansing the West Bank as well.
So if you look at what's going on here with Israel, Israel is deeply involved
in a conflict in southern Lebanon and with Hezbollah.
Furthermore, it's involved in a genocide in Gaza.
It's involved in pogroms on the West Bank.
And furthermore, it's constantly attacking Syria.
And on top of all that, it dragged the United States into a war against Iran.
You know, Israel is by far the most aggressive state in the Middle East.
What could make an argument that it is the most aggressive state on the planet?
This gets back to our earlier discussion of whether Iran or Israel
is the greatest threat to stability in the Middle East.
I don't know how anybody could make the argument that it's Iran.
The answer is it's Israel.
And most importantly, you want to remember that Israel is committing
the greatest of all crimes, which is genocide in Gaza.
And no matter what you think of the Iranian regime,
the Iranian regime is not committing genocide.
It's a messy world,
and that's why we always love talking to you.
University of Chicago political science professor
John Mirsheimer, thanks so much for joining us today.
It was my pleasure, Steve.
Thanks a lot for having me.
So what's the bottom line?
However this war ends and however long it takes,
one thing has become really clear.
Today's world is governed by the sword.
The order that prevailed over the past few decades
is just crashing down
and being replaced with a much more vicious system.
The United States is the change agent now
using brute force where it sees oil or assets
or territories that it wants.
Staying in old alliances like NATO
may just not be worth it for a new America.
If anything, we're heading back to the 19th century.
A dog eats dog, might makes right,
no rules place where all countries are up for grabs
and everyone needs muscle if they want to survive.
And that's the bottom line.
This is America with Al Jazeera's exclusive interview
with US Secretary of State Marco Rubio.
What are your main demands?
The Iranian regime can never have made their weapons.
The Iranian regime is able to take a lot of pain.
What's worse than having no off-ramp?
Having no allies.
NATO has done absolutely nothing.
This sound and that sight
can become the new normal across the continent.
This is America, every weekday on Al Jazeera.
Hard-hitting interviews.
I'm afraid that you might be one of the targets.
Anyone could become a target.
We have seen that they have no hesitation
about targeting any place.
Facing realities.
Does Qatar still trust Iran enough to mediate?
Let's say that this aggression
brings a benefit for no one.
Thought-provoking answers.
How many have been displaced inside Iran?
I've heard three million.
It could be more.
Hear their story on Talk to Al Jazeera.
There are police here who are saying
that they just want to keep the peace.
But there's still a lot of them.
The commanders here say their role
is to make sure that GOMA is protected.
This camp was supposed to be temporary.
Now there are more than 200,000 Sudanese refugees.
Hello, this is Al Jazeera, live from Doha,
with our continuing coverage of the war
between the U.S., Israel and Iran.
I'm Riley Carlson, here's what's coming up.
Donald Trump sets a Tuesday deadline for Iran
to reopen the Strait of Hormuz,
or the U.S. will bomb its power plants,
bridges and quote, unleash hell.
We are determined to defend.
Iran's foreign ministry dismisses
the U.S. president's warning
and vows a swift retaliation to any U.S. attacks.
That's his airstrike slam into Tehran.
At least 13 people have been killed in the latest strikes.
U.S. troops rescue a second airman
in a high-stakes mission in Iran
two days after his fighter jet went down.
And more Iranian attacks target Israeli cities.
The bodies of two victims have been recovered
from the rubble of a destroyed
apartment building in Haifa.
U.S. president Donald Trump has renewed threats
to destroy Iranian power plants and bridges
if it doesn't reopen the Strait of Hormuz.
He shared what appears to be a deadline on social media.
Tuesday, 8 p.m. Eastern time.
Earlier, Trump posted an expletive laden threat
to his true social account.
It promised that Iranians would be quote,
living in hell if the Strait isn't reopened.
Tehran has emphasized that it will retaliate if struck.
Foreign Ministry spokesman Ismail Begai says
U.S. related locations in the Middle East would be a target.
Our armed forces have made it clear
that in case Iran's infrastructure is attacked,
we would react in kind.
They would, our armed forces would target
any similar infrastructure that is owned
or in any way or manner related
to the United States or contributes
to their act of aggression against Iran.
Overnight, U.S. Israeli attacks on and near
the Iranian capital have killed more than a dozen people.
Strikes on a residential area south of Tehran
have left at least 13 people dead.
A separate attack on a residential area
in the city of Qom has also killed five people.
We'll be live from Tehran in just a moment,
but first Al Jazeera's Mike Hanna
has more on President Trump's comments
from Washington, D.C.
The unusual use of an expletive by a national leader,
perhaps a symbol of President Trump's frustration
with the Iranian government
and their refusal to concede to the demands
that he is making.
That reference as well was to the Strait of Hamouz,
which in recent days, President Trump had insisted
he did not care about saying the U.S.
did not need the oil passing through the Strait
and it was up to the countries
who are reliant on that oil to deal with the situation.
But now the demand about opening the Strait of Hamouz
appears front and center of the President's new demands
of the Iranian government.
President Trump threatening to, and I use his words,
blowing everything and taking the oil
if Iran does not meet his new deadline,
which has now been set at 8 p.m. Eastern time
on Tuesday evening.
He says in an earlier media post
that a power plant day and bridge day
all wrapped up on Tuesday.
But on the other hand, in addition to these threats,
President Trump is sending signals
that there's some kind of negotiation process underway.
He's indicated that his close confidants, Jared Kushner
and Stephen Whitcoff are in consultation
with either the Iranian government
and identified figures or some form of intermediary.
And speaking to U.S. news outlets,
President Trump says that he is optimistic
that there can be an agreement very soon.
He says the agreement could come within a matter of days
rather than a matter of weeks.
So you've got this dichotomous approach
from the President on the one hand,
threatening obliteration to civilian targets within Iran,
which some observers would contend to be a war crime.
But on the other hand, what he is saying is,
yes, we are talking, the talks are going well,
and they could come to fruition
before that new deadline I set,
which is 8 p.m. Eastern time on Tuesday.
Mike Hanna, Al Jazeera, Washington.
The Speaker of Iran's parliament
has also responded to President Trump.
In a social media post, Mohamed Begur Ghalibov wrote,
your reckless moves are dragging the United States
into a living hell for every single family.
And our whole region is going to burn
because you insist on following Netanyahu's commands.
Make no mistake, you won't gain anything
through war crimes.
Let's bring in Mohamed Val now,
who joins us live from Tehran.
Mohamed, what else is Iran saying about these threats
or the prospect of a change to the situation
in the Strait of Hormuz?
Yes, Iranian leaders are speaking in one voice
about this situation, and they are all saying
that Iran will not be intimidated
and will not be surrendering to the threats
by Donald Trump, even though the deadline
is fast approaching, the spokesman of the foreign ministry
also said that this war is illegal.
He made sure to explain the situation again
to the international community, to the general public
and also to the Iranians,
that Iran has the right to defend itself
till the end because this war has been imposed on it.
This war is illegal.
This war is based on a series of lies,
such as the lie that Iran was pursuing
the production of nuclear weapons,
that Iran was presenting an imminent threat
to the United States, and also that this war
has been waged to liberate Iranians
from a despotic regime as per the American terminology.
So they are all saying that this war is illegal.
It shouldn't have been waged on Iran on the first place.
Iran is wronged, and it has the right
to defend itself till the end
and to use whatever means it have,
including the military, in their first place.
And they say that they have what it takes.
Also, I have another statement
by former Foreign Minister Mohamed Jawad Zarif in this regard.
He said, Iran will defend itself
but heed this warning for your own good.
This aggression began with a war crime
targeting and murdering 170 school children.
Yesterday, in desperate and vulgar outburst,
Trump openly threatened further war crimes.
Complicity equals international criminal responsibility.
So there is no wavering here
and there is no spirit of compromise in Iran.
And the thing is that they say also
that if things get more complicated
and if the Americans continue to wage aggression
on the country, they will not only keep closing
the straight up hormones,
but also they will close the straight up babelment
which is going to add more complexity
and intensity to the international global energy crisis.
Yeah, it surely would.
Mohamed, the Israeli military says a wave of strikes
against government infrastructure in Tehran
was completed a short time ago.
We know that several cities came under attack.
What can you tell us about what was happening
around the country overnight and into this morning?
The Israeli more than a dozen cities have been bombarded
during the last several hours and throughout the night
and Tehran bore the brunt of that bombardment.
We can talk about 23 people killed around Tehran
during these strikes.
13 of them in the city of Baharistan.
It's a small town just to the south of Tehran.
Six of those 13 are children according to local authorities.
We have also the cities of mostly cities in the south
like Bandar Abbas, Ahvaz,
where the East airport was targeted.
We have Mahshahr city.
We have Bandar Lenge.
We have Kung city where six people were killed, 17 were wounded.
Shiraz also was bombarded, Isfahan, Karaj
and Qum were five people were killed.
So it's been an extraordinary night
of huge bombardment and strikes across the country.
Mohamed Vahl reporting live for us in Tehran.
Mohamed, thank you.
The threat of escalation in Iran puts the Gulf region
squarely in the crossfire.
The sites Iran is threatening to hit back at
are almost entirely located in GCC countries
which are already coping with daily attacks.
Kuwait says it has been hit
by a series of drone attacks.
Authorities report two major power
and desalination plans were targeted.
One of the facilities is in Al-Zor,
nearly 90 kilometers south of Kuwait city.
Another attack hit the finance ministry complex.
That building is in central Kuwait city.
And in Bahrain, Iran targeted an oil facility
sparking several fires.
Emergency response teams said the blaze
has been fully extinguished.
Over the past few weeks,
Manama has come under repeated Iranian drone
and missile attacks.
Mohamed Jamjum is here in the Qatari capital
of Doha with us now.
Mohamed, how concerned are Gulf countries
about these threats from the U.S.
President of this escalation?
Riley, it's a very concerning moment
for these countries, their governments
and the populations.
Let me first just mention where we're at
when it comes to some of the attacks
that we were hearing about the last few hours.
There have been statements from
the ministries of defense in both the UAE
and Kuwait over the course of the last few hours
that they had been intercepting missiles
and drones launched from Iran.
And we've heard in the last hour
that sirens have been going off in Kuwait as well
and that loud booms had been heard.
So we're waiting more details on those specific incidents
we'll get them to you as we have them.
When it comes to the rest of these Gulf countries,
look, one of the reasons that they're so concerned
is because Donald Trump has continued to threaten Iran
that if Iran doesn't reopen the Strait of Formuz
that the U.S. will attack power plants and bridges
amongst other sites in Iran.
And the Gulf countries are aware
that Iran has stated in the past that if the U.S.
and the U.S. and Israel escalate the war with Iran
and start attacking civilian infrastructure
and power plants and bridges,
that then they would target sites
of similar stature in Gulf countries.
And we've already seen desalination plants,
as you mentioned just a moment ago,
and petrochemical companies
and energy infrastructure sites
in many of these countries be targeted,
not just over the course of the past 48 hours,
but over the course of the past few weeks.
So that's the reason why this is such a time of concern
and such a critical juncture.
The fact of the matter is the countries in the Gulf,
they have been in a defensive posture since all this started,
but they've also repeatedly stated
that their patience is not without limit.
And so the question becomes if the U.S. strikes Iran,
if Iran retaliates by striking energy infrastructure sites
and civilian sites, power plants
and desalination plants in the region,
what will these countries do
and how will they cope going forward, right?
Yeah, and in the meantime, Iran insists, of course,
that the Strait of Hormuz is open,
just not to U.S. or Israeli ships or their allies.
But do we know if any progress
is being made behind the scenes
when it comes to plans to maybe broaden
who could move through it?
Well, Riley, what we know at this point
is that Oman and Iran had a meeting on Saturday
that they were represented
by deputy foreign ministry officials in those talks.
There were also experts from both countries
and that they were discussing trying to set up
some kind of a mechanism to monitor the shipping routes
in the Strait of Hormuz and what comes next.
Now, we've heard from Iranian officials
over the course of the last few days
as we've heard that being reported
from our correspondents in Tehran
that Iranian officials are considering
putting forth some kind of tolling mechanism
in the Strait of Hormuz.
We don't know if that's something
that's been discussed with Oman.
Oman is trying to de-escalate the situation.
The Omanis and the Iranians have said
that as a result of this meeting
they've identified objectives to continue talking about.
What we don't know is if those objectives
would be acceptable to the other Gulf countries,
the GCC states, we also don't know
if those objectives, if they were agreed upon,
would be acceptable to the U.S.
And if they're not acceptable to the U.S.,
what happens then?
This is a vital waterway
where 20% of the world's energy supply goes through.
It's been in a chokehold ever since this all began.
Of course, the Iranians do not want to give up
their leverage when it comes to the Strait of Hormuz.
So what exactly happens next?
Nobody really knows.
We do understand that the Omanis
are trying to de-escalate the situation.
They're trying to set up a mechanism.
Wherefore, it can be simplified
as far as the shipping that goes through
the Strait of Hormuz.
But at this point, far more questions
than there are answers.
All righty.
Absolutely, Mohamed Jamdroom for us here in Doha.
Thank you, Mohamed.
A U.S. airman has been rescued in Iran
after an intense 48-hour search operation.
The Weapon System Officer had been missing
since Friday when the fighter jet he was in
went down in the province of Kogilue
and Boyar Ahmed.
Tehran said it shot down the F-15E,
a two-seater aircraft.
John Hendren reports from Washington, D.C.
It was a daring and risky mission
to save an American airman
from becoming an Iranian prisoner of war.
Iranian forces searched the mountainous areas
of southwestern Iran
after an F-15E fighter jet went down on Friday.
It was the first time a U.S. aircraft
had crashed in hostile territory
in the five-week-old war.
Two Blackhawk helicopters took fire
as U.S. teams raced to find the missing crew member.
An A-10 Warthog, an air support aircraft,
was also damaged,
its pilot ejecting over the Gulf.
Iran broadcast photos of what it said was debris
from the fighter jet, including a jump seat.
Although the pilot had been rescued on Friday,
the weapon specialist remained in hiding,
evading Iranian forces for two days.
Finally, early on Sunday,
deep in Iranian territory,
the U.S. search operation was successful.
President Donald Trump made the announcement
on social media, posting We Got Him,
saying the Colonel had been behind enemy lines
in the treacherous mountains of Iran
being hunted by our enemies.
He said U.S. forces had been monitoring
his location 24 hours a day
and sent dozens of aircraft
armed with the most lethal weapons in the world
to retrieve him.
Trump added he sustained injuries,
but he will be just fine.
A U.S. official told Al Jazeera
the rescue operation began in darkness
but ended in an intense firefight and daylight
before dozens of heavily armed aircraft
and hundreds of troops transported the airmen out of Iran.
A U.S. officer in Iranian custody
could have given Iran leverage,
as it had when Iran took U.S. hostages in 1979.
With that crisis averted,
attention now shifts to the U.S. deadline
for Iran to open the Strait of Hormuz.
John Hendren, Al Jazeera, Washington.
In Lebanon, the Israeli army has carried out new strikes
on Beirut's southern suburb
in a densely populated residential area.
The death toll has now risen to at least five,
including three Sudanese nationals.
52 others were injured in those strikes.
Three others had been killed in an air strike
in the hills of Ainsade.
Israel says its continuing attacks
on Hezbollah military infrastructure,
more than a million people
have been forcibly displaced
across the country.
They hit a completely civilian area.
It's mostly migrants here, Sudanese people.
People were at home and they struck them.
Are those military objectives?
Where is the UN?
No one says anything.
Aren't they human too?
They're killing children and women.
The whole world has to speak up.
It has to see and say something.
Have we become nothing but numbers?
Are people of numbers?
How is that possible?
We are devastated.
Our morale is low.
When you see your friends and neighbors in pieces
on the ground and blood everywhere
and the house destroyed,
our house was destroyed.
Where are we going to sleep?
Where do we go?
Let's go live now to Zayna Khodor,
who joins us now from Beirut.
Zayna, you could hear in what those people
had to say, though, just how concerning it is
becoming in Lebanon,
that so many civilians are among the dead
in these strikes.
What more can you tell us?
The conflict is now in its sixth week
and the death toll just keeps climbing
with civilians being caught in this war.
According to Lebanese health ministry,
1,461 people have been killed,
more than 4,000 wounded.
Among those who are killed, children.
Roughly 130 children killed in that strike in Jnech neighborhood, which is on the edge
of Beirut's southern suburbs.
The strike came in without warning, and it is a densely populated area.
You mentioned three Sudanese nationals killed, but also a 15-year-old child.
Now the apparent target was a Hezbollah military commander, but despite these targeted
strikes, or what the Israeli military calls pinpoint strikes, at times civilians are killed.
Ayn Saadi as well.
This is an area just north of Beirut.
Three civilians were killed in a strike overnight.
They were in their apartment.
Again, it is not clear who the target was, because the missile targeted an empty apartment.
So that whole story or incident is still not clear.
In the south of the country, in the village of Tol in Nabatiyeh, a mother and a father
were killed.
Their children, a 15-year-old and 9-year-old, they were wounded.
And there have been cases in the south of the country where whole families are killed
in a single strike.
Now while the Lebanese health ministry does not provide any breakdown on the number
of civilians, how many combatants or civilians, but what is clear, at least 25%, roughly
25% have been women, children and medics.
And Zayna, let's stay in the southern part of the country for a minute here.
Where are the Israelis in terms of their ground invasion in the south?
What are they saying?
Well, that ground invasion continues.
But in the past 24, 48 hours, there hasn't been much advance on the ground.
The Israeli army cannot claim new military gains.
Yes, they are present in a number of areas, but territorial control does not mean operational
control because Hezbollah continues to target those troops in southern Lebanon.
But what we heard from Israel's chief of staff on Sunday was quite interesting.
When he says, yes, the supreme goal of Israel is the disarmament of Hezbollah.
But the current campaign is about advancing that goal.
He did not use the word achieve that goal, but advance that goal.
But he also mentions that more help is needed from the political leadership.
So this is the chief of the army saying that even though they reach up until the Letani River,
the declared aim of this invasion, it is not going to lead to Hezbollah's disarmament.
Hezbollah's strategic weapons, its military infrastructure is in the west of the country
and the Bekaa in Baalbek.
So the Israelis admitting even that 66 soldiers were wounded in the past three days.
So that invasion continues, but not much progress on the ground.
Zayna Khodor reporting live for us from Beirut.
Thank you, Zayna.
At least two people have been killed in an Iranian strike on a building in the city of Haifa,
according to Israeli media.
The residential structure partially collapsed after the attack on Sunday.
At least four other people have been wounded.
Rob McBride is following the developments here from the Jordanian capital, Amman.
Rob, what more do we know about this attack and the rescue mission that's been underway?
Yeah, this search has been underway through the hours of darkness from Sunday night
through now into Monday morning, made all the harder because this building has been in
a constant fear of collapse.
They were looking for four people who were unaccounted for, believed to be from the
same apartment.
And we got confirmation a short while ago that they have now recovered two bodies.
Two people remain missing.
As this search was continuing, there was another alert about an incoming missile.
This turned out to be an Iranian missile, one of these cluster warheads that spread damage
over a much wider area.
There were multiple impacts, quite a lot of damage recorded with four light casualties.
Now earlier on Monday morning, three salvos of missiles were detected from Iran fired
at the central part of Israel.
Alerts were issued.
Most of those were either intercepted or fell in open ground.
But as we've been coming on air, there's been confirmation of a much more serious missile
strike in the central part of Israel.
This again was multiple impacts from one or more missiles in the areas of Ben-Ai Barak
in Petitikva in Tel Aviv itself with confirmation that there have been three casualties, one
of those serious.
That is still a developing situation as we get into Monday morning here.
One of the missile that destroyed the building in Haifa, that was in a salvo of four that
were launched against Israel on Sunday.
One of those fell in a very important industrialized area in the south of the country near Beershiva.
There's a real concern that if there is an escalation this week as deadlines run
out and these ultimatums come into force, then increasingly Israel and Iran will be
getting involved in a far more serious exchange, targeting each other's critical infrastructure
and sites such as chemical factories and industrial works such as these as their war, their exchange
of missiles escalates, Riley.
Rob McBride, thank you for keeping us updated from Amman Jordan.
Let's take a look at some of the world's other news now.
In the Gaza Strip, Hamas says they will not hand over its weapons.
It is part of the second phase of the Gaza ceasefire plan, but the armed group says calls
to lay down its weapons are unacceptable, especially as Palestinians continue to be targeted by
Israel.
More than 700 people have been killed since the ceasefire came into effect in October.
As for raising the issue of weapons in this crude manner, it is nothing but a scandalous
attempt by the occupation to continue killing and genocide against our people, which
we will not accept under any circumstances.
We affirm that what the enemy was unable to seize from us with tanks and genocide, it
will not seize from us with politics or at the negotiation table.
The occupation's aggression against our people and its continued closure of the blessed
al-Aqsa mosque to worshipers in an unprecedented manner and the approval of the law for
executing Palestinian prisoners, we call upon the masses of our Palestinian people
in the brave West Bank, the blessed Jerusalem and the occupied interior to march toward
al-Aqsa mosque.
Mu'in Rabani is a non-resident fellow at the Center for Conflict and Humanitarian Studies.
He says Hamas' statement confirms that talks to implement the second phase of the Gaza
ceasefire plan are deadlocked.
What Hamas informed the mediators is that it will not discuss issues such as disarmament
relating to the second phase of the plan for the Gaza Strip until the items of the first
phase are implemented.
That includes a cessation of hostilities as you noted, virtual daily Israeli attacks
on the Gaza Strip have resulted in more than 700 Palestinians killed, humanitarian
aid continues to be restricted and most notably this national committee for the
administration of the Gaza Strip which was established by the Board of Peace continues
to be prohibited from entering the Gaza Strip by the Israelis and the Board of Peace is
doing absolutely nothing to ensure its ability to get in.
And so I think Hamas is taking two positions, A, it won't discuss the second phase until
the first phase is properly implemented and B, when those discussions do take place
it's not going to simply surrender its weapons unless Israel clearly meets its own obligations
as well.
And those are obligations that have to be consistent not just with what the Board of
Peace wants but with the international consensus and the rulings of the International
Court of Justice that this is an illegal occupation that must end.
It's been a subdued Easter in the occupied Palestinian territories where ceremonies have
been scaled back because of the Iran War.
A small Sunday Mass was held at the Church of the Holy Sepulchre in occupied East Jerusalem.
The site is revered by Christians as the traditional site of Jesus Christ's resurrection.
Israeli authorities have limited access there.
On Palm Sunday last week the Latin Patriarch was blocked from entering the church, sparking
international condemnation.
One of China's leading arts universities has scrapped degrees in subjects such as translation
and photography.
It says they're a waste of national resources in the age of artificial intelligence.
The decision is fueling debate online about how far technology should reshape education.
Katrina Yu reports from Beijing.
Alex Scher built her career in the creative industries after graduating with a degree
in English translation and interpreting, but qualifications like hers could soon disappear.
As some of China's biggest universities, cut courses they say are being overtaken by artificial
intelligence.
Alex says the move risks overlooking the broader skills behind translation, from communication
to critical thinking.
When you translate for sure, yes AI could probably get the accuracy up to almost close
to perfection, but there's still that personal style that's always been essential in translation
and when it comes to interpreting.
It's not just translation, degrees in photography, illustration and fashion design are also
being scrapped, with universities saying the future lies in human machine cooperation.
The changes are part of a broader government push to steer students towards industries
it considers critical to the country's future, including robotics, semiconductors and artificial
intelligence.
The pressure is growing.
More than 12 million students graduated in China last year, a record number, and many
are struggling to find jobs, highlighting a mismatch between skills and demand.
But AI is also creating new opportunities.
In the film and creative sectors, new roles are emerging, like prompt engineers
and AI animators.
For AI, it could take a month just to design characters or scenes.
Now we can complete an entire project in a month.
Universities are trying to adapt, launching new programs that combine creative training
with AI skills.
Alex says it's more important than ever for young people to diversify their skills.
She cites stand-up comedy among her own.
It's just the case that we're in this ever-changing and ever-changing faster
time period of human history.
And we just have to be ready.
It's just not those days anymore.
We can put our all of our eggs in one basket.
But she says one thing still matters.
The human touch.
Katrina Yu, Al Jazeera, Beijing.
We'll be back at the top of the hour with more coverage of the war
between the US, Israel and Iran.
Talk to Al Jazeera is next.
The latest news as it breaks.
A Russian oil tanker is on its way to Cuba,
carrying something like 670,000 barrels of desperately needed fuel with detailed coverage.
We have been hearing a number of gunshots by the Israeli military.
And this is another explosion very close to where people are living from around the world.
Many have told us that they're here to take a stand against what they call
the politics of hate and division.
As the United States and Israel continue their war in Iran,
the focus has been on missiles, targets and the question of who is winning.
But what if that's the wrong question?
Because in many modern conflicts, victory is no longer the only or even the main objective.
Wars today don't just destroy, they also produce.
They reshape power, economies and create systems that can outlive the battlefield itself.
From sanctions and arms industries to smuggling networks and shadow economies,
conflict can become functional.
For some, it consolidates political control.
For others, it opens new streams of profit.
And for many, it creates a constant state of threat that justifies its own continuation.
Wars are not always designed to end.
They evolve, adapt and sometimes they sustain the very actors fighting them.
In the Middle East, that system is becoming increasingly fragmented
as states are no longer the only players.
Armed groups, informal networks and regional actors play roles that shape conflicts
in ways the global powers can't fully control.
The consequences stretch far beyond the battlefield.
From energy markets to inflation, from superpowers to developing economies,
the costs of conflict are global.
But so too are its incentives.
So if war can become economically and politically useful,
what does that mean for peace?
To make sense of it all and to understand why some wars don't end,
we turn to a leading voice in the political economy of conflict.
Professor of Conflict Studies at the London School of Economics,
David Keane, talks to Al Jazeera.
David Keane, welcome to Talk to Al Jazeera.
You are a pioneer in the political economy of conflict,
so a field that shifts the focus away from who may be winning the war militarily
to who is essentially benefiting politically from all of this.
Can you start by explaining to us what that means?
Set out your store, friends, if you may.
Well, I think if we think about the aims in a war,
we often think the aim in a war is to win.
And clearly, that is an important aim in a war.
But there are also many others.
And one of them, I think, is making money.
Another one is a sort of a set of political functions or benefits
that may include things like suppressing dissent under the cover of war,
or divide and rule, or painting dissent as disloyalty.
Or even turning your enemy into the image
that you've put about in your propaganda,
making the enemy resemble your propaganda.
So those are two other aims.
Then there are sort of psychological aims.
And I think reversing shame and humiliation is often a big one.
And a fourth one, I would say, is the simple one of trying to stay alive.
Now, if the aim is winning, then what you need to do
is weaken or eliminate your enemy.
But with a lot of the other aims,
sometimes the enemy can be surprisingly useful.
So we get this phenomenon of useful enemies,
which I think is a real phenomenon.
And the problem there is that people acquire, as it were,
like quite a wide range of vested interests,
acquire an interest sometimes in actually maintaining the enemy
or taking actions that are predictably counterproductive
in terms of the reproduction of the enemy.
So making people angry, attacking civilians,
winning, as it were, new recruits for the entity.
It might be a rebel group or a terrorist group or a nation
that they claim to be trying to oppose or weaken.
So there's a question mark I'm trying to raise in a way
about the aims in a war
and whether the enemy is somebody that you want to eliminate
or somebody that you might be interested at some level
in continuing the existence of.
David, at this juncture in the Israeli-US war on Iran,
where despite claims by both sides
of a degree of military success,
it's almost impossible to say who the actual winners are.
But given your focus on how you frame world conflict,
I wonder whether it's possible to ask
who benefits from this tension the most
without potentially the need for an absolute victory?
Yeah, I mean, I think it's an interesting
and complicated question.
I mean, one of the things that we can observe,
and this is, I think, very common in wars,
is that even when there hasn't really been
convincing victory by any party,
a number of different parties find reasons to claim
that they have registered a success in the war.
And Trump, I think, awarded himself 15 out of 10
for his success in the war.
Israel, obviously, would claim some security benefits.
Iran can point to its ability to retaliate and so on.
But I think if you can claim success,
then that is kind of a political benefit in itself.
Beyond that, I think that the functions of war
as a distraction and the functions of war
as something that can quiet an internal dissent
and allow you to paint opponents as disloyal
is something that is really quite important
in the United States, in Iran, and in Israel.
And I think there are elements, for example,
of the revolutionary guards in Iran,
that have an interest in the continuation of sanctions,
that have an interest in the continuation
of international tension, pointing to common enemies,
labeling dissenters as disloyal and so on.
So these things come into play.
And I think in terms of Israeli politics,
there's been a lot of trying to portray opposition
as disloyal, there's been attempts to postpone
accountability for corruption.
There is, in a way, I think, a serial use of war,
including in Gaza, which was really a genocide in my book
to distract from a process of accountability at home.
I think Trump himself is very concerned
with distracting people at the moment.
Yeah, let me just jump in there
and break down what you've just said
because you've made it sound as if
the benefits of conflict for some countries
far outweigh the desire for any kind of lasting resolution
as a means of controlling opposition for...
or any kind of opposition within those given countries.
So war is the ultimate distraction, as you say.
Well, it is the ultimate distraction.
It doesn't mean that some of the threats are not real, you know,
because 9-11 was very real.
Iran has made many threats against Israel and so on.
You know, we have the horrific Hamas attacks on Israel and so on.
So these things are not necessarily invented
and often they're too ultra-real and all too horrible.
But nevertheless, you know, if we look at the pattern of responding to some of these events,
I think it does predictably create new enemies.
It does predictably enrage people.
And so we have to look beyond the declared aim of weakening the enemy
and the other possible functions, psychological, economic and political,
of taking these, what in my book, are predictably counterproductive actions
that are going to exacerbate conflict, that are going to perpetuate the war on terror,
probably entrenching the revolutionary guards in Iran, though, of course, we don't know.
You know, we have to keep an open mind about these things.
Just picking up David on something else you said,
because I'd like to know how this narrative of, I guess, a kind of continuous existential threat
allows countries to bypass demands within their own country.
So let's say demands for economic reform, human rights,
desire for an increase in public spending,
because in the first 100 hours of this conflict, the U.S. burned through $800 million per day.
I mean, that's significantly higher than the opening of the Iraq or Afghanistan wars.
I mean, that's money that could have been spent on housing, on education,
on healthcare in the United States, but it's been funneled into the war coffers.
Yeah, and I actually thought, you know, during the Trump's first administration,
the one sort of good thing about him was that he seemed to be relatively reluctant
to launch international wars.
You know, and he had a whole critique of the neoconservatives
and the way that, you know, a lot of the elements of the war on terror,
the waste of money, the waste of lives and so on, that that involved.
And that to me was the one really relatively convincing part of his campaign,
but he now seems to have radically departed from that.
And of course, Trump loves freedom.
I mean, he loves his own freedom and the ability to change his mind, to set the agenda.
And he has taken the United States in a radically different direction.
I also think Israel has kind of adopted some increasingly drastic remedies
to trying to solve the problem of its own security, you know, as we saw in Gaza.
So these things can kind of radicalize.
And actually, I think if you create enough enemies or you contribute to the existence of another enemies,
that in itself can encourage some very drastic solutions because of the fear of retaliation.
Talking about drastic solutions.
This is what the US Secretary of Defense Pete Hegseth said when he was questioned about the eye-watering costs of waging this war.
He said, quote, it costs a lot of money to kill bad guys.
It costs a lot of money to kill bad guys.
I mean, ironically, the Iranians have shown that they can fight an asymmetric war at a fraction of the cost.
That must be a rude awakening for the Trump administration.
Yeah, I think the Iranian regime has been quite clever in promoting influence in places like Syria, in Lebanon and so on at a fairly low cost.
You know, and a lot of it is encouraging militia strategies and recruiting people who are often quite impoverished at relatively low costs,
providing training which is relatively cheap and so on.
As far as the United States government is concerned, I think this division of people into good guys and bad guys is incredibly simplistic.
And it goes back at least as far as the Vietnam War.
And the idea there, as you know, was if we can just kill enough bad guys, kill enough Viet Cong, then this is going to solve the problem of Vietnam.
But we know that the mass bombing of Vietnam created a huge number of additional recruits to the Viet Cong.
So those tactics don't work.
And you have to think more creatively about how to isolate the so-called bad guys.
And that usually means tackling the corruption and the violence that has created a rebellion or a terrorist movement in the first place.
On that point, David, let's focus on Iran, if we may, because there are those clearly, as you've suggested, who benefit, I guess, from a continuation of the current system in Iran.
And when I say current system, I also mean potentially benefiting from a continuation of Western sanctions also.
I'm thinking about those who may have benefited from state monopolies, those who are controlling, smuggling, or the black markets, for instance.
Well, yeah, this is something that we see many times in conflicts.
We saw it in Syria.
We've seen it in former Yugoslavia as well, and Iraq as well.
When you get sanctions, you tend to get a big price difference between the country that's being sanctioned and the surrounding area.
And if you can actually successfully breach international sanctions, which clearly the revolutionary guards have done in the case of Iran,
the profits are often very considerable, and often you get a monopoly, as they have had, basically, as I understand it, on the smuggling that is breaching the sanctions.
So I do think sanctions are very problematic in that way, and it partly relates to people's ability to get around them.
And of course, the diverse nature of superpowers at the moment with Russia and China, and so on, you have plenty of options.
And you can go outside the dollar-based system.
This is part of the reason why so many people want gold at the moment.
Let me try to evade some of these sanctions.
Let me try and distill this then, because what I'm hearing is that you're saying that sometimes when the cost of war is cheaper for a nation,
or more beneficial for a nation than the price of peace, that it works in their interest to, in some way, sustain frictions, to maintain hostilities.
Yeah, I mean, I think the strongest example of that, or one of the strongest, is basically the incredible level of military spending within the United States that survived the end of the Cold War.
You know, you would have thought that was an opportunity to dismantle the military industrial structures, but spending stayed pretty much at the levels of the height of the Cold War.
So why was that opportunity not taken?
Well, clearly, there were a number of threats around the world, which the government pointed to, and the defense industry pointed to,
and terrorism was foremost among them for a while, and then Russia kind of came up with the agenda.
But that was an opportunity that was spurned.
And of course, these things have consequences, because if you build up your own arms, you're encouraging the other guy to build up their arms,
and then you can point to his arms build up as justification for your own.
And this is what happened during the Cold War.
So we have these kind of self-sustaining systems that are built on the mass manufacture of things that can kill people.
It is extremely profitable.
And there are a lot of predictably counterproductive tactics that are being adopted, which serve those systems.
And I think very rarely work.
Of course, you can declare victory.
You know, remember the mission accomplished in 2003 that George W. Bush declared.
But these victories very rarely materialize, because a war economy will often deepen, it will complicate.
Let me pick you up upon that point of mission accomplished, because we're talking about the apparent end of the war on terror,
the decades of conflict that came after 9-11.
I mean, we did, of course, see the destruction of Al Qaeda.
We saw the killing of Osama bin Laden.
We saw the U.S. pull out of Afghanistan.
But in your mind, is what we are seeing now in the Middle East some way of a continuation of that war on terror?
Or is it something else?
Is it something new?
Well, I think it is partly a continuation of it.
We saw, as you say, the defeat of Al Qaeda.
But then, of course, we had Al Qaeda in Iraq, which kind of grew out of it.
There was a claim of victory against Al Qaeda in Iraq.
But then we had ISIS, which grew to a large extent out of Al Qaeda in Iraq.
So you have this sort of serial declaration of victories, and then people can relax for a little bit.
But then something else happens.
And a lot of times these threats are feeding into each other.
There's a continuity between these organizations.
I think the destruction of Gaza, that is, in a way, a very distinct problem.
But it was an action that was presented by Israel within the framework of a war on terror.
In Sri Lanka, where I was in 2009, the government wreaked horrible destruction on the Tamil population
in the name of an international war on terror.
And it was actually difficult for Britain or the United States to criticize that.
When they themselves were detaining people indefinitely,
they themselves had the language of the war on terror and we need to be ruthless.
We need to suspend liberty to a certain extent in the interest of security.
Specifically on the language used around the war on terror,
I guess a very seismic symbolic shift at least came with the rebranding of the Secretary of Defense
to the Secretary of War, the Defense Department to the War Department
because I mean that signaled almost a kind of move away from more of a reactive war on terror
to a US administration that sought to project power, to pursue a peace through strength,
I think, as the words used by Pete Hegseth.
So do you see that as a rebranding of what's gone before?
Or is that really a defining departure from what we've seen in the past?
I think it's a great question. I think it is partly a rebranding.
But it's partly an indication that violence and the assertion of America's right,
in particular, to do what it likes, has become sort of incredibly shameless under Trump.
And Trump is somebody really who has systematically rejected shame
and indeed made a lot of political capital, in my opinion,
out of offering people a kind of vicarious shamelessness through his abuses
and through his spectacular demonstrations of freedom, as I say, freedom for himself.
So I think there are some significant differences.
For example, George W. Bush and Tony Blair,
they did make some efforts to try to create some sense of international legitimacy
for what they wanted to do in Iraq and to try and get the UN on board to a certain extent.
We're not seeing that now with Trump and Netanyahu.
We're just seeing a kind of go it alone spirit, which I think is incredibly dangerous
and incredibly destructive.
So I do think there's a shamelessness about what's going on
and that thing you mentioned about relabeling as a Department of War.
You know, Trump would say, well, this is, you know, this is honesty.
You know, he projects this image of honesty. I'm not a hypocrite.
The liberals are hypocrites. I tell you the truth as it is.
And he's made some considerable political capital out of that, in my opinion.
But it's also a very frightening turn.
David, talking about political capital, we've talked about the big powers.
I'd like to talk about the small powers, if I may,
because I wonder if the rise of non-state actors,
Hezbollah in Lebanon, the Houthis in Yemen,
whether they fit into this into this frame as well,
because I want to know if they are motivated by the same impulses
that perhaps Iran or the United States may be for their own ends.
I mean, how does your approach to this work,
when war is being waged by smaller paramilitary networks,
okay, some see Hezbollah as being almost a kind of mini-franchise of Iran
in the same way that you would view the branch of a bank internationally.
But is that a wrong way of looking at this?
Well, I think a lot of these non-state actors,
they do very often have state backers,
and we've seen it with Hezbollah,
we've seen it with the rapid support forces and the UAE in Sudan.
So we can't sort of regard them simply as non-state actors.
I think that in the case of Hezbollah in Lebanon,
there has been quite a strong effort from the Lebanese government
to weaken Hezbollah,
and that's something that can potentially, I think, bear a lot of fruit.
And then when Israel comes in and starts bombing Lebanon
and displacing, as I understand it, a million people,
this can easily set things back.
So the states tend to sort of weigh in on these struggles,
these local struggles, often in extremely counterproductive ways.
I think Sudan is an interesting case of a government that,
going back to the 1980s, tried to mobilize militias,
mobilize its own militias for the purposes of counterinsurgency.
But then the government, in a way, lost control of the violence
because the militias were economically motivated to a large extent.
They spread rebellion to new areas,
and on the whole, they refused to disband after particular military campaigns,
and they became, as were, a political factor in their own right.
And we know that the RSF is a successor to the Janjaweed militias
that created the Darfur genocide.
And it's been a huge factor in Sudan politics ever since,
basically extorting the government,
using gold in particular to build up its strength,
and eventually turning against the army
with the result of this horrific civil war that we have at the moment.
So militias don't always obey what their puppet masters
tell them to do, and that can be very destructive in itself.
David, can a conflict like the Iran-Israel rivalry ever truly end,
taking in everything you've discussed,
or does that system simply evolve into new forms of hybrid warfare,
or to protect essentially underlying profit margins
and existing power structures?
Well, I think conflicts can come to an end.
I think a lot of people thought that the Cold War would never end
because partly of the vested interests unfold,
but it did actually surprise us by ending.
Of course, people who were making the argument that it will never end
will now point to various aspects of a revival of the Cold War,
in terms of Russia and even China and so on.
But I do think sometimes that violence is a little bit like energy
in the sense that it can change from one form to another,
but it very rarely disappears entirely.
In practice, I think one of the things you can do is to make peace
more profitable and more attractive for various warring parties
than war itself.
You can offer them a stake in a political settlement, in a peace process.
You can buy them off if you like.
One of the problems with that, of course, is that you tend to entrench corruption
and indeed violence within the peace settlement
that you're actually creating or offering.
David, in a fragmented global economy,
how does the political conflict of those big powers,
the political conflict that we are seeing play out in the Middle East,
I mean, how does that affect the global south?
How does that affect nations that are watching from the sidelines
or simultaneously protecting the big powers in Washington D.C.
in Beijing or Moscow, for instance?
I think there are a lot of economic impacts as well.
For example, there were...
Food Program now is talking about perhaps 45 million people
facing severe food shortages and starvation
as a result of the war that's currently going on
with Iran and Israel and the United States.
So, you know, we know that oil prices are going up.
We know that fertilizer prices
have been drastically affected.
This affects food production
and it affects people's food security.
And I think, you know, if we go back in history
just a little bit to, for example, 2011,
you know, you had a huge increase in global food prices
for various reasons.
And that fed rather directly into famine
in places like Yemen and Somalia.
And it also fed into the so-called Arab Spring
and the Civil War in Syria, for example.
So these kind of knock-on effects, you know,
they're not always predictable,
but I think you can predict that many of them
are going to be extremely bad
and the people that are going to suffer
are going to be, you know, very far from Washington
or Jerusalem.
David King, thank you for talking to Al Jazeera.
Yeah, pleasure to talk to you.
As the war on Iran escalates,
Al Jazeera's correspondents are on the ground.
Donald Trump says he intends to speak to the Iranians
in the next couple of days,
but added he has no idea
who will be on the other end of the call.
Well, most of the people we had in mind are dead.
A lot of signs, people saying that the U.S.
should not be attacking Iran,
calling on Congress to act.
Members of Congress are away from Washington this weekend.
There needs to be the proof
of an imminent threat to American interest.
This was our last best chance to strike.
The U.S. Senate has decided they are not going to step in
and stop this ever-expanding war.
Stay with Al Jazeera for the latest developments.
Tehran, a city where centuries of history
rise from its histories and monuments,
now coming under assault.
At the heart of the city stands Kolesan Palace.
More than four centuries old,
a witness to coronations and major political decisions,
but now damaged by American and Israeli airstrikes.
International organizations like UNESCO
warn about the impact of these attacks
on our collective heritage.
They are UNESCO World Heritage sites,
priceless treasures that belong to all of humanity.
Many now fear that centuries of history
could become another casualty of war.
Hello, this is Al Jazeera live from Doha
with our continuing coverage of the war
between the U.S., Israel and Iran.
I'm Riley Carlson, here's what's coming up.
Donald Trump sets a Tuesday deadline for Iran
to reopen the Strait of Hormuz
or the U.S. will bomb its power plants, bridges,
and quote, unleash hell.
We are determined to defend.
Iran's foreign ministry dismisses
the U.S. president's warning
and vows a swift retaliation to any U.S. attacks.
That is airstrike slam into Tehran province.
At least 23 people have been killed,
including six children.
At least five people have been killed
in an Israeli strike on Lebanon's capital.
We're live in Beirut's southern suburb.
And more Iranian attacks target Israeli cities.
Two bodies have been recovered
from the rubble of a destroyed apartment building in Haifa.
U.S. president Donald Trump has renewed threats
to destroy Iranian power plants and bridges
if it doesn't reopen the Strait of Hormuz.
He shared what appears to be a deadline on social media.
Tuesday, 8 p.m. Eastern time.
Earlier, Trump posted an expletive latent threat
to his true social account.
It promised that Iranians would be quote,
living in hell if the Strait isn't reopened.
Tehran has emphasized that it will retaliate if struck.
Foreign ministry spokesman Ismail Bagai
says any U.S. related location
in the Middle East would be a target.
Our armed forces have made it clear
that in case Iran's infrastructure is attacked,
we would react in kind.
They would, our armed forces,
would target any similar infrastructure
that is owned or in any way or manner
related to the United States
or contributes to their act of aggression against Iran.
We will be live from Tehran in just a moment,
but first, Al Jazeera's Mike Hanna
has more on the president's comments from Washington, D.C.
The unusual use of an expletive by a national leader,
perhaps a symbol of President Trump's frustration
with the Iranian government
and their refusal to concede to the demands
that he is making.
That reference as well was to the Strait of Hormuz,
which in recent days, President Trump had insisted
he did not care about saying the U.S.
did not need the oil passing through the Strait
and it was up to the countries who are reliant on that oil
to deal with the situation.
But now the demand about opening the Strait of Hormuz
appears front and center of the president's
new demands of the Iranian government.
President Trump threatening to, and I use his words,
blowing everything and taking the oil
if Iran does not meet his new deadline,
which has now been set at 8 p.m. Eastern time
on Tuesday evening.
He says in an earlier media post
that a power plant day and bridge day
all wrapped up on Tuesday.
But on the other hand, in addition to these threats,
President Trump is sending signals
that there's some kind of negotiation process underway.
He's indicated that his close confidants,
Jared Kushner and Stephen Whitcoff,
are in consultation with either the Iranian government
and identified figures or some form of intermediary.
And speaking to U.S. news outlets,
President Trump says that he is optimistic
that there can be an agreement very soon.
He says the agreement could come within a matter of days
rather than a matter of weeks.
So you've got this dichotomous approach
from the president on the one hand,
threatening obliteration to civilian targets within Iran,
which some observers would contend to be a war crime.
But on the other hand, what he is saying is,
yes, we are talking, the talks are going well,
and they could come to fruition
before that new deadline I set,
which is 8 p.m. Eastern time on Tuesday.
Mike Hannah, Al Jazeera, Washington.
The speaker of Iran's parliament
has also responded to Trump.
In a social media post, Mohammed Begur Ghalibov wrote,
your reckless moves are dragging the United States
into a living hell for every single family.
And our whole region is going to burn
because you insist on following Netanyahu's commands.
Make no mistake, you won't gain anything through war crimes.
Meanwhile, overnight and early morning,
U.S.-Israeli attacks on Iran have killed at least 34 people.
Strikes across Tehran province
have left at least 23 people dead,
including half a dozen children.
The capital itself has also been hit.
A separate attack on a residential area
in the city of Qom, south of Tehran, killed five people.
And in southern Iran, a strike on the city of Bandar-Leng
has killed another six.
Let's bring in Tohida Sadina, who joins us live from Tehran.
Tohida, the Israeli military, says the waves of strikes
against government infrastructure in Tehran
was completed just a short time ago.
What more can you tell us about the attacks
that took place overnight and into this morning?
Well, actually, Tehran had another night
of heavy bombardment last night in the eastern, southern,
as well as the western parts of the capital.
But the most notable one, I think,
happened in the Sharif University of Technology,
the campus at which was targeted,
living an unprecedentedly huge amount
of damage to this building
and the other buildings in the areas near the campus.
And of course, we know that a gas facility
was also targeted around the area.
And we know that it is force major university
that has been targeted over the past few weeks,
showing the extended scope of the Israeli
and American strikes now targeting
more infrastructural areas, including universities,
hospitals, schools, oil-related
and still related infrastructure,
all putting a huge amount of pressure
on the economy of the country.
But beyond the capital, we know that in other cities,
we had the continued campaign of the air strikes
by the Americans and Israelis
in the cities of Karaj, Tehran, Shiraz, Esfahan and Boucher.
We've got the reports and footages coming
about the severe damages to the areas
as a result of these attacks in Bandar-e-Lingas.
You mentioned six people in Wom five people
and in the Baharistan, a small city located
in the southern areas of the capital.
At least 13 people, according to the local authorities
have been killed among which six were children.
We're dealing with these air strikes continuing
and impacting the very infrastructure of the country
following the recent threats
by the U.S. President Donald Trump.
Yeah, and Toheed, on those threats
from the U.S. president, what else is Iran saying
about either those threats or the prospect
of any change to the situation in the Strait of Hormuz?
Yes, indeed.
We're dealing with a sort of high-stakes situation
but according to what we hear from the Iranian side,
first, they're not that much unfamiliar
with this threatening language.
It's like dancing with the same old tune for them
since the very beginning of this war.
They're facing threats
but this is not just limited to this war
but earlier also they had this language experienced
but also we know that they're taking it quite seriously.
Seeing as I told you, the extended nature
of the scope of the attacks over the past one or two weeks,
I would say, and the message furthermore
that is coming from Tehran is that of defiance,
the resilience and deterrence, and of course, retaliation.
They are saying that in case of more attacks
on the infrastructure of the country,
there is going to be a tit for tat strategy
targeting the U.S. assets across the region
or any infrastructure in which the United States
has got a share or an assist associated with
and of course, the Israeli territories.
But speaking of the state of Hormuz,
again, we are hearing a lot of statements
from the Iranian side.
The gist of the matter is that the country is trying
to use it as a leverage point
in this already actually intricate situation
seeing the Jewish strategically significant role
of this choke point
and they're also trying to implement plans
to impose tariffs for the ships
which are planning to pass through.
And last but not least, they are saying that it's not open,
it's not closed, it's open to everyone,
it's close to our adversaries.
All right, Tohide Sadi reporting live for us from Tehran.
Tohide, thanks.
The threat of escalation in Iran
puts the Gulf region squarely in the crossfire.
The sites Iran is threatening to hit back at
are almost entirely located in GCC countries,
which are already coping with daily attacks.
Kuwait says it has been hit by a series of drone attacks.
Authorities report that two major power
and desalination plans were targeted.
One of those facilities is in Al-Zor,
nearly 90 kilometers south of Kuwait city.
Another attack hit the finance ministry complex.
That building is in central Kuwait city.
In Bahrain, Iran targeted an oil facility
sparking several fires.
Emergency response teams said
the blaze has been fully extinguished.
Over the past few weeks,
Minama has come under repeated Iranian
missile and drone attacks.
Malik Trena is live with us now from Kuwait city.
Malik, how concerned are Gulf countries
about the U.S. president's threats of escalation here?
Extremely concerned to say the least, Riley.
I mean, you know, the secretary general
of the GCC, Jasmin Abdaoui, earlier this week
said that 85% of the retaliation attacks
coming from Iran have targeted the Gulf.
You know, more than 6,000 now ballistic missiles
and drones have targeted this entire region.
So people become extremely concerned.
You know, just in the last 30 to 40 minutes or so,
we heard about authorities responding
to an incident in Abu Dhabi
and the industrial city of Abu Dhabi
where debris from an interception
injured one person.
In the last couple of hours,
we've seen alarms raised here in Kuwait
and also more so and a few others in the UAE.
You know, yesterday was a really devastating day
for people here in Kuwait.
You know, we had two water and power,
water desalination plants targeted.
The Azur plant that you mentioned earlier
is one of the biggest in the Middle East.
So the Iranians have proven
that they can target and hit
civil civilian infrastructure here in the Gulf.
So that's extremely worrying.
You know, whenever President Trump escalates,
Iran retaliates.
And so, you know, people who,
what I've seen in the last couple of days, Riley,
is authorities here in Kuwait
have been putting power generate,
huge power generators next to distribution,
electricity distribution centers
that just goes to show you that authorities here
are, you know, making contingency plans
for if this war escalates.
You know, I think the call has been
to de-escalate the situation
and try to bring this war to an end.
Nobody here across the region
wants to see things increase,
you know, increase and escalate.
They certainly do not.
Malik Trena, live for us in Kuwait City.
Malik, thank you.
In Lebanon, the Israeli army
has carried out new strikes
on Beirut's southern suburb.
In a densely populated residential area,
the death toll has now risen to at least five,
including three Sudanese nationals.
52 others were injured in those strikes.
Three more people were killed
in an airstrike in the hills of Ainsadeh.
Israel says it's continuing attacks
on Hezbollah military infrastructure.
More than a million people
have been forcibly displaced across the country.
They hit a completely civilian area.
It's mostly migrants here.
Sudanese people.
People were at home and they struck them.
Are those military objectives?
Where is the UN?
No one says anything.
Aren't they human too?
They're killing children and women.
The whole world has to speak up.
It has to see and say something.
Have we become nothing but numbers?
Are people of numbers?
How is that possible?
We are devastated.
Our morale is low.
When you see your friends and neighbours
in pieces on the ground
and blood everywhere and the house destroyed,
our house was destroyed.
Where are we going to sleep?
Where do we go?
Zayna Hodder joins us live now from Beirut.
Zayna, you can hear there
in what these people are saying,
how concerning it is for them
that the civilian death toll in Lebanon
continues to climb ever higher.
What more can you tell us?
Well, civilians are increasingly being caught
in this conflict.
1,461 people have been killed
in this conflict,
which has now entered its sixth week
with more than 4,000 people injured yesterday
in an Israeli strike in Znech,
which is on the fringe of the Beirut Southern suburbs.
It was a densely populated area.
The apparent target was a Hezbollah military commander,
but three Sudanese nationals were killed
along with a 15-year-old child.
So even though the Israeli military
may call these targeted strikes,
pinpoint strikes when they go after
a certain individual member of Hezbollah,
at times civilians are killed.
There was another incident in Ain Saadi,
that's north of Beirut,
where three civilians were killed.
This is an area outside Hezbollah's influence,
a predominantly Christian neighborhood.
And those who were killed
are really not part of this conflict,
this ongoing conflict.
And it's raising and heightening tensions
in those regions
because people there are blaming Hezbollah
and Hezbollah supporters
for seeking shelter in those areas.
And then you have strikes in the south of the country,
for example, in the village of Tol,
in Nabati, where a father and a mother were killed,
and their 15-year-old and nine-year-old child were wounded.
And there have been several instances
where whole families are killed in a single strike.
So the civilian death toll is rising,
according to the statistics that are being provided
by the Lebanese Health Ministry,
because they don't really distinguish
between combatants and civilians,
but among the women, children,
and the paramedics who have been killed,
we are talking about roughly 25% of the casualty toll.
All right, Zaina, and while we have you,
let's talk about where Israel is
in terms of its ground invasion in southern Lebanon.
What are they saying right now about it?
Well, the Israeli military
is operating in southern Lebanon,
but in the past 24, 48 hours,
they haven't made any significant military gains
on the ground.
Yes, they have territorial control
of some areas along that border,
but territorial control does not mean operational control
because Hezbollah continues to fight back.
It is putting up resistance.
And then we heard from the Israeli chief of staff
on Sunday, where he said,
yes, Israel's ultimate goal is to disarm Hezbollah,
but the goal of the current campaign
is about advancing this goal.
He does not use the word achieve.
He uses the word advance.
And he also calls on the political leadership to play a part.
So this is the Israeli army saying that
even though they reach up until the Letani River,
the stated goal of this invasion,
it's not going to achieve Hezbollah's disarmament.
The Israeli military knows very well
that Hezbollah's strategic infrastructure
and strategic weapons
happens, is up in the Bekaa Valley, in the Baalbek area, that's in the east of the country.
So taking control of the south of Lytani is not going to stop rocket fire.
And Hezbollah is promising to put up a fight.
And yesterday, Hezbollah saying that the only way to bring calm to southern Lebanon
is for Israel to withdraw from that area, responding to the president, who again called
for negotiations, saying negotiations does not amount to surrender, which is a message to Hezbollah.
So no end in sight. The Israeli military's advance has been
slow, with Hezbollah putting up resistance.
And once again, as you were reporting, Zana civilians there caught in the crossfire.
Zana Hodor live for us in Beirut. Thank you.
At least two people have been killed by an Iranian strike in the city of Haifa,
according to the Fire and Rescue Service.
A residential building was hit and partially collapsed.
At least four others have been wounded.
Emergency teams are searching for two others missing in the rubble.
Nidda Ibrahim joins us now from Ramallah in the occupied West Bank.
Nidda, it wasn't just Haifa overnight.
There have been multiple attacks across Israel.
What can you tell us about them?
Not really. These attacks continue.
And just in the last few minutes, we heard thoughts here after interceptors of work
to stop an attack that was coming from Iran that was targeting southern Israel,
including areas in the Dead Sea.
This was considered the fifth salvo to be sent from Iran into Israel since midnight.
It focused more on the center of the country,
where Tel Aviv has been suffering from damage to the buildings.
No casualties, according to the Israeli Ambulance Service.
But two salvos, one of them hit the south and the other was targeting
northern Israel.
But in general, we are talking about these cluster munitions,
these fragmenting warheads that have caused damage in Tel Aviv,
according to the Israeli sources.
It seems that we are looking at an intensification of rockets,
maybe because there has been some attempt by the Israeli home front
to ease restrictions in certain areas that they say have suffered less and less attacks.
So they wanted to resume education.
This is something that we've seen happen before.
And when the Israeli home front eased restrictions,
the Iranians intensified attacks as a way to disrupt normal life in Israel
and continue to impose kind of pressure on the government
through keeping the population in their homes,
not being able to conduct their daily lives.
Although these people are trying to push back,
and we've seen yesterday how an Israeli court
tried to ease restrictions when it comes to worshipers
going to the western wall in Jerusalem.
Now this has been deemed by many here as a double standard.
Because how come the Palestinians who were celebrating Easter yesterday
were not able to get into the Holy Sepulchre Church?
The ceremony was only limited to 15 people,
while at the same time Israelis are being granted through the court
permissions to pray up to 100 people.
This is something that has been widely criticized here
as the country still faces these rocket attacks
and barrages from Iran at the same time,
sometimes coordinated attacks come from Hezbollah's side.
Nidda Ibrahim reporting live for us from Ramallah in the Occupied West Bank.
Thanks, Nidda.
The Iran War is piling pressure on Sri Lanka,
which is still recovering from an economic meltdown four years ago.
The government has just raised gas prices by 20 percent.
Petrol and diesel are being rationed,
and electricity costs are up 25 percent.
Those surging prices have left many Sri Lankans struggling to get by.
Manel Fernandez reports from Colombo.
Lassit Gayan has worked for a food delivery company in Colombo for four years.
The 39-year-old's income depends on the number of deliveries he makes.
But restrictions on fuel and price increases caused by the Iran War
have affected his earnings.
I make around $20 a day, but I have to buy all my meals.
That costs more than $5 a day.
I use what's left for fuel, rent, and to send home to my family.
Restaurants like this, where Gayan is picking up his first order for the day,
are also struggling.
Gas for cooking is more expensive.
And manager Suranga Thirunagama says
good quality ingredients are difficult to find.
This has forced many outlets to increase their prices.
Something Thirunagama says he's trying to avoid.
We're trying our best to manage without raising prices,
but it's getting more challenging day by day,
because today's prices are not the same tomorrow.
We can't budget. Prices are increasing.
And it's already evident.
Gayan says he's delivering fuel orders these days.
Many people we spoke to told us the worst part is the uncertainty.
On the way to his next pickup, Gayan fills up.
The government has imposed fuel restrictions.
Motorbike riders get a weekly quota of eight liters.
Half the fuel Gayan says he usually goes through.
Station owner Sampat Kotalavala is also dealing with uncertainty.
We only receive about 50% of the supplies we order.
And we manage these stocks according to the framework the government has given us.
It's not enough for some, but generally it's okay.
But that's for today. I can't say what tomorrow will be like.
There are other pressures too.
A long pending electricity price increase took effect this month,
with some bills set to go up by 25%.
The government has asked people to use power sparingly.
Ioning and washing clothes only once a week.
And government officers have been told to switch off air conditioners early.
Just as Sri Lanka is recovering from its worst economic crisis,
the Iran war is causing more uncertainty.
People are paying more for fuel, food and even public transport
as a conflict thousands of kilometers away since prices soaring.
On the road, Gayan has stopped for a cup of tea and a snack
that's costing him more now than it did two weeks ago.
But he must hurry because the next order is waiting.
Menel Fernandez, Al Jazeera, Colombo.
Let's take a look at some of the world's other news now.
In the Gaza Strip, Hamas says it will not hand over its weapons.
Disarmament is part of the second phase of the Gaza ceasefire plan.
But the armed group says calls to lay down its weapons are unacceptable.
Especially as Palestinians continue to be targeted by Israel.
More than 700 people have been killed since the ceasefire came into effect in October.
As for raising the issue of weapons in this crude manner,
it is nothing but a scandalous attempt by the occupation
to continue killing and genocide against our people,
which we will not accept under any circumstances.
We affirm that what the enemy was unable to seize from us
with tanks and genocide, it will not seize from us
with politics or at the negotiation table.
The occupation's aggression against our people
and its continued closure of the blessed Al Aqsa Mosque
to worshipers in an unprecedented manner
and the approval of the law for executing Palestinian prisoners,
we call upon the masses of our Palestinian people
in the brave West Bank, the blessed Jerusalem,
and the occupied interior to march toward Al Aqsa Mosque.
Mohin Rabani is a non-resident fellow at the Center for Conflict and Humanitarian Studies.
He said Hamas's statements confirms that talks to implement
the second phase of the Gaza ceasefire plan are deadlocked.
What Hamas informed the mediators is that it will not discuss issues
such as disarmament relating to the second phase of the plan for the Gaza Strip
until the items of the first phase are implemented.
That includes a cessation of hostilities.
As you noted, virtual daily Israeli attacks on the Gaza Strip
have resulted in more than 700 Palestinians killed.
Humanitarian aid continues to be restricted.
And most notably, this National Committee for the Administration of the Gaza Strip,
which was established by the Board of Peace,
continues to be prohibited from entering the Gaza Strip by the Israelis,
and the Board of Peace is doing absolutely nothing to ensure its ability to get in.
And so I think Hamas is taking two positions.
A, it won't discuss the second phase until the first phase is properly implemented.
And B, when those discussions do take place,
it's not going to simply surrender its weapons
unless Israel clearly meets its own obligations as well.
And those are obligations that have to be consistent,
not just with what the Board of Peace wants,
but with the international consensus and the rulings of the International Court of Justice
that this is an illegal occupation that must end.
One of China's leading arts universities has scrapped degrees
in subjects like translation and photography.
It says there are a waste of national resources in the age of artificial intelligence.
But the decision is fueling debate online about how far technology should reshape education.
Katrina Yew reports from Beijing.
Alex Scher built her career in the creative industries
after graduating with a degree in English translation and interpreting.
But qualifications like hers could soon disappear.
As some of China's biggest universities,
cut courses they say are being overtaken by artificial intelligence.
Alex says the move risks overlooking the broader skills behind translation
from communication to critical thinking.
When you translate for sure,
yes AI could probably get the accuracy up to almost close to perfection.
But there's still that personal style that's always been essential in translation
and when it comes to interpreting.
It's not just translation.
Degrees in photography, illustration and fashion design are also being scrapped
with universities saying the future lies in human machine cooperation.
The changes are part of a broader government push to steer students
towards industries it considers critical to the country's future
including robotics, semiconductors and artificial intelligence.
The pressure is growing.
More than 12 million students graduated in China last year,
a record number, and many are struggling to find jobs
highlighting a mismatch between skills and demand.
But AI is also creating new opportunities.
In the film and creative sectors, new roles are emerging
like prompt engineers and AI animators.
Before AI, it could take a month just to design characters or scenes.
Now we can complete an entire project in a month.
Universities are trying to adapt, launching new programs that combine creative training
with AI skills.
Alex says it's more important than ever for young people to diversify their skills.
She cites stand-up comedy among her own.
It's just the case that we're in this ever changing and ever changing faster time period
of human history and we just have to be ready.
It's just not those days anymore.
We can put our all of our eggs in one basket.
But she says one thing still matters, the human touch.
Katrina Yu, Al-Dazeera, Beijing.
Up next, Inside Story takes a look at how the war in Iran
is deepening the humanitarian crisis in Gaza.
I'll be back in about 30 minutes with our continued coverage of the war
between the U.S., Israel, and Iran.
Stay with us. We'll be back after a short break.
The conflict is arising because of Israel's insistence
on striking oil facilities inside Iran.
This is one of the oil facilities of the country that has been targeted.
You can see the puff of cloud.
Once those interceptors take out those missiles and rockets and drones.
Hezbollah rockets have reached this far into Israeli territory and Israel.
Consider this a serious escalation.
Lebanon's government is struggling to meet the demand for emergency shelter.
This stadium is being converted into a mini tent city.
Stay with Al-Dazeera for the latest developments.
On counting the cost, with higher oil prices and east sanctions,
Russia is hoping to gain from the conflict in the Middle East
and further its war aims in Ukraine.
But those plans are at risk from Ukrainian attacks.
So can Russia help fill the global energy gap,
or is its capacity already under threat?
Counting the cost on Al-Dazeera.
The war in Iran is deepening the humanitarian crisis in Gaza
in violation of the ceasefire.
Israel has severely restricted aid and maintained its airstrikes.
The US-brokered deal is meant to be in phase two,
but appears to be in limbo.
So who could step in to help Palestinians?
This is Inside Story.
Looking to the program, I'm Imran Khan.
It's called The Forgotten Crisis.
Humanitarian conditions in Gaza remain dire,
despite a US-brokered ceasefire that came into effect in October.
For months, the Israeli military violated the agreement,
carrying out airstrikes,
limiting the entry of aid and building materials.
But it got worse when Israel and the US
launched their joint offensive on Iran at the end of February.
The RAFA border crossing,
a lifeline in southern Gaza, was closed again.
In Israel, further restricted deliveries of food,
fuel and humanitarian aid.
With the war in Iran disrupting global supply chains
and the UN warning of threats to food security,
one of the implications for Palestinians in Gaza
will discuss that with our guests in just a moment.
But first, this report from Michael Apple.
An Israeli airstrike targets a vehicle killing everyone inside.
There's a war going on, but this isn't Iran.
It's what a ceasefire looks like to Palestinians in Gaza.
We feel that we are in a state of war
and that the war is still raging in the region.
We witness bombardments and assassinations all the time.
Even though we are in a ceasefire, we do not feel it.
Israel is among the estimated 1.7 million people
forced from their homes in the strip.
With some plastic and a lot of prayer,
she tries to keep the reign at bay.
Her hopes that there's an end in sight to the misery
is fraying, much like her tent.
The UN says some Palestinians are only getting half
of the calories needed to sustain life.
Israel maintains a stranglehold on the border crossings.
Many here say they feel forgotten by the world.
Before the Iran war, the same people who forgot about us then
just keep on forgetting about us now.
Food supplies have decreased and prices have gone up.
The landscape is apocalyptic.
It bears the scars of war.
But the human cost cannot be ignored.
Israeli attacks have killed nearly 73,000 Palestinians
since October 7th, 2023.
The vast majority of them women and children.
More than 172,000 people have been wounded,
many of them sustaining life-changing injuries.
Another 10,000 Palestinians are unaccounted for,
believed to be buried underneath the mountains of rubble.
Israel still controls nearly 60% of Gaza,
a so-called yellow line marking where its troops are meant to operate
came into effect with the ceasefire.
But it's regularly violated.
The killing hasn't stopped either.
More than 700 Palestinians have been killed
during the nearly six months of the ceasefire.
The UN estimates the Israeli military has dropped around
200,000 tons of munitions on Gaza.
And up to 12% of those bombs haven't detonated.
Specialized teams find them and mark them.
UXO, unexploded ordinance, a danger that will take decades to clear.
Palestinians are trapped in limbo, enduring a fragile ceasefire
while the humanitarian crisis deepens.
And much of the world's attention is focused elsewhere.
Michael Apple, El Jazeera, For Inside Story.
Now, before we talk to our guests,
let's talk to our correspondent in Gaza City, Hind Khudri.
Hind, you've been a correspondent for us now,
since almost the beginning of the war and throughout the ceasefire.
But I don't want to speak to you as a correspondent today.
I want to talk about your family, your friends.
I want to talk about Palestinians
and how they're still suffering despite this ceasefire.
Life's just not got any easier for you, right?
Well, Amidran, I remember talking to you the last time six months ago.
And we were very hopeful at that time.
For example, I was looking forward to see my family
as we have been separated since October 2023,
but still six months into the ceasefire.
And I still didn't see my mom or meet my brothers.
And I'm not the only case.
There are thousands of Palestinians
that are still waiting for freedom of movement.
It's not only that.
It's the continuous humanitarian situation
which is deteriorating every single day.
Amidran, I have been sick for the past week.
And I haven't been finding any medicine.
I have been going through pharmacies, going through hospitals.
And the Israeli authorities are not letting in any medical supplies
into the Gaza Strip.
And I'm talking about a normal flu and infection in the lungs.
There's no antibiotics.
There's no ventilating inhalers.
And this is the case and has been the case for the past six months.
There has been a lot of promises.
Most of Gaza's population is literally still living on the streets
in very fragile, torn out tents where shelter items are not entering.
And with the Iran war now, Palestinians feel more forgotten
because there has been no progress in the ceasefire deal
in the technocrat teams that were supposed to be coming into Gaza Strip.
More restrictions have been imposed on the Gaza Strip.
And let me tell you very basic stuff where eggs, for example,
are still a struggle for a lot of Palestinians.
Anything nutritious has been bound into the Gaza Strip.
And we all carry this amount of loss,
amount of homelessness,
the loneliness we're still feeling that, yes, there is ceasefire,
but we're still being killed every couple of days
where in the last couple of days
there has been a vehicle that has been targeted where three people...
were killed police officers have been also been a target by the Israeli authorities and also the
fact that there are thousands of Palestinians still trapped under the rubble where families
weren't even able to bury whatever is remained of their families. And that's the story during the
day but when the night falls and it gets colder and people are living in tents it just must be
even worse. I mean just what's it like being a child there?
Children Emron are still queuing up on food kitchens on water trucks because none of these
struggles have been solved. Also the fact that your mother is cuddling you because it's the only
source of warmth the fact that rain is another nightmare other than airstrikes and Emron believe
me we are still literally sleeping every single day on very loud drone sounds as drones did not
leave the sky of Gaza neither night or day and it is the ongoing trauma of this sound where
we used to hear it and we expected an airstrike over and over again most of Gaza's children are
still deprived from medicine they're still deprived from education and also let me tell
you that there are thousands of children that were the only survivors and they're living without
parents without family members and children every child in Gaza carries a different story of struggle
and all of these stories are heartbreaking. I mean hon I really hope you get some medicine soon
because I can hear it in your voice thank you for bringing us up to date for what it's like for
people just living in Gaza. Let's now bring in our guests from southern Lebanon we're joined by Dr
Mohammed Tahir a war surgeon who has worked extensively in Gaza he's also the CEO of Al-Risala
Foundation Alex Dual is in Boston Massachusetts he's the executive director of the World
Peace Foundation and specializes in famine and in Ramallah Javier Abouid he's a political
analyst and former communications director for the Palestine Liberation Organization a warm welcome
to you all I want to start with Dr Mohammed in southern Lebanon you just heard our correspondent
there Hind Khaldri talking about the fact that you can't even get cold and flu tablets over the
counter medications in Gaza if you can't get that and there's been a war on the medical sector
this I mean there's just no medicines in Gaza now how does that make you feel given that you
worked in that sector? Yes thank you first of all for having me look what we know about the Israeli
regime is that the killing never stops and the suffering never stops it just transitions
from phase to phase sometimes the killing has accelerated the suffering is ever more and then
when they turn direction to another part of the world and they you know bring about suffering
there they slow the suffering elsewhere and that's simply because they don't have the bandwidth to
bring about so much suffering across the world in at the same intensity now Gaza of course when I
was there it was a killing it was a killing field it was an abattoir and actually now that I'm
based in Lebanon I can tell you that I'm in a war here today in Lebanon but there was something
completely different that was an outright genocide and the suffering is unimaginable I
oftentimes think back to what we saw and it's unthinkable that this was ever allowed to happen
today in Gaza I was talking to my colleagues in fact yesterday they have no building material to
re-establish hospitals they have no access to materials to do interventional procedures
they're lacking in oncologists they're lacking in pulmonologists they're lacking in endoscopists
they're lacking in the plastic surgeons and of course you know you heard simple medicines not
being available bringing about the suffering for the average person on day to day but the most
vulnerable are also at most risk and you see every day people dying in front of our screens
and pleads going up to the world for evacuation evacuations come to a halt as well so the
suffering is really something that cannot be imagined. Javier I'm going to bring you
in in just a second because I want to talk to you about all the politics of this but
on the humanitarian front I want to start with Alex. Alex this is a famine that's unfolding
in front of our eyes on our cameras but is not getting any attention. Regrettably tragically
appallingly so so exactly a year ago a year before the operation that President Trump and
Benjamin Netanyahu unleashed on Iran there was the complete siege on Gaza and that
siege was tighter than the siege today but the condition of the people entering into those
siege conditions today is as we've just been hearing utterly deplorable these are people
already at the brink so deprived of so many of the essentials needed to sustain
life living in the most miserable conditions really ground down by two and a half years
and so what we I fear we will be seeing is a descent into famine conditions
comparable to what we saw at the same time last year with the difference that last year there was
international intention and outcry which mounted over the months and eventually by September
October pushed the United States to recognize what was happening and pushed Israel to towards
opening the border crossings and so on and I don't see any of that pressure now as we've
been hearing this is this is a crisis forgotten ignored by the world well let's talk about that
pressure Javier I don't need to ask you about the suffering the Palestinians you live it every
single day but there is a board of peace there is you know a ceasefire there's supposed to
be a negotiation going on this is not supposed to be happening phase two is supposed to be happening
that all seems to have disappeared am I right in thinking that certainly and running things from
having me here first of all the board of peace it's unleashing its kind of attempt to set an
alternative to the UN by President Donald Trump his administration the person they have in charge
of the Gaza reconstruction Mr. Mladenov is a former UN envoy here he doesn't have words when Palestinians
are killed on a daily basis in Gaza know when there is a very limited access to water cooking
gas and other important elements so clearly what we are facing and we're not only in Gaza but
also in the occupied West Bank is how the Israeli plans that talk about openly now about
ethnic cleansing about annexation are coming out without any sort of significant international
response and let's be very clear this is not only about the Trump administration we're facing terror
attacks by Israeli settlers on a daily basis here in the occupied West Bank the European Union
response seems to be something like calling for more reforms within the Palestinian
Authority and support and this is a way of getting closer to a state that is appearing
on the ground because of the culture of impunity that Israel continues to enjoy so it's a situation
of overall crisis I would define I mean have you I just want to follow up on that because
1500 Palestinians have been killed in the occupied West Bank since October the 7th 2023
that's more than that were killed on October the 7th 2023 right that day that actually
unleashed hell on Gaza if Gaza was the war that everybody concentrated on it's a forgotten war
in the occupied West Bank raids are going on every single day I've been there I've seen them
you know I've been at the end of them so you know why do you think the occupied West Bank is
the forgotten part of this war do you think it may be emblem perhaps because here there is no
armed resistance against Israeli occupation and it seems an international community and
particularly Western powers only tend to care about what's happening in Palestine when there are
Israelis that are being affected by Palestinian resistance and that's extremely unfortunate
because it sends a very wrong message just over the month of March we have over 200 Israeli
settler terror attacks against Palestinians not counting the actions of the Israeli
occupation forces not a single Israeli settler has been arrested or prosecuted
for those attacks but in return we have six Palestinians killed by those Israeli settlers
we have dozens it's not hundreds of settler militias armed by the Israeli government and
Israel in general they are not really facing consequences or meaningful consequences for
their actions so clearly what we are facing here in the occupied West Bank is extremely
dramatic why because here also it's a priority of of Israel here is where they have over 200
settlements 700 000 settlers and the the campaign to annex more and more Palestinian land
Alex I'm going to come to you now the board of peace was set up to get to a place where they could
get food aid everything into the Gaza Strip and look for long-term solution but there was
an organization in place that could do that that had all of the knowledge and the infrastructure
that was the United Nations it was the United Nations relief works agency the refugee agency
of the Palestinians Israel completely sidelined it so the Gaza board of peace is a failure do you
think I think you've really answered your your question in the way that you've framed it and
I think that's absolutely correct there was a workable infrastructure that could deliver
the essentials with the professional proficiency the reach the partnership the experience and above
all the humanity the fact that UNRWA and another international organization is present on the
ground in in in Gaza also in the West Bank have those routes those contacts with the community
means that they can respond with the sense of compassion with the the sense of of humanity
to the people and their real needs albeit with very limited resources under extreme duress and
what we have with the board of peace is essentially a vacuum the the we have plans for more
militarized forms of ration provision we have plans for building a sort of Riviera this is a
a performance populist piece combined with a claptocratic peace for profit formula it is
throwing away everything that we know has worked and everything that is founded on
the the basic principles of the of the charter of of the united nations and international law
Mohammed doctors like you have been barred from going back into Gaza you yourself as I
understand it are not allowed to go back in to Gaza Israeli is restricting even volunteers
getting in the border pieces clearly as we've heard isn't really doing the things it's supposed
to be doing you a shirt you are nodding your head in agreement there when they were talking
about the fact that there was a mechanism that allowed people like you in and that's been destroyed
just talk us about the effect on the medical professionals like you when you can't get in
to help absolutely right look my colleagues in Gaza are phenomenal doctors physicians nurses and
so on they've just been constrained by the environment imposed upon them by the Israeli regime
in that they're not allowed for example to go outside for fellowship training
pickup skills that otherwise other surgeons would be would have access to and in addition to that
of course they have a limitation on on technology and health care and so on and so
although they're talented surgeons there are certain areas were certain you know
areas of expertise that are missing there and they are reliant upon colleagues from the outside
coming in and not only performing surgeries there but also trying to fill the gap in the training
that they've been denied and as a result lots of people simply don't have access to the usual
sort of health care people around the world in addition to that you have to remember you're
dealing with the most complex and severe injuries on the face of this earth and I'm telling you this
first hand because I was involved in the medical evacuation program where we took out the most
complex cases to neighboring countries and we tried and we were treating them there and that
involved a multidisciplinary team from from the from the globe to arrive at you know at
decisions in the patient's best interest and so within when they deny us they're basically
not only cutting off a lifeline to the doctors there in terms of training they're denying patients
you know they're right you know innocent people they're right to health care and this is of course
all orchestrated it's a it's a strangulation process they don't want the people to be there
anymore this is a you know a you know we are on a phase of genocide and of course they're
not going to allow people like me me coming on the show for example means that I don't have
access to residents anymore anyone who's outspoken anyone who describes the suffering they ban you
Alex how much of what you've just heard Dr. Maui talk about constitutes a war crime
I it's it's worse than a war crime I mean this is you know this is the the crime
that go it's a crime of extermination it's a crime of genocide but it's something more it's
a it's a crime against humanity in the most profound sense that it is trying to kill
the humanity of a people and and the sense of trauma that these people who have
survived this will have for the rest of their lives that the extent to which the basic social
fabric that makes us more than simple animals has been destroyed is is deeply profound and
let me just add one sort of detail to this which is that when we think of the number of
people who are suffering from physical and mental disabilities as a result of this just
the number of child amputees is a very very straightforward visible tangible example how
are these young children going to be able to become food secure themselves how are they going
to have livelihoods how are they going to earn money how are they going to be able to
provide for families in in future the level of vulnerability to to to destitution to food
insecurity to hunger is so much higher as a result of this onslaught have one of the words
that's always used for the Palestinians whether it's in the occupied west bank whether it's in
Gaza whether it's abroad is resilience we are the Palestinians we are used to this
we will you know resist in our own little ways and there is a certain amount of that
that is true but i'm speaking to people now and everybody is getting much more and more
frustrated at this idea that the world's ignoring us because we've been through
since 1948 so everybody's just used to it you've got to how would you kind of combat that
if you were speaking to somebody for them say the UN who was like you know maybe we should
give them some money but maybe not they've been going through this for far too long
and i think we should not romanticize resilience we should be very proud of Palestinian resilience
since 1948 however this is not how a people should be living we are in a constant state of
struggling i mean today people are celebrating Easter to give an example and even in order
to get to a church people have to actually fight for the right even praying has become
an act of resistance and the Israeli occupation or to talk of course about al-Aqsa most being
close during most of the holy month of Ramadan so in other words when we talk about Palestinian
resilience i think it involves all aspects of Palestinian life but people should not get
used to it people should get to act in order for Palestinians to be able to enjoy the
rights and here i think Imran what's what's extremely important is as we've been talking
in this program is to make clear that what's happening with Palestinians it's not just a
situation between Israel and Palestine but it has an international responsibility element
that's not being met as we speak Alex one of the things about attention global attention when
it comes to a particular genocide like Gaza is that you get money donor step forward it's a
thing that pushes it that publicity almost pushes somebody to do something but when the spotlight
disappears that money also disappears right that's correct and and we have the the the
one two terrible punch not only is that the the the the publicity vanishing and therefore the
public funding but but also aid budgets are being cut and not just in the United States i mean
the the United Kingdom is now giving a lower proportion of its GDP per capita as international
aid than at any time in the last 60 years and that is absolutely shocking the the funds for this
are are drying up and and people are being left on their own and however resilient however
steadfast they are there comes a point at which human life simply cannot be sustained under
this pressure i want to thank our guests alex the wall have you able to eat and dr. mohammed
to here and thank you too for watching you can see the program again anytime by visiting our
website aljazeera.com and for further discussion go to our facebook page that's facebook.com
forward slash aj inside story and you can also join the conversation on x our handle
is at aj inside story that's it from me imran khan and the team here in doha stay with us
for more coverage of the war between the u.s israel and iran coming up in just a moment
Sprawling across 2,600 hectares, the Dangotiri finery was built to help end Nigeria's reliance on imported fuel.
But today, this 650,000 barrel per day giant is being asked to do much more.
Shipping disruptions caused by the war in Iran have throttled nearly a fifth of the world's energy flow.
With Middle Eastern supplies diverted or delayed, Africa is feeling the squeeze and looking for a lifeline closer to home.
The Dangotiri finery here in Leki has become a vital strategic shield for Nigeria and many other countries.
The 650,000 barrel per day facility provides steady supply of fuel as international markets grapple with depleted inventories.
Low domestic crude production means the refinery is often starved of the very oil setting beneath Nigerian soil,
forcing the plant to look abroad for raw materials.
The race is on to see if African production can outrun a global energy crisis.
Americans, they don't have any clear image and plan of what to do.
The logic behind this is to eliminate the nuclear weapons program, to eliminate Iran's support for terrorism.
The Israelis do not want to have opening of political talks between Tehran and Trump.
Stay with Al Jazeera for the latest developments.
That would precipitate an attack against American forces to prevent Iran from getting milked.
There is no coherent strategy and you can see that's reflected in the media coverage.
Many American media see like a video game, from the graphics on the screen to who they speak to, war for them is big business.
We saw this exact same pattern happen in Gaza, the same lazy flattened reporting that we saw in Gaza when it comes to the war on Iran.
The listening post decodes the media on Al Jazeera.
Hello, this is Al Jazeera live from Doha with our continuing coverage of the war between the US, Israel and Iran.
I'm Riley Carlson, here's what's coming up.
Overnight US and Israeli strikes on Iran kill at least 34 people.
Civilian infrastructure, including atop university is among the targets.
More Iranian attacks target Israeli cities.
Two bodies have been recovered from the rubble of a destroyed apartment building in Haifa.
Israel also carries out attacks across Lebanon, targeting a residential building in the capital where at least three people are killed.
Donald Trump sets a Tuesday deadline for Iran to reopen the Strait of Hormuz,
or the US will bomb its power plants and bridges and quote, Unleash Hell.
Thank you for joining us.
The US and Israel have stepped up their attacks on Iran.
A deadline set by President Donald Trump is nearing.
He's demanding that Iran reopen the Strait of Hormuz.
Tehran maintains that the waterway is open to everyone except its enemies.
At least 34 people have been killed in Iran in overnight strikes by the US and Israel.
Several areas have been targeted, including a university in Tehran and an airport in the Southwest.
Iran says more than 2,000 people have been killed since the war began.
Meanwhile, Iran has continued its retaliatory strikes, sending missiles across Israel.
At least two people have been killed in the northern city of Haifa,
and there's been extensive damage in and around Tel Aviv.
US President Donald Trump has renewed threats to destroy Iranian power plants and bridges
if it doesn't reopen the Strait of Hormuz by Tuesday at 8pm Eastern time.
We are live in Ramallah in the occupied West Bank, Kuwait City, Beirut, and in Tehran.
And that is where we'll begin with Tauheed Assadi.
Tauheed, what can you tell us about these attacks that took place overnight and into the morning?
There were more than a dozen cities in Tehran that were hit.
Yes, indeed. Tehran, the capital of the country, witnessed another night of heavy bombardment,
which different areas located in the east, north, south, as well as the western areas of the capital were targeted.
And different places including infrastructural facilities have been impacted,
some of them even directly hit, including Sharif University of Technology,
which is known as Iran's MIT, one of the most, or perhaps I can say,
the most important technical university of the country.
The president of the country came out to confirm the attack and the footages coming out
indicate a huge amount of damage to different buildings, including the mosque
and other facilities, laboratories, and other places.
Of this important university also, we know that the area has been the witness of other attacks.
Actually, a gas facility is said to be targeted as well in the area
as adjacent to the campus of Sharif University of Technology.
And of course, we know that beyond the capital, we have a relatively long list of different cities
experiencing the ongoing nature of the American and Israeli airstrikes, including Karaj, Shiraz, Esfahan, Boucher,
Bandar-e-Lenge, where at least six people are said to be killed,
or at least five people and in Baharistan, a very small city located in the vicinity of the capital.
There's local authorities are saying that at least 13 people have been killed, including six children.
And obviously, infrastructurally speaking, the country is also experiencing ongoing attacks on different places,
including power-related infrastructure, roads as bridges, and other facilities that are critically important for ordinary citizens.
And, Toheed, what is Iran saying about these types of attacks?
This isn't the first university that's been hit in Iran.
And as well, we've seen attacks on bridges and power structures, as you say.
What is Iran saying about these types of attacks?
The day before yesterday, we had the chance to talk to Iran's Ministry of Science, Research, and Technology,
and he told us that at least 30 universities so far have been hit as a result of these airstrikes.
The latest was Shahid Bihesti University in the campus at which we were to witness
that the laser and plasma research institute was targeted heavily, heavily damaged,
and the dormitories located in the campus were also impacted, some of them in a very, I would say, huge way.
The good news was that the students were out for Noruz holidays, so no casualties.
But the latest is actually, and of course, prior to that, we also had reports about the heavy bombardments
of the Iran's University of Science and Technology located in the eastern areas of the capital.
And prior to that, we had the Isfahan University of Technology being targeted.
But the latest, as I was explaining, is Sharif University of Technology.
And the Iranian side is just considering it as a war crime,
and the Foreign Ministry's spokesperson came out the other day to call it an assault, a systematic crime,
a systematic attack on the academic and cultural foundations of the country,
condemning these attacks that are right now, I would say, getting broader when it comes to their scope.
You know, at the very first days of these airstrikes, it was states-related buildings,
or mostly, I would say, military headquarters or military-related infrastructure.
But over the past two weeks, I can say we see a severe damage to infrastructures, hospitals, schools,
red crescent buildings, transportation-related facilities, and that is obviously the heavy cost
that the very ordinary citizens living in the country are going to be, are going to indeed pay.
Right. And, Toheed, there's also been significant concern over the past month or so,
as you say, about strikes that have happened on or around the Bashar nuclear power plant
for strikes, from what we can tell so far.
What is Iran saying about the concerns that they have about that area being targeted?
It is not that one, but we know that when it comes to nuclear facilities of the country,
starting from earlier, much earlier, in June, when the Americans and Israelis
started a campaign of airstrikes, three of the most important facilities,
Natanz, Fordo, and Isfahan, were targeted.
And moving on in this war, we also witnessed, actually, nuclear-related facilities of the country
being some of them directly, some of them indirectly hit.
And about this recent one, we know that the areas in the vicinity have been
witnessed, the airstrikes by the Americans and Israelis.
The Iranian side has raised concerns about that.
And we've got this statement a couple of hours ago from the Iran's Atomic Energy Organization.
They came out to give a detailed account of the areas targeted, and they said,
quote-unquote, heavy water and its derivatives are vital for medicine, disease treatment,
and advanced industries.
U.S.-Israeli attack on Iran's heavy water facility is a crime against science and humanity health.
Our scientific progress will not be halted, nor will our resolve to serve global peace and health.
This is the very latest reaction that we had from the Iranian side.
Meanwhile, they are condemning, and also we know that diplomatically speaking Iran's previously,
actually, UN mission to New York Day to the United Nations,
they just wrote a letter to express their actually condemnation,
and they have asked for immediate action from the international community in that regard,
seeing the risk of contamination and other related risks that are out there
when it comes to attacking nuclear facilities.
Toheed Asadi reporting live for us from Tehran.
Thank you, Toheed.
At least two people have been killed in an Iranian strike on a building in the city of Haifa
according to Israeli media.
The residential structure partially collapsed after the attack on Sunday.
At least four other people were wounded.
Neda Ibrahim is following developments in Israel for us from Ramallah in the occupied West Bank.
Neda, there were multiple attacks actually in Israel overnight, not just in Haifa.
What can you tell us about those?
All these attacks continued, and we were reporting from here when we heard
loud thuds as a result of a continued Iranian missile fire being targeted.
This time the target was southern Israel, but at the same time,
we are talking about an intensification of these missiles from Iran in the past 24 hours.
That has kept people going to shelters, going to fortified areas,
and that increased fears because we are talking about Haifa,
a very important and strategic city, a portal city that has been hit several times,
but the last attack that took place late yesterday included the rocket or the missile was not intercepted.
That has caused a lot of panic because according to Israeli media,
the missile that was not intercepted had a fragmenting warhead,
but they say it was a coincidence, or they don't know if it was a technical failure,
that the warhead itself did not detonate and splinter in so many areas that kind of minimized the damage,
but the damage is still huge.
We are talking about these two killed, but also two others who are missing.
Their belief to be in a critical condition under the rubble as search and rescue continues in the city of Haifa.
When we talk about the rest of the attacks, they've also been targeting the central area,
including Tel Aviv, Beit Hahtiqva, these areas that have seen their share of attacks in the past few weeks.
Nidda Ibrahim reporting live from Ramallah in the occupied West Bank.
Thanks, Nidda.
The threat of escalation in Iran has put the Gulf region squarely in the crossfire.
In the United Arab Emirates' capital, one person was injured after debris from an intercepted missile fell in an industrial area.
Saudi's Defense Ministry says two drones have been intercepted and destroyed in the past few hours.
Malik Traina is live with us from Kuwait City following all of these developments for us.
Malik, I want to begin with the U.S. president's threats of this looming deadline to escalate attacks on bridges and power plant infrastructure.
How concerning is this for the Gulf countries?
I think extremely concerning to save the lease, because what we've consistently seen is that whenever the U.S. and the Israelis strike facilities,
especially civilian infrastructure in Iran, Iran immediately retaliates here in the Gulf.
I mean, yesterday is just a prime example, right?
So two days ago, I believe our teams in Iran said that a petrochemical company was targeted in Iran.
Yesterday, we saw the Al-Barouj petrochemical company in the UAE being targeted.
Fires erupted there after debris from an interception resulted in damage.
And also here in Kuwait, we saw yesterday a petrochemical company being hit.
You know, when that bridge was targeted in Iran, Iranian media immediately published a list of 10 bridges across the region.
Nine of those bridges were here in the Gulf, including the Sheikh Jabal Khazway.
That's one of the longest maritime bridges in the world.
It cost officials here more than $3.5 billion to build.
So, you know, just yesterday, we also saw a power station, a power and water station being hit here.
So it's extremely worrying for the Gulf about these attacks.
I think the immediate, what immediately the Gulf officials want to do is try to extend this deadline.
We saw this about 10 days ago when that two-day deadline was looming.
And then President Trump said that, you know, Iranians are negotiating.
Just yesterday, we saw the Omanians saying that they're in talks with the Iranians.
I think what officials will try to do now is say, look, you know,
the Iranians are talking to the Omanians.
Maybe there's, you know, there can be fruitful solutions.
They can come up with some kind of deal that will appease President Donald Trump.
And, you know, we can de-escalate the situation as soon as possible.
We'll see if they can do that before the deadline.
Malik, Saudi Arabia and the UAE have also reported overnight strikes into Monday.
What can you tell us about those?
Yeah, that's right.
So in the UAE, a telecommunications company,
authorities said that they were responding to an incident
at a telecommunications company in Fujairah.
Just a little bit before that, we heard about an incident
in the industrial city of Abu Dhabi, Saudi Arabia, within the last hour,
saying that it intercepted two drones.
And this morning here in Kuwait, numerous alarms were sounded.
You know, it just goes to show that these retaliation attacks,
you know, the Gulf has bared the brunt.
More than 6,000 ballistic missiles and drones have targeted the Gulf
since this war has started.
And I think here in Kuwait, you know, they're the closest country to Iran.
Just 80 kilometers of water is what separates these two countries.
So, you know, especially here, I think, you know,
they're increasingly concerned of any escalation that will happen.
Malik Trena, live for us in Kuwait City. Malik, thank you.
Israel has carried out multiple strikes across southern Lebanon
and the capital, Beirut, causing widespread damage and death.
At least four people were killed in a drone strike
targeting a car in the Nabataea district in the south.
In a separate attack in the same area, one person was killed.
Overnight, the Israeli military targeted an apartment east of Beirut,
killing at least three people.
In the southern suburbs, strikes on a densely populated area
killed five people on Sunday.
Israeli attacks across Lebanon have killed more than 1,300 people
according to the country's health ministry.
They hit a completely civilian area.
It's mostly migrants here, Sudanese people.
People were at home and they struck them.
Are those military objectives? Where is the UN? No one says anything.
Aren't they human, too? They're killing children and women.
The whole world has to speak up. It has to see and say something.
Have we become nothing but numbers, a people of numbers?
How is that possible?
We are devastated. Our morale is low.
When you see your friends and neighbours in pieces on the ground
and blood everywhere and the house destroyed, our house was destroyed.
Where are we going to sleep? Where do we go?
Zehna Hodor is live for us now in Beirut.
Zehna, you can hear in those people's voices just how concerned they are
about these strikes in civilian areas.
The population is on the move. Hundreds of thousands of people
have been displaced from their homes
and now many of them are seeing these strikes happen in their neighbourhoods.
How frightened are people?
People are afraid as civilians become increasingly caught up in this conflict.
Israeli strikes have been and continue to be.
relentless in the past hour or so. You mentioned that strike in Faro Man, a car was hit, four
people were killed nearby. There was another strike, another person killed in the east of the
country in Mashkara. Three people killed. And these strikes are happening constantly.
The latest figure provided by Lebanon's health ministry is 1,461 people killed and more than
4,000 wounded. Now, while the Lebanese health ministry does not distinguish between
combatants and civilians, what we know from the numbers of children killed, women and paramedics,
that's at least 25% of the casualty toll. Yesterday in Beirut, an apartment was targeted
in Ain Saadi. This is outside Hezbollah's area of influence. It was empty, but people who were
underneath that apartment on the second floor were killed. Three people killed. Also yesterday,
a densely populated area in Shnech. That's a district close to Beirut's southern suburbs,
just on the fringe of Beirut's southern suburbs. Five people were killed. Three Sudanese
nationals, a 15-year-old child. And the apparent target was a Hezbollah military commander. So
people are concerned. There is no front line in this conflict, whether it's Beirut,
south Lebanon, east Lebanon, with these strikes continuing unabated.
Zayna, let's talk about southern Lebanon, where, of course, the Israeli ground invasion
is underway. What are they saying, the Israelis, about what's happening there,
and how their objectives are being achieved? Well, in the past 24, 48 hours, Israeli
military's objectives appears to be to surround the town of Bintish Bay, a very strategic ground
in the central sector of southern Lebanon. They're trying to cut the supply lines to
the town and besiege it. It still has not happened. Really, in the past few days,
the advance has slowed. This invasion, the declared aim of reaching the Litani River,
it has slowed simply because Hezbollah is fighting back, and they're putting up fierce
resistance. And now we're hearing from Israel's chief of staff saying that while the ultimate
goal of Israel is the disarmament of Hezbollah, the goal of the current campaign is to advance
that goal. He's not even using the word achieve, but advance. And he's also saying that more needs
to be done by the political leadership. So this is the army chief acknowledging that even if they
reach the Litani River and control this occupation and set up this occupation zone in the south of
the country, this is not going to disarm Hezbollah. Hezbollah's strategic weapons,
its military infrastructure, its precision-guided missiles, they're in the east of the country
in Baalbek in the Bekaa area. And the Israelis know that very well. So it's not enough to take
control of the Litani River. And, you know, we're hearing more statements like this in the Israeli
army even saying that over the past three, four days, 66 soldiers were wounded, which really
is an acknowledgement that they are engaging in combat with Hezbollah in the south of the
country. Zena Hodder reporting live for us from Beirut. Thank you, Zena. Israel's forced
evacuation orders have displaced hundreds of thousands in southern Lebanon.
Taya resident Jamal Salim Farhan says he won't leave his home despite repeated Israeli bombings.
I'm joined now by Mohamed El-Masri, a professor of media studies at the Doha Institute for Graduate
Studies. Thanks for being with us, Mohamed. I want to start with this threat, this latest post by the
U.S. president giving this deadline of Tuesday at 8 p.m. What do you make of this? It seems as though
the president may be getting frustrated, at least publicly, with the lack of negotiation that's
happening. Is that what you read into it? Yeah, that's actually one of the first words that
came to my mind when I saw his post yesterday. It's clear that he's becoming frustrated.
The war has not gone according to plan. I think he was promised by Benjamin Netanyahu
and Pete Hegseth and Lindsey Graham and a couple of others, perhaps Jared Kushner,
that this would be a quick decapitation and regime change, that the regime or the counter
protesters had been sort of ripened for a regime change. And it hasn't gone that way.
And he's been frustrated, I think, ever since as he climbs this escalation ladder.
And on the Strait of Hormuz, you can clearly see his frustration. He said about 10 days ago or so
that Strait of Hormuz is no big deal. It's not important for the U.S. Somebody else should
handle it. Later he said it would be easy to retake the Strait of Hormuz. And now he's issuing
this very serious threat of escalation. It seems like he's putting much more emphasis on the need
to get the Strait of Hormuz open. We've seen the word war crime used a lot in these threats
from the president to hit power plants, to hit bridges, to hit civilian infrastructure.
The highest ranking Democrat in the House, Jim McGovern, posted on Excel, just read this to what
he said. He said, when the U.S. degrades international humanitarian law, we invite others
to do the same. That makes us all less safe. Is that a concern when it comes to the repercussions
of what is happening on the battlefield right now? No question about it.
You know, this kind of behavior was normalized in Israel. Israel was targeting civilians
and civilian infrastructure for two years nonstop. And the international community
just kind of shrugged. And the U.S. was obviously providing support. The difference here is that
the U.S. is participating directly with the Israelis targeting civilian infrastructure.
They hit this university last night, but they also hit a couple of universities last week.
They've hit hundreds of hospitals and health facilities, thousands of residential homes.
They're using 2,000-pound bombs to take out entire city blocks. They've hit tens of schools,
pharmaceutical plants, steel plants. I could go on. So it's very, very dangerous. There was
a letter signed the other day by a hundred academics from the top universities, Stanford,
Yale, Harvard, warning about war crimes. And the concern that you're talking about,
that this could sort of become normalized, is a very real one, I think.
And I asked that question because we're not just talking about it in Gaza. We're not just
talking about it in Iran. We've been talking about it in Ukraine. We've been talking about it in
Sudan. Are these instances really happening at a more expedited rate? Or does it just feel
like we are? How do we get a grip of how much these violations are happening in these
conflicts that are happening around the world? Well, war crimes are a sad reality of violent
conflicts. We've seen that really throughout modern history. But I think the Gaza moment
was a really, really important one because it's very rare. I can't think of a time when a government
telegraphed their war crimes so blatantly and brazenly, boasted about them,
and then did them on live stream. I think that was so tragic in many ways about Gaza,
is that the Israelis were live streaming the genocide there, and the international community
just kind of shrugged. In the case of Russia, you're right, Russia has committed war crimes
in Ukraine, but there's been a kind of a double standard because the response by
Western leaders, including the United States, has been very condemnatory. They've condemned
those Russian attacks, those Russian war crimes, and they've been very quick to do that.
They've been unambiguous. But when it comes to the Israeli crimes, obviously the American crimes,
they're much less likely to do that. What does condemning do? What good is that to combat the
war crime? Well, it's a start. You're right. I mean, look, that's a fair kind of pushback.
I ask because it goes to the normalization, right? It goes to some things being condemned,
some things not, as you say. Yeah. Well, I think you're also getting at a larger question about
the international system, which has been undermined. You have the US and Israel working systematically
to undermine the rules-based order for quite some time, and I think, unfortunately, they've
been successful. And so there are a lot of folks who have lost hope that individual people
will be held accountable, and that states will be held accountable for the crimes that they
commit. It's a dangerous moment for sure, and we keep sort of passing new thresholds.
And it is absolutely making everybody less safe. We see that now with this threat because
it's not just a threat against Iran, right? It would, of course, be disastrous for Iran and
the Iranian people if Trump follows through on this threat. But Iran has promised that the
entire region would go dark. So this would be dangerous for a lot of people.
And this will be very concerning for members of the GCC, which have been bearing sort of the
brunt of these retaliatory attacks, and are now wondering which of their power plants,
which of their bridges may be in the crosshairs if this goes forward.
That's absolutely right. And it's also becoming more dangerous for Gulf countries
because there is some, and I would be remiss if I didn't point this out,
there is some evidence that there have been some attacks launched from some
Gulf countries. France 24 did an investigation that they put out yesterday showing that there
have been a couple of attacks at least just in the past 10 days or so originating in Kuwait,
which might explain why the Iranians have been going so hard at Kuwait in these recent weeks.
So absolutely it's dangerous for the entire, for the entire region, really.
When it comes to these threats from the US president, is it time perhaps for a different
strategy? Because it doesn't seem like Iran is taking the bait, at least from the outside,
for people looking in. The president seems to be thinking that he can sort of strongarm them
into moving forward with opening the Strait of Hormuz, going to negotiations,
and Iran for whatever reason publicly says we're not going to play that game.
So where does the strategy shift or does it?
I mean, I mean, honestly, I would say that strategy is too generous of a word. I think this
this administration got into this war very haphazardly. I tried to explain it a moment ago.
I think they were pushed into this war by Benjamin Netanyahu and a pro-Israel cohort
inside the United States. I do think that Trump was convinced that this would be a very easy
regime change operation. The US had been on the ground. They've boasted about the fact that they
provided the opposition with guns. This was just reported yesterday in Fox News. Trump told Fox
News that he was boasting about that. The Mossad was on the ground according to Mike Pompeo and
a variety of Israeli media reports. And so they had all of their eggs in that basket.
And once that didn't happen, they've been trying to catch up ever since. And they've been trying
to get a hold on the narrative. And it's kind of gotten out of control. And I think Trump is
just trying to react as we continue to climb this escalation ladder. It's been a miscalculation.
He doesn't understand Iranian society. He doesn't understand the amount of support
that does exist for the current government in Iran. And he doesn't understand how deeply
entrenched the regime is there. They have a deep bench. And so killing five or ten or even a
couple of dozen leaders is not going to have the effect that Trump thinks it does. And so
to your point, yeah, someone needs to get in Donald Trump's ear and tell him that
even though it might look like a defeat, the wisest thing right now would be to take the
first off ramp. Mohamed El-Masri from the Doha Institute for Graduate Studies,
thank you for being with us. Thanks. You're watching Al Jazeera and our continuing
coverage of the war between the U.S., Israel and Iran. Here are the latest developments this hour.
At least 34 people have been killed in Iran in overnight strikes by the U.S. and Israel.
President Trump has set a Tuesday deadline for Iran to reopen the Strait of Formuz or the U.S.
will quote, unleash hell. Iran has continued to send missiles towards Israel. According to
Israeli media, at least two people have been killed in the northern city of Haifa.
There's also been extensive damage in and around Tel Aviv. Israel has carried out multiple
strikes across southern Lebanon and the capital Beirut, causing widespread damage and death.
Overnight, the Israeli military targeted an apartment east of Beirut, killing at least
three people. U.S. President Donald Trump has been giving Iran shifting deadlines to reopen
the Strait of Formuz. That's as Iran insists the key waterway isn't actually closed and that
the only ships that belong to its enemies are the ones being barred from passage.
Trump issued his first ultimatum on March 21st. He threatened to bomb Iran's power plants if the
Strait wasn't reopened within 48 hours. He later extended that deadline by five days,
claiming that negotiations were underway. Trump issued a new deadline on March 26th.
He gave Iran 10 days or until the evening of April 6th to reopen the Strait.
Trump issued his latest Hormuz threat on Sunday. After vowing to bomb power plants
and bridges if Tehran doesn't comply, he posted what appears to be a Tuesday
8 p.m. eastern time deadline for the deal. Al Jazeera's Mike Hannah has more on the
president's comments from Washington, D.C. The unusual use of an expletive by a national
leader, perhaps a symbol of President Trump's frustration with the Iranian government
and their refusal to concede to the demands that he is making.
That reference as well was to the Strait of Hormuz, which in recent days President Trump
had insisted he did not care about saying the U.S. did not need the oil passing through
the Strait and it was up to the countries who are reliant on that oil to deal with the situation.
But now the demand about opening the Strait of Hormuz appears front and center of the
president's new demands of the Iranian government. President Trump threatening to, and I use his words,
blowing everything and taking the oil if Iran does not meet his new deadline,
which has now been set at 8 p.m. eastern time on Tuesday evening. He says in an earlier
media post that a power plant day and bridge day all wrapped up on Tuesday.
But on the other hand, in addition to these threats, President Trump is sending signals
that there's some kind of negotiation process underway. He's indicated that his close confidants,
Jared Kushner and Stephen Whitcoff are in consultation with either the Iranian government
and identified figures or some form of intermediary. And speaking to U.S. news outlets,
President Trump says that he is optimistic that there can be an agreement very soon.
He says the agreement could come within a matter of days rather than a matter of weeks.
So you've got this dichotomous approach from the president on the one hand threatening obliteration
to civilian targets within Iran, which some observers would contend to be a war crime.
But on the other hand, what he is saying is, yes, we are talking. The talks are going
well, and they could come to fruition before that new deadline I set, which is 8 p.m. eastern time
on Tuesday. Mike Hanna, Al Jazeera, Washington.
Ross Harrison is a senior fellow and book series editor at the Middle East Institute.
He told my colleague Malin Said that Iran is likely to interpret Trump's remarks as a sign
that the U.S. may be running out of options to reopen the Strait of Hormuz.
Well, I think they're accustomed to Donald Trump's style at this point.
I think they assume that what they're seeing in terms of Donald Trump's, frankly,
escalatory language and profane language is a sign of frustration and a sign that there may be
fewer options available to the United States to achieve the goal of opening the Strait of Hormuz.
So I think they're interpreting this as, to some degree, success of their policy of sort of
boxing Donald Trump in. And the fact that I think that they assume that this kind of escalatory
language is going to be followed by some kind of escalation on the ground in the coming days.
So that would probably be their assumption whether, in fact, that plays out, well, remains to be
seen. Ross, how do the Iranian leadership feel about the prospect of American boots on the
ground? Well, I'm sure they're not, they don't anticipate it any kind of a positive way,
though I think they're probably spent the last number of weeks preparing for it.
I think that they are recognizing that this boots on the ground approach may not have a
clear political objective, Maline, that if in fact the boots on the ground will be used to try
to open the Strait of Hormuz, it's likely to do the opposite. I think they understand that,
which is the way they're interpreting Donald Trump's tantrum this morning,
they're interpreting that I think to some degree as a recognition of the fact that Donald Trump
understands that a boots on the ground approach is not going to achieve the objective that it's
purported to have, which is to open the Strait because the minute the Strait becomes a combat
zone, ships aren't going to go through. So I think it's a recognition on the part of the
Iranians that the United States might not have a clear political objective and that there's
really no way to achieve the goal of opening the Strait with military means alone.
Details are emerging about the rescue of a U.S. airman after an intense 48-hour search operation.
The weapons systems officer had been missing since Friday when the fighter jet he was in
went down in southwest Iran. Tehran said it shot down the F-18E, a two-seater aircraft.
John Hendren reports from Washington.
It was a daring and risky mission to save an American airman from becoming
an Iranian prisoner of war. Iranian forces searched the mountainous areas of southwest
Iran after an F-15E fighter jet went down on Friday. It was the first time a U.S.
aircraft had crashed in hostile territory in the five-week-old war.
Two Blackhawk helicopters took fire as U.S. teams raced to find the missing crew member.
An A-10 Warthog, an air support aircraft, was also damaged, its pilot ejecting over the Gulf.
Iran broadcast photos
of what it said was debris from the fighter jet, including a jump seat.
Although the pilot had been rescued on Friday, the weapon specialist remained in hiding, evading
Iranian forces for two days.
Finally, early on Sunday, deep in Iranian territory, the U.S. search operation was successful.
President Donald Trump made the announcement on social media, posting, We Got Him, saying
the Colonel had been behind enemy lines in the treacherous mountains of Iran being
hunted by our enemies.
He said U.S. forces had been monitoring his location 24 hours a day and sent dozens of aircraft
armed with the most lethal weapons in the world to retrieve him.
Trump added, He sustained injuries, but he will be just fine.
A U.S. official told Al Jazeera the rescue operation began in darkness but ended in
an intense firefight and daylight, before dozens of heavily armed aircraft and
hundreds of troops transported the airmen out of Iran.
A U.S. officer in Iranian custody could have given Iran leverage, as it had when Iran
took U.S. hostages in 1979.
With that crisis averted, attention now shifts to the U.S. deadline for Iran to open the
Strait of Hormuz.
John Hendron, Al Jazeera, Washington.
As reported in John Story, U.S. officials say the rescue mission involved several aircraft.
Iranian state media released these pictures, reportedly showing the wreckage of a C-130
aircraft in Isfahan province.
American media are reporting U.S. forces destroyed at least one of their own planes on purpose
because it had become stuck and was unable to fly out.
Iranian armed forces dispute that series of events, claiming that its soldiers destroyed
two C-130 aircraft and two Blackhawk helicopters in what it characterized as a failed U.S.
rescue operation.
With God's help and support and through the vigilance and readiness of the fighters of
Islam and the armed forces, using electronic warfare, advanced new air defense systems,
the implementation of a ground mosaic defense plan, and the creation of a military and
security cordon, a number of these aircraft, including two C-130 military transport planes
and two Blackhawk helicopters, were hit and forced to make emergency landings
in an area south of Isfahan.
Under Iranian Islamic fighters, completed the operation to encircle the enemy in order to
prevent the disgrace of Trump, the President of the United States, and the hollow prestige
of the Army, was forced to carry out heavy bombing of its downed aircraft, equipment,
commanders, and soldiers.
Simon Mail is a retired British Army general and a former Middle East adviser at the
UK Ministry of Defence.
He explains how the rescue operation unfolded.
An F-15 has two aircrew, obviously a pilot and a weapons officer.
The Colonel rescued his, the weapons officer.
He'll be the back seat for those who watched Top Gun.
That is the goose, as opposed to the Maverick post.
And when the aircraft is hit, obviously both eject.
What was interesting is the pilot ejected and was found relatively quickly and was
rescued.
And the weapons officer was not.
They would have landed inevitably a good distance probably from each other.
They'd both have transponders.
They'd know pretty quickly where they'd landed.
They'd be a transponder probably in the ejector seat.
I'm not an airman.
I'm a cavalryman, armor officer, and clearly on the pilot.
Now, in this case, of course, the pilot, although we understand to have been wounded
or damaged in some way, whether by the ejector or the strike on the aircraft, will have
gone into his escape and evasion tactics, which every pilot, every aircrew, is taught
as just part of their basic training.
And there will be inevitably that any number of films about this locals will know
where it's landed.
They'll have seen the parachutes come down.
There will be local police.
There may be a local barracks.
And all of these have a certain degree of sheer luck if you're far enough away
from them to a put a distance between yourself and the ejector seat or the debris of
the crashed aircraft.
And you can quickly be located.
But even if you're located, you've actually got to be retrieved.
I don't know the circumstances of the pilot being rescued.
But this obviously was a man who was, say, however badly injured, trying to put
distance between himself and the aircraft, the ejector seat.
And meanwhile, of course, they will have got drones over him, armed drones.
So they will have had eyes on him in many ways.
They would have been able to track him anyway.
But they'll soon or later have had eyes on him,
therbin imaging at night, visual during the day.
But even then, you've got to imagine a net getting closer and closer around him.
And eventually, you've got to put somebody on the ground who can physically
lift him off.
And in that, you've got to create a sort of area, sanitized area around him.
And certainly the report does refer to possibly the idea that they put
some aircraft on the ground or helicopters.
And that, again, you know, they're vulnerable as well.
And those may have been hit while they destroyed them,
in which case they'd have trans-shipped crew.
The Iran War is piling pressure on Sri Lanka,
which is still recovering from an economic meltdown four years ago.
The government has just raised gas prices by 20%.
Petrol and diesel are also being rationed now,
and electricity costs 25% more.
Manel Fernandez reports from Colombo that many people are struggling to cope.
Lassit Gayan has worked for a food delivery company in Colombo for four years.
The 39-year-old's income depends on the number of deliveries he makes.
But restrictions on fuel and price increases caused by the Iran War
have affected his earnings.
I make around $20 a day, but I have to buy all my meals.
That costs more than $5 a day.
I use what's left for fuel, rent and to send home to my family.
Restaurants like this, where Gayan is picking up his first order for the day,
are also struggling.
Gas for cooking is more expensive.
And manager Suranga Tirunagama says good quality ingredients are difficult to find.
This has forced many outlets to increase their prices.
Something Tirunagama says he's trying to avoid.
We're trying our best to manage without raising prices,
but it's getting more challenging day by day
because today's prices are not the same tomorrow.
We can't budget.
Prices are increasing.
And it's already evident.
Gayan says he's delivering few orders these days.
Many people we spoke to told us the worst part is the uncertainty.
On the way to his next pickup, Gayan fills up.
The government has imposed fuel restrictions.
Motorbike riders get a weekly quota of 8 litres.
Half the fuel Gayan says he usually goes through.
Station owner Sampat Kotalavala is also dealing with uncertainty.
We only receive about 50% of the supplies we order.
And we manage these stocks according to the framework the government has given us.
It's not enough for some, but generally it's okay.
But that's for today. I can't say what tomorrow will be like.
There are other pressures too.
A long-pending electricity price increase took effect this month
with some bills set to go up by 25%.
The government has asked people to use power sparingly.
Ironing and washing clothes only once a week.
And government officers have been told to switch off air conditioners early.
Just as Sri Lanka is recovering from its worst economic crisis,
the Iran war is causing more uncertainty.
People are paying more for fuel, food and even public transport
as a conflict thousands of kilometres away since prices soaring.
On the road, Gayan has stopped for a cup of tea and a snack
that's costing him more now than it did two weeks ago.
But he must hurry because the next order is waiting.
Minna Fernandez, Al Jazeera, Colombo.
The Middle East conflict is also affecting workers in Indian-administered Kashmir.
The region relies heavily on handicrafts
with thousands of people working in the industry.
But their livelihoods are at risk
because at least half of their goods are sold in the Middle East.
And with the region stuck in a war, orders are being delayed or cancelled.
Lina Abu Akle reports.
The Kotas are one of thousands of families
who have been part of Kashmir's craft industry for generations.
They spin yarn from the wool of Himalayan chang-thangi goats
on traditional hand looms, creating Peshmina scarves.
Peshmina is not just work for us, it's our legacy and identity.
I am one of the thousands of women who hand-spin the yarn
and this spinning is the backbone of our livelihood.
However, their income is in jeopardy.
The family has reduced production
using only two of their four hand looms.
That's because at least 50% of Kashmir's handicrafts
are sold to the Middle East
and the regional conflict has led to cancellations.
This is impacting us a lot.
The work is minimal, about 90% less than usual.
Tausif Bhatt also comes from a family of Peshmina makers.
But now, he runs a company employing around 60 people.
If the situation remains the same and the conflict continues,
I think we may eventually have to shut down the business.
The Kashmir Chamber of Commerce says it's not only a lack of orders
that is a problem, but the cost of sending anything
has risen astronomically.
Nobody can send the shipments, we have the airline problems,
we have the by sea, there are problems.
And I would rather say 400,000 people are affected with this war.
That's a lot of families at risk of losing their livelihoods.
Let's take a look at some of the other stories making news.
In the Gaza Strip, Hamas says it will not hand over its weapons.
Disarmament is part of the second phase of the Gaza ceasefire plan.
But the armed group says calls to lay down its weapons are unacceptable,
especially because Palestinians continue to be targeted by Israel.
More than 700 have been killed since the ceasefire came into effect in October.
As for raising the issue of weapons in this crude manner,
it is nothing but a scandalous attempt by the occupation
to continue killing and genocide against our people,
which we will not accept under any circumstances.
We affirm that what the enemy was unable to seize from us
with tanks and genocide, it will not seize from us with politics
or at the negotiation table.
The occupation's aggression against our people
and its continued closure of the blessed Al Aqsa Mosque
to worshipers in an unprecedented manner
and the approval of the law for executing Palestinian prisoners,
we call upon the masses of our Palestinian people
in the brave West Bank, the blessed Jerusalem
and the occupied interior to march toward Al Aqsa Mosque.
Muin Rabani is a non-resident fellow
at the Center for Conflict and Humanitarian Studies.
He says Hamas's statement confirms
that talks to implement the second phase
of the Gaza ceasefire plan are deadlocked.
What Hamas informed the mediators
is that it will not discuss issues such as disarmament
relating to the second phase of the plan for the Gaza Strip
until the items of the first phase are implemented.
That includes a cessation of hostilities.
As you noted, virtual daily Israeli attacks
on the Gaza Strip have resulted
in more than 700 Palestinians killed.
Humanitarian aid continues to be restricted
and most notably this National Committee
for the Administration of the Gaza Strip
which was established by the Board of Peace
continues to be prohibited
from entering the Gaza Strip by the Israelis
and the Board of Peace is doing absolutely nothing
to ensure its ability to get in.
And so I think Hamas is taking two positions.
A, it won't discuss the second phase
until the first phase is properly implemented.
And B, when those discussions do take place,
it's not going to simply surrender its weapons
unless Israel clearly meets its own obligations as well.
And those are obligations that have to be consistent
not just with what the Board of Peace wants
but with the international consensus
and the rulings of the International Court of Justice
that this is an illegal occupation
that must end.
Thousands of Palestinians in Gaza
are still waiting for Israeli permits
to evacuate for medical treatment.
Aza Audwan and her grandson were granted a permit
and went to Egypt.
He had a congenital heart condition
and needed urgent surgery, but he died.
When Aza returned to Gaza,
she found her husband and children
had been killed in an airstrike.
She's now alone.
In this report, she shares her story.
Who are you, mother?
My brother-in-law, my brother-in-law.
I left Gaza with Hafideh,
the most secure one.
Hafideh was the first one to give birth to my son.
He had a congenital heart condition
and needed urgent surgery,
because he had a congenital heart condition
and had severe injuries.
He was suffering a lot.
A lot of cuts,
the fire and the war that we saw
were unbearable.
He needed urgent surgery,
but unfortunately, in Gaza,
there were no hospitals or hospitals.
No hospitals were able to treat him.
In the end, we were transferred to Egypt
and went to Egypt to treat him.
In the end, he died.
He died of a sudden death.
We were shocked
that we saw Józef after him.
After him, we saw most of his family.
I want to tell you
that Józef and his children were killed in the war.
They were all martyred.
I don't know what to say.
I don't know what's in his heart.
My Lord, young people,
young people like Warda,
young people,
young people like me,
my children, Warda,
my heart,
they were all martyred.
Józef,
my life, my heart,
they were all martyred.
He had a big face.
He was all martyred.
Ukraine has struck a coal mine
in Russian-controlled Luhansk,
damaging a power substation
and trapping 41 workers underground.
That's according to a Russian-installed official
in the region.
Leonid Pesetchnik said
emergency crews are working to rescue the miners
and restore power to the site.
He said that the miners do have a supply
of drinking water.
Serbia says that explosives have been found
near a pipeline that carries Russian gas to Hungary.
Authorities say the discovery was made
outside a Serbian town near the Hungarian border.
It comes just a week
before closely watched elections in Hungary.
Prime Minister Viktor Orban
is fighting to extend his 16 years in power.
He's linked Ukraine to those explosives
without blaming Kiev directly.
As Christians around the world
mark the Easter holiday,
under the shadow of war,
religious leaders were calling for peace.
Sonya Gallego reports.
It is the most important date in the Christian calendar,
marked this year by both tradition and tension.
Addressing more than a billion Catholics worldwide
from the Vatican,
Pope Leo led his first Easter Mass as pontiff.
And the message from St. Peter's Square
was shaped by events far beyond it.
Death is always lurking.
We see it present in injustices,
in partisan selfishness,
in the oppression of the poor,
in the lack of attention given to the most vulnerable.
We see it in violence,
in the wounds of the world,
in the cry of pain that rises from every corner
because of the abuses that crush the weakest.
An appeal for mercy as the conflict in the Middle East
loomed over what is meant to be a celebration of renewal,
where despite airstrikes and destruction,
many felt the need to commemorate the holiday.
Over the weekend, the message resonated in Germany
in the annual Easter March in Cologne,
not a religious procession,
but a demand for an end to hostilities.
And in France, as the bells of Notre Dame in Paris rang out,
calling worshippers to mass.
In Lyon, thousands of adults were baptized.
A sign said church leaders of the search for meaning
in an ever more uncertain world.
Sonia Gallego Al Jazeera.
One of China's leading arts universities
has scrapped degrees in subjects like translation
and photography, saying they're a waste of resources
in the age of artificial intelligence.
The decision is now fueling debate online
about how far technology should be shaping education.
Katrina Yu reports from Beijing.
Alex Scher built her career in the creative industries
after graduating with a degree
in English translation and interpreting,
but qualifications like hers could soon disappear.
As some of China's biggest universities cut courses,
they say are being overtaken by artificial intelligence.
Alex says the move risks overlooking
the broader skills behind translation,
from communication to critical thinking.
When you translate for sure,
yes, AI could probably get the accuracy up
to almost close to perfection,
but there's still that personal style
that's always been essential in translation.
And when it comes to interpreting.
It's not just translation.
Degrees in photography, illustration,
and fashion design are also being scrapped
with universities saying the future lies
in human machine cooperation.
The changes are part of a broader government push
to steer students towards industries
it considers critical to the country's future,
including robotics, semiconductors,
and artificial intelligence.
The pressure is growing.
More than 12 million students graduated in China last year,
a record number,
and many are struggling to find jobs,
highlighting a mismatch between skills and demand.
But AI is also creating new opportunities
in the film and creative sectors.
New roles are emerging,
like prompt engineers and AI animators.
Before AI, it could take a month
just to design characters or scenes.
Now we can complete an entire project in a month.
Universities are trying to adapt,
launching new programs.
that combine creative training with AI skills.
Alex says it's more important than ever
for young people to diversify their skills.
She cites stand-up comedy among her own.
Baby, what's your name?
It's just the case that we're in this ever-changing
and ever-changing, faster time period of human history
and we just have to be ready.
It's just not those days anymore.
We can't put all of our eggs in one basket.
But she says one thing still matters.
The human touch.
Katrina Yu, Al Jazeera, Beijing.
Four astronauts are just hours away
from becoming the first people
to see the dark side of the moon.
The Artemis II mission crew
has entered the final phase of its journey,
preparing to do a loop around the far side of the moon.
At this point, the moon's gravity
has a stronger pull on their capsule than Earth's.
The three Americans and one Canadian
will travel further from Earth
than any human before them
as they complete their first crewed lunar fly-by
in more than 50 years.
They'll lose communications for about 40 minutes
while passing behind the moon,
where they are also expected to witness a solar eclipse.
We will be back in just a moment
with more extensive coverage of the war
between the U.S., Israel and Iran.
I'm Raleigh Carlson.
Cyril Vanieg will be here next
with more on the day's coverage.
Stay with us.
The Latest News.
As war continues, uncertainty hangs over everyday life,
especially when it comes to how long it will take.
It's the very organized citizens
who continue to pay the price.
And in-depth reports.
Iranian officials are denying this,
the foreign minister,
saying that they're not looking for a ceasefire.
They want a comprehensive end of this war.
From the heart of the story.
We have a list here that the Iranians have published
about the civilian facilities
that have been struck,
that is for Iranians a red line.
On counting the cost,
with higher oil prices and east sanctions,
Russia is hoping to gain from the conflict in the Middle East
and further its war aims in Ukraine.
But those plans are at risk from Ukrainian attacks.
So can Russia help fill the global energy gap
or is its capacity already under threat?
Counting the cost on Al Jazeera.
Hearing the facts.
The busy day for Iran today
could mean when Iran retaliates,
it will be a busy day for cities in the Gulf.
Asking questions.
How much damage can this conflict
really inflict on the global economy?
Reporting from the action.
This is the third time the Israeli military has targeted an area
outside Hezbollah's traditional strongholds.
With the latest global news and insightful documentaries,
Al Jazeera's teams across the world
bring you closer to the heart of the story.
This is Al Jazeera live from Doha
with our continuing coverage of the war
between the U.S., Israel and Iran.
I'm Cyril Vanier,
coming up in the program today.
Overnight, U.S. and Israeli strikes on Iran
kill at least 34 people.
Civilian infrastructure,
including a top university, has been targeted.
Iran carries out strikes in Israel,
killing two people in the northern city of Haifa
and causing extensive damage in and around Tel Aviv.
Donald Trump extends his deadline for Iran
to reopen the Strait of Hormuz to Tuesday,
but warns that he will, quote,
unleash hell if they don't.
Israel also carries out attacks across Lebanon,
targeting a residential building in the capital
where at least three people have been killed.
So the U.S. and Israel have stepped up their attacks on Iran.
A deadline set by President Donald Trump is nearing.
He is demanding that Iran reopen the Strait of Hormuz.
Tehran maintains that the waterway is open
to everyone except its enemies.
At least 34 people have been killed in Iran
in overnight strikes by the U.S. and Israel.
Several areas have been targeted,
including a university in Tehran
and an airport in the southwest.
Iran says that more than 2,000 people have been killed
since the war began.
And Iran has continued its own retaliatory strikes,
sending missiles across Israel.
At least two people have been killed
in the northern city of Haifa
and there has been extensive damage in and around Tel Aviv.
U.S. President Donald Trump has renewed threats
to destroy Iranian power plants and bridges
if it doesn't reopen the Strait of Hormuz by Tuesday
that is 8 p.m. Eastern time.
Iran saying that it will retaliate
to any strikes on infrastructure
and that any sites in the region connected to the U.S.
would be a target.
But we're live in Beirut, in Kuwait City,
in Ramallah, in the occupied West Bank,
and in Tehran, the Iranian capital.
That's where we start with Taheed Asadi.
So Taheed, brief us on what was targeted inside Iran.
Well, last night, it was yet another night
of the heavy bombardments of the Americans in Israel.
These targeting different places across the Iranian capital
to Iran, where the northern, excuse me,
the southern, eastern and western parts
of the capital were targeted.
And to give you a picture,
we know that over the past two weeks,
the damages are going to actually impact
more of infrastructural facilities,
not only in the capital but across the country.
Earlier in the morning,
we've got footages of the attacks
on Sharif University of Technology,
which is known as Iran's MIT,
the most important technical university
of the country, targeted.
The president of the university came out
to confirm the attacks,
and also we know that a gas facility
adjacent to the university campus was also hit.
But so we know that the scope of these airstrikes
go well beyond the capital.
We have a relatively long list of different cities
across the country, including Karaj,
Shiraz, Isfahan, Boucher, Bandar-e-Lenge,
where at least six people were killed,
Ome, where at least five people were killed,
Baharistan near Tehran,
in which at least 13 people were killed,
including six children.
And that is basically showing the damage
and cost of these ongoing sustained campaign
of airstrikes.
Now, moving us into a sort of next level,
speaking of the infrastructure,
we know that several schools, universities, hospitals,
and other infrastructural areas
have been impacted so far,
living a huge amount of cost upon the Iranian nation.
So Donald Trump has been threatening
to blow up Iran's bridges and power plants
if the country doesn't reopen the Strait of Hormuz
by Tuesday, 8 p.m. Eastern time in the U.S.,
which would bring us to the early hours
of Wednesday morning Iranian time.
Is there any sign that Iran may moderate its approach
in any way before that deadline?
Not that much that we can call a sign.
We know that it's not the first deadline
and it's not the first time that he is coming up
with this threatening rhetoric
to direct and address Iranians.
And there are a couple of points in that regard.
First, we know that Iranians are sort of used
to this rhetoric from the very early days of war.
And this is a continuation of the same for Iranians.
It would be like dancing with the same old tune,
but it's still, it doesn't mean
that they're not going to take it seriously
because over the past two weeks,
they have seen the translation of these statements
into real act of war,
something that Iranians are calling war crime,
targeting universities, schools, hospitals,
and bridges and other infrastructure across the country.
So the threat is going to be taken very seriously.
But on the other hand,
the rhetoric that we hear from Tehran Cyril
is not that of actually going in line
or accepting these sort of threatening language,
but quite the other way around.
They are talking about defiance.
They're talking about retaliation.
They're talking about deterrence.
And they're saying that in case
our infrastructure is attacked,
there is going to be obviously a tit for tat retaliatory
strategy they have threatened,
specifically the military spokesperson.
And in particular,
the spokesperson for joint military headquarters
of Khatam al-Ambiyah have came out several times
to say that Iran is going to target
the infrastructure of the Israeli territories
as well as all the U.S. assets across the region.
And those infrastructure providing support,
such as electricity or whatever,
to the American bases across the region,
are going to be their quote-unquote legitimate target,
which means we will be dealing
with another level of escalation
in this already intricate situation.
Tahir Asadi reporting from the Iranian capital, Tehran.
Thank you very much, Tahir.
At least two people have been killed
in an Iranian strike on a building in the city of Haifa.
That is according to Israeli media.
The residential structure partially collapsed
after the attack on Sunday.
At least four others have been wounded.
And we did mention earlier in the program
that sites in and around Tel Aviv were also attacked.
Nida Abraham is following those developments in Israel
from Ramallah in the occupied West Bank.
Nida, after more than five weeks of war,
can you give us an overall picture
of how much damage Iran has actually done in Israel?
Well, the main issue that remains concerning
to Israelis is that extensive damage to buildings,
to homes, these continued strikes from Iran
are causing people to be in shelters in fortified areas,
but that does not mean that they won't get targeted
or hit by these Iranian missiles.
When we talk about Haifa,
there was a failure to intercept this missile,
although it has been detected
and several intercepting missiles
tried to stop it from attacking this building,
but indeed it still did that.
When we talk about the south of the country,
near Dimona, which is where the nuclear Israeli facility is,
they've seen major damage several times,
one time causing damage to hundreds of homes
causing people to be displaced,
but also we're talking about another hit yesterday
that hit a factory the third time
since this version of this battle started
between the Israel and between Israel, the US and Iran.
We need to remember that these hits
are sometimes affecting strategic assets inside Israel,
but because of the tough and strict military censorship,
we know little about what happens there
because this is part of the war Israel is trying to wage,
a psychological aspect to try and keep the population
supporting this war.
And in the beginning, we were reporting
of this high support of this war
amounting to almost 80% of people saying in polls
that they support this war,
this is something that they see as an existential threat.
But as the war goes on and as these war goals
that Netanyahu has promised his people
are not being achieved,
it's taking much longer than had been anticipated
and that's the ultimate fear for many Israelis,
a war of attrition.
They know that Iran can stand for a long time.
It has prepared itself for a long war,
but can the Israelis handle that?
We have calls from certain opposition leaders
saying that education needs to go back,
that they need to try and resort some normalcy
so people can go on with their lives
despite these continued strikes.
Nitta, it's really interesting what you bring up
about the support for the war,
which isn't as high today five weeks in
as it was at the very beginning.
You were mentioning 80% support for the war in Israel.
That was five weeks ago,
but since then, as you also reported,
people have been going in and out of their shelters
and their bunkers as missiles rain down on Israel,
and it's more than that.
I understand that some people are now living
in those shelters rather than just occasionally
going into them.
So I don't know if it's possible to measure the patience
that Israelis might still have with this war,
but what are the indications in terms of
how much of a runway they're willing
to give their government to continue this war?
Well, that's the tough question.
How long can they handle?
And we know that when protests have happened
during the Gaza war,
Netanyahu paid little attention to the streets anger,
the streets calls for him to end the war sooner than he did.
But this time we're also seeing a similar wave
of more Israelis feeling, are we waging a war
because Netanyahu wants to win the next elections?
We know that his government is one of the few
in the history of Israel to complete its full term
and we expect it to hand over power
when the elections take place later this year.
But Netanyahu is not ready to give up just yet.
He wants to win these seats
and he also wants to avoid his corruption trials.
So he's pushing for a continuation of the war,
saying he has more bank of targets,
he has more strikes to do in Iran,
and that he did not give up on the main goal
of changing the regime,
but that did not get achieved.
And Israelis find themselves going to shelters,
as you say, sometimes living in them
because of the continued sirens blasting,
not just from Iraq, but also from Hezbollah,
which according to Israeli army officials,
they've been underestimating the power of Hezbollah.
So that's a very sensitive issue
and there are more Israelis who believe
that they are waging a war to help Netanyahu standing
and that is not sitting very well with many of them.
Nida Abraham reporting from Ramallah
in the occupied West Bank.
Thank you very much, Nida.
The threat of escalation in Iran
has put the Gulf region squarely
in the crossfire as well.
In the United Arab Emirates capital,
one person was injured after debris
from an intercepted missile fell in an industrial area.
And the Saudi defense ministry says
that two drones have been intercepted
and destroyed in just the past few hours.
Al Jazeera's Malik Trena is in Kuwait city.
Malik, you're monitoring developments
really across the region, across the Gulf.
What are you seeing today?
Well, in the UAE, zero authorities in Fujairah
said they were responding to an incident
at a telecommunications company.
You know, the debris from these interceptions,
what we've learned here in the Gulf
can be very dangerous and sometimes deadly.
In the UAE, you know, numerous people have died.
Due from the debris shrapnel, from these interceptions.
You know, you mentioned the industrial city in Abu Dhabi
where one person was injured.
He was a Ghanaian national.
And we've seen attacks also across the region.
You know, in Saudi Arabia, the Ministry of Defense,
they're saying they intercepted two drones
in the last couple of hours.
And here in Kuwait, we woke up to the alarms
being sounded numerous times.
So these attacks on the Gulf continue.
Malik, question specifically on Kuwait,
because yesterday you were reporting on this,
Kuwait was really badly hit
and that included critical infrastructure,
including desalination plants.
24 hours after that wave of attacks,
what's the damage assessment?
Well, authorities here are still assessing the damage.
I mean, numerous, several locations in Kuwait were hit.
You know, two power and water desalination plants.
One next to the Ezur desalination plant,
that's one of the biggest in the Middle East.
You know, desalination is extremely important
for the Gulf, but here in Kuwait, more so.
You know, there's eight desalination plants.
More than 90% of the drinking water
comes from these plants, so it's extremely important.
I think for Kuwait officials, you know,
the water infrastructure is a red line
and that continues to be crossed.
But we also saw, you know, according to authorities,
fires where several fires broke out
at the petrochemical company, as well as oil facilities.
We saw two power generation units
being taken off the grid.
A finance ministry building was hit.
Also, the Kuwaiti Petroleum Company headquarters was hit.
You know, the ministerial complex here in Kuwait
and houses 19 buildings.
You know, there's the Ministry of Labor,
the Ministry of Social Affairs, the Ministry of Finance,
and various, you know, very important government institutions.
They've told employees not to show up to work,
to work remotely.
I think here in Kuwait, you know,
what we've seen in the last couple of weeks
is that these Iranian drones have been able
to circumvent their air defense system.
So as this, you know, looming deadline approaches,
people here become extremely worried.
You know, the Kuwait is the closest country to Iran.
Only 80 kilometers of water is what separates it.
So, you know, on a geographical standpoint,
it's the most easily targeted, you know.
And it also borders Iraq,
where officials have been saying for the last week or so
that a lot of these drones or attacks
are coming from Iranian factions,
Iranian allied factions from Iraq.
So, you know, people here become extremely worried.
And when President Trump says that, you know,
he's gonna let the gates of hell lose,
obliterate power and water infrastructure,
what we've consistently seen is Iran attacks the Gulf.
So I think, you know, the main objective
for Gulf countries right now
is to try to de-escalate the situation.
They've said from the beginning
that, you know, there's no military solution here.
Let's de-escalate the situation.
Let's find a diplomatic path towards ending this war
and bringing long-term stability.
Malik Trina reporting from Kuwait City.
Thank you very much, Malik.
And US President Donald Trump has been giving Iran
shifting deadlines to reopen the Strait of Hormuz.
That is, as Iran insists
that the key waterway isn't actually closed
and that only ships that belong to its enemies
are barred from passage.
Trump issued his first ultimatum on March 21st.
He threatened to bomb Iran's power plants
if the Strait wasn't reopened within 48 hours.
But he later extended that deadline by five days,
claiming that negotiations were underway and going well.
And Trump issued then a new deadline on March 26th
and he gave Iran 10 days.
So that was the second extension.
Or until the evening of April 6th to reopen the Strait.
Trump issued his latest Hormuz threat on Sunday.
After vowing to bomb power plants and bridges
if Tehran does not comply,
he posted what appears to be a Tuesday,
8 p.m. Eastern time deadline for a deal to be made
or the Strait to be reopened.
Michael Shubridge is the Director
of Strategic Analysis Australia.
That is a defense and security think tank.
He's in Moruya in Australia.
Michael, it's good to have you on the program.
We appear to see two opposing beliefs here.
The US belief that they can ultimately bomb Iran
into changing their behavior.
And the Iranian belief, apparently,
that holding and controlling the Strait of Hormuz
actually puts them in a dominant position,
gives them more leverage than the entire
military capability of the United States.
Those two things, completely contradictory ideas,
they don't meet in the middle.
So where does that take us?
Well, Cyril, I think you're right
to lay out those two very different perspectives.
And that's what President Trump
seems to be finding so jarring and difficult.
He thought that overwhelming military power
from Israel and America would cause
the Iranian regime to fold and meet his demands.
That just hasn't happened.
And as the war has gone on through weeks,
the Americans and Israelis keep trying
to do the same thing, but more of it,
more bombing and damage to military and government sites,
and expect a different result.
That isn't happening.
So right now, the leverage is with Iran.
So you say, that was gonna be my next question,
that the US and Israel continue to bomb,
hoping that what hasn't yet happened,
in other words, Iran changing its behavior,
Iran conceding, or Iran even capitulating,
it hasn't yet happened, but they believe or hope
that maybe it will happen.
Do you think that it can?
No, I don't, because I think doubling down
on this failing course of action
by the Americans and Israelis is not gonna change
the fact that the Iranians have sufficient military power
to keep the strait closed
to those that doesn't want to pass the strait,
and to attack the broader infrastructure
of the Gulf States and Israel.
So that my real concern now,
is unless these very uncertain, strange negotiations
around a ceasefire somehow come to fruit,
we will see the escalation from America and Israel
to destroy more civilian infrastructure in Iran,
and Iran will reciprocate by damaging
even more civilian infrastructure across the Gulf.
From a defense standpoint,
I wonder how you analyze the fact that the U.S. and Israel,
specifically the U.S., actually,
has been saying for weeks that they are this close
to getting rid of all of Iran's missiles and drones
and missile and drone building capability.
They've been saying this for weeks,
and yet Iran is still able to fire missiles and drones.
How does that make sense from a defense standpoint?
Well, because the American assessments
aren't founded on good information,
and they don't seem to have taken account
of very recent experience.
So why is Israel now doing a major ground invasion
of Lebanon?
Just a year ago, we were told that completely destroyed
Hezbollah's leadership and their capacity
to launch rockets and drones against Israel.
And then we heard from the Israelis,
well, Hezbollah had unexpectedly, rapidly rebuilt
its leadership and missile and drone capabilities.
Well, Iran is able to do that on a much bigger scale.
And the Houthis are another good example.
So it's no surprise, I would think,
to many people in the U.S. intelligence community
that Iran can still keep launching missiles and drones.
It just seems not to have percolated into the White House.
Okay, well, Michael, sorry to allow me to insist,
because you're saying it's no surprise
to many people in the intelligence community.
But what you're also telling us
is that both Israel and the United States,
we're talking about the most formidable
military force in the world.
You're saying they went into this war
with a completely false assessment
of their enemy's capabilities.
Yes, I am.
And I think, well, Israel, I'm not sure, had that delusion.
I think the Israeli plan is really to weaken
Iran as much as possible
and they're happy to have the Americans helping.
So this looks more like what Israel likes to see,
but I think there's no doubt
that the American government is surprised
in a way that they simply shouldn't be.
So in that case, I circle back
to something similar to my first question,
which is if the U.S. belief is we can bomb them
and somehow change the situation.
And if you're telling us, actually, no,
their information is wrong, their assumption,
their base assumption for this war
on the American side is wrong,
then what happens next?
Because if they keep bombing and nothing changes,
surely at some point,
that information to use your words
will percolate up to the White House.
Well, only after a lot of other damage has been done.
So it looks to me with these increasingly angry,
frustrated, incoherent messages
coming out of President Trump
at all hours of the day and night
that he wants to double down
because at the moment it's an embarrassment.
And so destroying broader infrastructure in Iran
or doing something symbolic like seizing Karg Island
may then let him change the story,
but it doesn't change how the war's going.
Michael Shubridge, thank you very much
for joining us on the program.
And Israel has carried out multiple strikes
across Southern Lebanon and the capital, Beirut,
causing widespread damage and death.
Israeli military attacks targeted multiple areas
in the Nabata district in the south.
At least four people were killed
in a drone strike targeting a car.
And in a separate attack in the same area,
one person was killed.
Overnight, the Israeli military targeted an apartment
east of Beirut, killing at least three people
in the southern suburbs.
Strikes on a densely populated area
killed five people on Sunday.
Israeli attacks across Lebanon
have killed more than 1,300 people.
That is according to the Lebanese health ministry.
Let's bring in Al-Jazeera Zain al-Khodr.
You're in the capital, Zain al-Khodr.
What more can you tell us about that attack in Beirut?
Civilians are increasingly being caught up
in this conflict.
The attack in Beirut on Sunday.
There were two.
One in the district of Znech.
Five people were killed.
Three Sudanese nationals, a 15-year-old child,
and the apparent target, a Hezbollah military commander.
So even in the so-called targeted assassination,
civilians are being killed.
In another strike in Beirut last night in Ain Sa'adi,
that's a district north of Beirut,
three people were killed.
The missile targeted the third floor of the building
and these civilians were on the second floor
of the building.
The Lebanese health ministry saying that 1,461 people
have been killed, 4,000 people wounded.
That doesn't include the latest casualties this morning
in Mashkhara, that's in West Bikar,
three people killed.
In Farouman, a car was hit,
that's in the Nabati district in South Lebanon,
four people killed.
There was another strike in Nabati, another person killed.
So the death toll keeps climbing
and this conflict is in its sixth week.
The Lebanese health ministry and its figures,
it doesn't differentiate between combatants
and civilians, but if you count the number of women,
children, paramedics, that's roughly 25%.
So there is increasing concern
because this conflict really has no red line.
Even though Israel may want to target a specific Hezbollah,
a member, it doesn't really matter
if that member is an intensely populated area.
Zayna, I know it is difficult to make out precisely
how the war in the southern part of the country
is going, Southern Lebanon,
but what are you able to tell us?
We understand Israel continues to push
a little further into the country,
but we also understand that they are met
with what I think is fierce resistance
from Hezbollah fighters.
No doubt, yes, there has been fierce resistance.
Hezbollah trying to slow that advance
and in fact, in the past 48 hours, it has been slowed.
The Israeli military now focusing on trying
to besiege the southern town of Bintish Bayle,
which is a few kilometers from the border
in the central sector of South Lebanon,
a very strategic town,
trying to cut the supply lines to this town.
It also has a symbolic value
because it's known as in Lebanon
as the capital of the resistance.
So, yes, that invasion has been slowed down,
Israel facing obstacles with the Israeli army chief
saying that while the ultimate objective of Israel
is to disarm Hezbollah,
the objective of the current campaign
is to advance that objective.
He's not even talking about achieving that objective,
but advancing that objective.
The Israeli army is under no illusion
that even if you reach the Littani River,
it doesn't mean you disarm Hezbollah.
Hezbollah's strategic weapons,
it's long-range missiles,
they're in the east of the country,
in the Bekaa, in the Baalbek region.
Over the past two years,
we've reported repeatedly about airstrikes
targeting those regions
and yet we see Hezbollah launching those rockets.
Zeina Hodor reporting from the Lebanese capital Beirut.
Thank you very much, Zeina.
In the Gaza Strip now, Hamas says
that it will not hand over its weapons.
Disarmament is part of the second phase
of the Gaza cease-fire plan.
That's the phase that we're currently in,
but the armed group says
that calls to lay down its weapons are unacceptable,
especially as Palestinians continue
to be targeted by Israel.
More than 700 have been killed
since the cease-fire came into effect in October.
As for raising the issue of weapons
in this crude manner,
it is nothing but a scandalous attempt
by the occupation to continue killing
and genocide against our people,
which we will not accept under any circumstances.
We affirm that what the enemy was unable to seize from us
with tanks and genocide,
it will not seize from us with politics
or at the negotiation table.
The occupation's aggression against our people
and its continued closure of the blessed al-Aqsa mosque
to worshipers in an unprecedented manner
and the approval of the law
for executing Palestinian prisoners,
we call upon the masses of our Palestinian people
in the brave West Bank,
the blessed Jerusalem and the occupied interior
to march toward al-Aqsa mosque.
Ukraine has struck a coal mine in Russian-controlled Luhansk,
damaging a power substation
and trapping 41 workers underground.
That is according to a Russian-installed official
in the region.
Leonid Pazashnik said emergency crews
are working to rescue the miners
and restore power to the site.
He said the miners have a supply of drinking water.
Four astronauts are hours away
from becoming the first people
to see the dark side of the moon with their own eyes.
So the four crew members of the Artemis II mission
have entered the final run-up
to a loop around the back of the moon.
At this point, the moon's gravity
has a stronger pull on the capsule
that they're traveling on than Earth's gravity.
The three Americans and one Canadian
will travel further from Earth than any human
when they complete the first crewed lunar fly-by
in more than 50 years.
They will lose communications for about 40 minutes
while they're behind the moon,
but they will also be witnessing a solar...
Stay with us.
Our coverage of the war between the US, Israel and Iran
continues after this.
As the US-Israel war on Iran rages on,
its impact has spread far beyond the battlefield.
Energy prices are soaring
as facilities and supply routes are targeted.
Vital shipping lanes choked.
We strongly encourage other nations
whose economies depend on this train
to come and help us.
Stay with Al Jazeera for extensive coverage
and expert analysis
as shockwaves continue to shape the global economy.
In-depth analysis of the day's headlines.
Diplomacy yet again was used as a ruse for war.
Critical debate.
Who betrayed the table?
Who attacked the negotiations for the second time?
For the third time,
during the talks we should be attacked,
who is talking about a greater country for itself?
Israel, not Iran.
Iran has been a huge supporter of terrorism over the years.
I really have to take exception to the idea
that Iran is innocent in this.
Inside Story on Al Jazeera.
Hello, I'm Rashad Salamat.
This is Counting the Cost on Al Jazeera.
We're looking at the global economic impact
of the war in the Middle East.
One nation that's hoping to gain
from the Middle East conflict is Russia,
the world's third biggest oil producer.
Higher crude prices due to this disruption
in the Strait of Hormuz
have allowed Russia to earn more
from its oil and gas exports.
The US has temporarily eased sanctions
on Russian oil, but the European Union
has refused to do that,
saying more revenue will embolden Russia's efforts
to prolong its war in Ukraine.
But the revised budget plans are at risk
following repeated Ukrainian attacks
on ports and oil refineries.
Russia has banned petrol exports
to protect against domestic fuel shortages.
So can Russia help fill the global energy gap?
Or is its capacity already under threat?
Russia is seeing a turnaround
in its economic prospects
as oil and gas prices rise
and its tankers benefit from US-sanctioned waivers.
While the European Union is holding on to sanctions,
is there a new appetite in Europe
for Russian oil and gas?
The increased revenues expected to help close budget holes,
as well as bolster Russia's war plans against Ukraine.
But Kyiv has accelerated its strikes
on Russian oil infrastructure.
Will Ukrainian attacks limit Moscow's ability
to stabilize the global energy market?
We have a panel of guests to discuss all this shortly,
but first, here's Finnton Monaghan's report.
The war in the Middle East has raged for more than a month.
Disruption to shipping through the Strait of Hormuz
has cut off 20% of the world's oil and gas supply.
Many countries are preparing for tough times,
but for one, the chaos could provide
an opportunity to come out ahead.
Now that the prices of our traditional exports are rising,
but the markets are in turmoil,
there may be a temptation to take advantage of the situation,
to generate short-term gains.
I would like to emphasize it once again.
We must exercise common sense.
Russia is one of the world's largest producers of oil,
number three behind the United States and Saudi Arabia.
It relies on oil and gas revenues
to fund around a third of its national budget.
Up until 2022, it provided around 10% of global supply.
But the war in Ukraine upended Russia's economic model.
Western powers imposed sanctions
that closed off many key markets.
Russia continued to sell oil to partners like China and India,
but had to do so at a discount.
The Iran War has changed that arithmetic.
Fuel prices are surging,
as countries rushed outbid each other
to access suddenly limited supply.
The result has been a win-full for Russia.
Years of war and sanctions had squeezed Russia's finances.
Oil and gas revenues were down to $10 billion
in the first two months of the year,
a 47% drop compared to the same period in 2025.
The Kremlin was reportedly planning a 10% cut
to all non-security spending.
But now, analysts predict Russia could gain
an additional $45 billion in budget revenue this year.
If the war drags on for more than six months,
that could reach as high as $151 billion,
enough to replenish state coffers
and maintain war spending for years to come.
The need to stabilize global energy markets
has also benefited Russia.
The US loosened sanctions on Russian oil
that's already at sea,
freeing up around 100 million barrels for sale.
Europe shifted away from Russian energy,
but the current crisis has created pressure
to reverse that policy.
So far, the EU is resisting that temptation.
We see that the Russian economy is not doing well,
even the oil price hike is not helping them
as much as they need.
They have huge issues with recruitment
of new soldiers to their army.
So we have to see that this is the picture
that we can't give up now
with actually have to increase the pressure.
Ukraine is also keen to undermine Russia's advantage.
It stepped up attacks on oil export hubs.
40% of Russia's oil export capability
is now compromised,
according to the Reuters news agency.
Kiev strikes at damaged refineries,
causing fuel shortages in some regions.
Moscow is responded by imposing an export ban on petrol.
Ukraine's allies have been seizing tankers
belonging to the so-called Russian shadow fleet,
carrying oil and violation of sanctions.
Russia has downplayed the impact,
but warned it could make the global energy crisis worse.
Ukraine's attacks are creating,
amongst other things,
some entirely temporary difficulties,
but those could lead to greater price rises
and even deeper crisis,
including in the European Union and Britain.
Russia appears positioned to benefit
from the crisis in the Gulf,
and the longer the disruption continues,
the more it stands to gain.
Vinten Monaghan, Al Jazeera, for Counting the Cost.
Let's dive deeper into this.
Joining us from Moscow is a Russian energy expert
of Vyacheslav Mishenko in London.
We have John Lov.
He is head of policy
at the Think Tank New Eurasian Strategy Centre
and has previously worked with NATO
and the Russian oil and gas industry,
and in Berlin is Maria Pashtukova.
She's an expert in energy geopolitics and diplomacy,
as well as the program lead at E3G.
It's an independent think tank
focusing on energy policies globally.
First of all, Vyacheslav, let's start off with you.
How, what kind of state
is the Russian oil industry actually in?
Yes, well, actually, so for a decade or so,
Russian oil industry was a subject of coordination.
I'm talking about the production of oil, of course,
within the OPEC Plus platform.
And now I think because of the situation in the Gulf,
so this agreement and actually restrictions on production,
they don't work anymore.
So I think, so the production is there.
So Russia possesses some additional volumes to produce
and there are two crudes actually,
two market crudes like euros,
which normally should go to the west side
and actually ESPO, ESPO,
calls after the pipeline,
East Siberia Pacific Ocean,
which goes to the Pacific Ocean, actually.
I think that's the,
direction Russia could increase because the demand is in Asia-Pacific and actually South
and East Asia, and it amounts around 80 million tons a year, and in general I think Russia
could add and ship additional routes to this direction.
On top of that, there are some cargoes which were a subject of sanctions already
on the routes, and I think of fuck, and in general the American administration gave permission
to key buyers like India to get the screwed.
It was about 50 million barrels, I think, which already sold in the first month.
And the permission, if I'm not wrong, is 11th of April will be shut.
So I'm not sure about whether they go and prolongate it, but if so, Russia could
deliver more Euro-screwed to India as well.
Maria, the same question for you, and of course we're looking at all this in light of many
attacks by Ukrainian drones on Russian oil facilities.
Yes, sure.
So what I would say is that the serious bottleneck right now is the availability of freshers,
export infrastructure.
Its exports fell already by about 400,000 barrels month to month in February.
That was even before the latest Baltic escalation.
And then the March attacks on Primorsk and East Luga hit the export system much more directly.
What we're looking at is approximately 40% of Russia's crude export capacity that has
been affected, not of all of that taken out completely, but some parts of it.
So the Russia's Western export system has been impaired quite a bit.
And given that there are export constraints on the eastern track, because most of the
capacity towards the east is already at maximum or close to maximum, it is a big question
whether Russia will be able to boost its exports at all, will have actually to cut production
both of crude and petroleum products, because particularly the Western ports were
responsible for some exports of Russian petroleum products.
In that respect, even if Russia were able to boost its production and it has never
been a big swing state, so a boosting production in a short, short-distance demand has never
been Russia's forte, even if it would have been possible.
It's a big question whether it will be able to get it out.
We do not know the extent of the damage done fully yet.
We might be looking at several weeks, might be looking at some parts of that capacity
being out of operation for some months.
So I would say Russia cannot really meaningfully help offset the global energy disruptions
in particularly on oil in the short or mid-term, because what we're looking at is
it is not all of the 20 million barrels a day that normally exit hormones that are locked right now.
I think we're looking at about 9 to 10 million barrels a day of global oil shorted,
because a significant part of that is still getting out via land and sea.
But also Iran keeps exporting almost at capacity to China.
But still, it's about 10 million barrels a day.
It's about 10% of global oil demand.
Russia can in no meaningful way replace these cargoes.
John, two quite opposite views there.
What's your take?
Well, my take is that Russia is going to struggle to increase production significantly,
both in short-term and mid-term.
Short-term, I think probably over the next year, it could do another,
probably additional 5%, something like that.
It would then have to drill a lot more wells.
And then you'd be looking maybe at another 5% in a year's time.
So I tend to agree with you that Russia's ability to fill the gap here
is going to be somewhat limited.
And indeed, we've got also the fact, as Maria was saying,
that these export terminals have been damaged recently.
It's difficult to know how long it's going to take to repair those,
but there's certainly going to be some short-term impact.
So I think relying on Russia to be a sort of swing supplier
in these conditions is really rather optimistic.
Yeah, just your take on this.
I mean, the thing is that Russia produces the right kind of oil as well.
And how much of that is the spare capacity?
I'm not sure about whether I can answer this question,
but I would like to stress that since we're talking about the volumes,
I think the strategy at the moment shouldn't be just about the volume,
because economically, I think we, I mean, like Russian producer,
so we don't need to satisfy all the demands.
So I think the key element of this is the economic efficiency of the trade
because the crude and the special Russian crude
is now so because of the spread,
because of the physical markets and future market spread.
So the physical volumes are being traded with the premium now.
And I think Russia could gain and actually sell probably
not too many destinations and not the big volume of crude,
but with a high economic efficiency,
I think getting more commercial value of this.
So I think this is the strategy we should bear in our minds.
John, so let's just turn it this other way.
Is Europe actually reconsidering the use of oil from Russia?
And that would go really against the grain for many countries in Europe.
I'm not including the likes here of, let's say, Hungary.
Well, the European Union is committed to phasing out its
fossil fuel imports from Russia over the next year, 18 months.
Now, this this crisis is certainly,
I think, going to concentrate minds in some European capitals.
The I think probably major attraction
might be to import additional Russian gas.
And Russia has still been exporting gas to Europe
since the start of the war in Ukraine, but much, much reduced volumes.
You know, before the war started,
it was what up as high as, you know, 180 billion cubic meters per year.
And last year, I think it was down to about 18.
So there's been a sort of dramatic change here.
That's that's pipeline gas and still some significant volume
of liquefied natural gas, LNG.
But I suspect that some European countries
are really going to start to feel the pinch next winter
if this crisis persists.
So that question will certainly be opened up again.
But then we come up against the question of how to manage
the this war in Ukraine, how that might be playing out
and whether the perception that contributing more significantly
to Russian budget revenues, just as the time when Ukraine is running short
of money and European countries might be, in fact,
struggling to support Ukraine in the same way is going to create,
I think, a real headache for some European leaders.
Maria, is how much politics is going to play
into what's going on in Europe as they look at Russian oil and gas?
Well, I think John's right that European
quarters overall will not be changing or it doesn't seem to be changing
even under this very real economic pressure.
This is definitely not the same as we are as in close.
There are, of course, some rhetorics, particularly in the in the right
to lean populist parts of of the national party landscape,
especially in Germany, AFDs, of course, as always, pushing for
for strong relations with Russia.
But this is not mainstream within most governments.
Hungary, of course, is an exception as always.
But the shift away from Russian oil and gas is real strategically.
It has been since 2022 and this has remained so.
The Commission says that the remaining roughly 35% of Russian gas
should be out of the European markets in under two years.
And the 2% of Russia's oil exports that are remaining by pipeline
in 2025 should be phased out completely as well.
The it is not just the political rhetorics.
And that is quite clear.
We hear Dan Jorgensen, the head energy head of the European Commission,
saying that what is needs to be in the focus is cushioning the shock
to to the consumers, but as standing by its Russian gas phase
are the European Russian gas phase out target.
But the reality is not just the political.
The reality is also that in terms of
of the legal legal constraints and the market constraints,
it's not that possible for the EU to go back to any considerable
uptake of Russian oil and gas.
There are regulations that both prevent major
every exports or reviving of experts via not stream
because that pipeline has not been unbundled yet.
And it's a whole whole on by gas problem that has been the problem
before it has been put out of commission.
There are market constraints because during the
the restructuring after the Ukraine war,
Europe has already diversified significantly towards Zhebron
and Algeria, Norway and the U.S.
And part of its portfolio is blocked by those suppliers.
So for Russia, there is not that much place to return to anymore.
As John says, there is some maybe short term uptake
you might be saying over the extreme pipeline
because that one the European branch of it is currently underused.
And there is some additional capacity that can be can be used by Russia
if there were demand from the Eastern European countries,
especially in the short term.
LNG picture looks different.
Russia is exporting at capacity from terminals
that are not under heavy sections.
Article in G2 that could bring potential significant capacity
to the market is still very restricted on the sections.
It's exporting just above 10% of its full capacity
and most of it to China.
So there is there is no real sign or no show
of that reality changing in that sense.
I would say European course is not changing so far.
We'll see what happens in the next month or two.
Of course, it all depends on how long the conflict
and the closure is straight up almost persists.
But right now it remains quite firm on phasing out Russian fossil fuels completely.
Fyatyslav, how much does Russia actually need this money, this revenue
and can higher oil prices really ultimately offset reduced export volumes?
I can answer this question on about the budget.
I'm not sure about what I possess the numbers, but I think so.
Again, I think the strategy, the short term strategy
is actually to sell on the higher prices
and to get the most economic values from the operations
or the export operations within this time frame actually.
And so I think budget is getting now much better
because the previous months were quite upset
because of the sanctions and because of the prices,
which were quite low.
Actually, previous, I am talking about the 2025.
But now I think it's getting better and the revenues are coming.
As I said, Russian crude, available, physically available,
is being traded with the premium to the benchmarks.
And that's the good signal for the for the budget.
John, how critical is energy income for funding Ukraine's war plans?
Well, I look at it this way.
Sorry. And indeed, I look at it this way.
The of course, all revenues are a significant part of the the Russian budget.
And the other side is right that in the first quarter of this year,
all revenues were significantly down
on where they'd been in the first quarter of 2025
around from memory around something like 50 percent down.
And this was starting to create a budget crunch.
And the Russian government was seriously discussing
cutting large parts of the budget by 10 percent,
leaving defense spending, social spending unaffected.
So it was clear that this combination of sanctions
and low oil prices were starting to have some real effect
and making it much more uncomfortable to continue fighting the war.
But it has to be said that this war is not hugely expensive for Russia
when we talk about the country being on a war footing
and having a war economy.
I think we have to be have to be careful
because it's not consuming a vast amount of GDP,
whether it's six to eight percent or something like that.
But giving the countries at war,
it this this it is really not a massive investment, as one would expect.
However, of course, the increased oil revenues
are going to reduce the pressure on the budget
generally that's going to make I think the Russian public feel
that the it's not critical to find an immediate end to this war,
the country can go on for a good long while
and certainly the political leadership will see it that way.
But I think there is this the additional benefit here
of the fact that some European countries are going to struggle,
I think, to make the case to their publics
that they need to keep supporting Ukraine at current levels
and possibly going to have to do more for Ukraine,
given that obviously the US is no longer prepared
to provide either economic assistance or military assistance to Ukraine.
So that puts the burden on Europe to procure weaponry for Ukraine
from the United States.
And this is going to, I think, create more of an issue
in some European countries.
And Maria was rightly referring to the rise of the far right
in certain European countries.
And we can hear voices in France and Germany,
critical of this investment in Ukraine's defense.
So I think there is another aspect here for the Russian leadership
that we need to consider that Europe is going to struggle,
at least in the foreseeable future,
to maintain this level of support for Ukraine.
Maria, could one of the things which results from this
that some of these gas fields, in particular,
and perhaps some oil ones which were uneconomic
could become economic if this disruption lasts a long time
and oil and gas prices remain elevated?
Well, this is a good question.
I would be cautious about that because for some time,
and I would defer to Wettoslav, of course,
for a more concrete picture,
but there have not been major oil discoveries in Russia
that can bring some considerable revenue if deployed today.
I think when the Russian oil industry sees that Russia's
oil fields are pretty mature, a lot of them.
And also, given the overall constrained investment climate
and what we should not be forgetting,
the global economy is heading into a macroeconomic crisis.
The investment conditions are very likely to worsen
for every kind of energy, not just including fossil fuels,
of course, including oil and gas.
In that sense, it is quite hard to predict
if there will be any uptick in Russian
additional oil production.
Of course, there are other producers out there
that might benefit from this demand
for non-golf oil and gas.
The gas is probably the biggest winner,
given that they can run up their shell fairly quickly
and it responds to higher prices.
And then there are some Atlantic or some some producers
across the Atlantic, outside of the gas,
including Brazil, Vienna and Canada,
that might be able to pump a little bit more
if they fast-track the projects
that have not been approved.
They are in the approval process already,
but there is really not that much spare capacity
that can be boosted in the near or mid-term
and the investment climate
and the overall demand projection
for global oil and gas demand
is really not that rosy for some major
very capital intensive investment decisions
to be taken on new exploration or in new fields.
In that sense, I think my answer would be rather no.
OK, I mean, that to you now,
Viacheslav here as well,
can some un-economic fields become now profitable
and sustainable?
But of course, this is going to be contingent
on how long prices do remain high.
Yes, but I would like to reverse a little bit
the situation because the market is first.
I know that in the US and in Russia,
nobody wants to invest massively
just because of the situation.
So I think we should look at the medium
and long-term actually market movements.
And I think this is short-term situation
doesn't give any signal to the investors
and to the upstream sector.
But since the situation will be going that way,
and of course it depends on how strong
will be the damage on the Gulf production
and the next period after the war,
I think then the signal will come there
and I think we could expect some investment decisions
actually not only in Russia,
but in general in the upstream sector.
And of course it needs to actually to agree with the buyers.
So on the long-term relations,
because since we are talking about the crisis
and the situation now,
it's just brief and quite momentum.
And this is a spot mark in general.
But since we're talking about long-term cooperation,
I think the investments are there,
but they should be based on the contracting
and on the long-term contract agreements.
Absolutely. And if you look at the futures curve,
you see prices much, much lower actually as well.
But John, I want to get your take on this as well.
If the war was to come to an end tomorrow,
what would that mean for prices?
And would they go down really quickly?
Or given that Russia still has problems,
it still has not reached its capacity
and it's refineries are being bombed by the Ukrainians.
And would high prices be elevated for quite a while from now on?
Well, my understanding is that if the war were to end tomorrow,
it would take probably up to 10 months
for markets to stabilize in other words,
for supplies to be rerouted
and for, if you like,
the sort of previous arrangements to recommence.
So that is a long period.
So during that time,
we would probably expect to see prices relatively elevated
and that would be advantageous to Russia
because the problem is,
and we had to consider the fact
that if prices were to go excessively high,
let's say, I didn't know $150,
then we would probably see
some fairly dramatic destruction of demand.
And that then reduces the opportunity
for producers such as Russia
to benefit from increased prices.
So there is some sort of balance here,
I think, to be achieved if Russia and others
want to gain from this current disruption.
But the signals so far are that there is no easy way
for the United States to exit this situation in Iran
that nobody has any sort of solution
for how to deal with the straight-up hormones
other than perhaps persuading the Iranians
that it will be a good idea
to actually revert to previous arrangements.
But who's going to do that?
Is it going to be the Chinese?
because it really doesn't look feasible
to open the straight by military means.
John Loh, thank you so much.
Viachesav Michenko and Maria Plashtukova.
Thank you so much for joining us.
And that is our show.
Get in touch with us on X at Richard TV
and do use the hashtag AJCTC when you do.
Or drop us an email.
Counting the cost at aljazeera.net is our address.
But there is more for you online at aljazeera.com
slash CTC.
That'll take you straight to our page,
which has individual reports, links,
and entire episodes for you to catch up on.
That is it for this edition of Counting the Cost.
I'm Rashad Salamat from the whole team in Doha.
Thank you for joining us.
Aljazeera's coverage of the war in the Middle East
continues in just a moment.
As the war on Iran escalates,
Aljazeera's correspondents are on the ground.
This is the first time that President Trump
has spoken publicly live.
We projected four to five weeks.
All the while insisting that the United States
has plenty of weapons left.
We have only just begun.
Still, he's not ruling out,
sending US troops into Iran.
We expect to take additional losses.
Today, we grieve for the four heroic American service
members who have been killed in action.
That is a price Americans say they do not want repeated.
Stay with Aljazeera for the latest developments.
We saw this exact same pattern happen in Gaza.
The same lazy, flattened reporting that we saw in Gaza
when it comes to the war on Iran.
The listening post decodes the media on Aljazeera.
Sprawling across 2,600 hectares that Angotiri finaries
build to help end Nigeria's reliance on imported fuel.
But today, this 650,000 barrel per day giant
is being asked to do much more.
Shipping disruptions caused by the war in Iran
has throttled nearly a fifth of the world's energy flow.
With Middle Eastern supplies diverted or delayed,
Africa is feeling the squeeze
and looking for a lifeline closer to home.
The Angotiri finary here in Leci
has become a vital strategic shield for Nigeria
and many other countries.
The 650,000 barrel a day facility
provides steady supply of fuel as international markets
grapple with depleted inventories.
Low domestic crude production means
the refinery is often starved of the very oil
sitting beneath Nigerian soil,
forcing the plant to look abroad for raw materials.
For now, the race is on to see if African production
can outrun a global energy crisis.
Hello, this is Aljazeera, live from Doha
with our continuing coverage of the war
between the US, Israel, and Iran.
I'm Cyril Vanier, coming up in the program this hour.
Overnight, US and Israeli strikes on Iran
kill at least 34 people.
A top university is among those targets.
Donald Trump sets a Tuesday deadline for Iran
to reopen the Strait of Hormuz
and says that he will, quote,
unleash hell if they don't.
Iran carries out strikes in Israel,
killing two people in the city of Haifa
and causing extensive damage around Tel Aviv.
And Israeli attacks across Lebanon,
one strike hits a residential building in Beirut,
killing at least three people there.
The Artemis II mission enters the final phase
of its journey, preparing to loop around
the far side of the moon.
The US and Israel have stepped up their attacks on Iran.
At least 34 people have been killed in overnight strikes.
Several areas have been targeted.
That includes a university in Tehran
and an airport in the southwestern part of the country.
And the Revolutionary Guard Corps has also announced
that the head of its intelligence organization
has been killed.
We'll talk about that in a moment.
Iran has continued its retaliatory strikes,
firing missiles across Israel.
At least two people have been killed in the city of Haifa.
Attacks also caused extensive damage in and around Tel Aviv.
And US President Donald Trump has again threatened
to destroy Iranian power plants and bridges
if it doesn't reopen the Strait of Hormuz by Tuesday.
Iran has said that it will retaliate
to any strikes on its infrastructure.
It says any sites in the region connected to the US
will be a target.
We're live in Ramallah.
That's in the occupied West Bank.
We're live in Kuwait City.
We're also live in the Iranian capital, Tehran.
And Tohid Asadi joins us from there.
Tohid, so the IRGC, the Iranian Revolutionary Guard Corps
have confirmed that the head of their intelligence unit
has been killed.
What can you tell us about that?
Well, actually, over the past 24 hours
and overnight, specifically,
Tehran has been witnessing the continuation
of the air strikes across the country.
And the latest came a few minutes ago from IRGC
coming out in a statement to say that Majid Khatami,
the head of IRGC's intelligence organization,
was killed in the attacks earlier this morning.
And obviously, this is going to be another major blow
to the security apparatus of the country.
We know that his role is critically important
in this apparatus.
And we know that earlier,
that the minister for intelligence of the country
was killed alongside many other top military
and intelligence and security officials
as a result of the air strikes
by the Americans and the Israelis.
But we know that this is not the only attack
across the capital.
Sharif University of Technology,
which is known as Iran's MIT,
one of the most important, actually,
technical universities of the country,
was also targeted.
The damage to the campus is quite visible
based on the footages that we have been receiving.
And obviously, that doesn't stop in the capital
which witnessed extensive damages
as a result of these air strikes.
But we have a relatively longer list of different cities
across the Iranian territories,
including Karaj, Shiraz, Isfahan, Boucher,
Bandar-e-Lenge, in which at least six people were killed,
Qom, where five people were killed,
the Baharistan located in the vicinity of Tehran,
a small city in which 13 people,
according to the local authorities,
were killed among whom we can say
at least six were children.
And obviously, we are dealing with a more extensive
scope of damages when it comes to Iran's infrastructure
coming within the context of new threats
directed by the U.S. President Donald Trump
about more tax infrastructure
on the infrastructure of the country.
Tahir, what can you tell us about communications
at the moment between Iran and the U.S.?
And we understand those communications to be indirect,
but all of this is happening
as Donald Trump has given Iran two days
to reopen the Strait of Hormuz
or face bombing, major bombing on its bridges
and its power plants.
Within that context, where do communications stand?
Time and again, we hear from the Iranian side
that direct negotiation with the United States
is off the table.
The message we hear from Tehran is that of defiance,
deterrence, resilience,
and obviously retaliation against actually
the attacks that the country is facing,
even though when it comes to communications,
we heard from the spokesperson for the Ministry
of Foreign Affairs, Ismail Baghaed, the other day,
talking about mediated communication.
And we know that so far at least one proposal
has been delivered to Iran, the 15 point.
Also, there are some media reports
about another one being delivered to Iran,
even though on that,
we don't have any official confirmation from Tehran.
It's still there saying that mediated communication,
as well as regional and global interaction
in terms of diplomacy, is at work.
Foreign Minister Arajci has held many different
actually phone conversations with his counterparts
across the region and beyond to, in a sense,
talk about the latest developments,
some of them perhaps intended to de-escalate the situation.
However, it goes without saying that the rhetoric
we hear from both sides or three sides,
I may say Tel Aviv, Washington on the one hand
and Tehran on the other,
is far from any point of de-escalation
at this certain point as the air strikes
by the Americans and Israelis continue
as the scope has been extended.
On the one hand, and on the other,
Iran is talking about the continuation
of their retaliatory strikes.
They're saying that there's going to be
a tit for tat strategy for these strikes,
U.S. assets across the region, infrastructure,
providing support to U.S. assets
across the region, including U.S. bases,
as well as the Israeli territories
are said to be the targets of Iran's retaliatory actions,
retaliatory strikes.
It just, they're also, they're saying
that they're going to continue to make sure
that the security of the country
is guaranteed for a long time.
Tahir Asadi reporting from Tehran.
Thank you very much.
At least two people have been killed
in an Iranian strike on a building
in the city of Haifa,
that's according to Israeli media.
The residential structure partially collapsed
after the attack on Sunday.
At least four others have been wounded.
Al Jazeera's Nida Ibrahim is following those developments
in Israel from Ramallah in the occupied West Bank.
So Nida, after five weeks of war,
can you give us an overall brief
of how much damage Iran has actually done in Israel?
Well, more than the damage that Iran's missiles
have caused to the buildings, to the infrastructure,
it also affected the morale of the Israelis
who after five weeks are asking
how long will this war continue?
As Iran keeps firing these cluster ammunition warheads
that continue to splinter and detonate in several areas
causing major damage.
Now, according to the Israeli ambulance service,
we are talking about at least 8,900 people
who have gone to hospitals
as a result of these strikes.
Now, yes, a very limited fraction
of those still remain in hospitals.
We talk about major cases being hit
with panic attacks, with psychological distress
or sometimes with stones from the shockwaves of these attacks.
But still that continues to disrupt life in Israel.
Also, we are talking about these attacks
happening sometimes in coordination between Hezbollah
and Iran, targeting several areas
in the Israeli geography or a same area twice
at the same time in a way that they want
to overwhelm the aerial defense systems.
And also these defense systems have failed
at times to intercept such missiles
like what happened yesterday,
like what happened at Haifa yesterday,
and also a rocket from Hezbollah
being fired into another Israel as well.
These questions that Israelis are asking now,
they want to know if their government
is correctly handling this war specifically.
We are talking about closure of educational facilities.
These, some classrooms have been hit
according to the Israeli estimates.
We are talking about the disrupted flight system
that where many Israelis cannot travel.
So wherever you look, you see this war affecting life
in Israel with no clear end inside
while the politicians at the same time
are still interested in maintaining this world
a bit longer.
Nida, you told us earlier that at the start of the war
there was overwhelming public support for the war in Israel
to the tune of about 80% of Israelis
who supported this war effort against Iran.
But now five weeks in
and people are still living under constant threat.
You told us about the school closures.
You told us about people going in the bunkers
and needing to shelter on a regular basis.
Is it possible to assess how much patience
Israelis still have for this war?
Also, all that patience is definitely being tested
not just by the continuation of the war
but the nature of the missiles being fired into Israel.
Now we are talking about a prime minister
who promised to change the regime,
to topple it in the beginning of the war.
But now he's saying, you know what?
Maybe we managed to limit Iran's existential threat
against us but not really stop
all of its ballistic missiles being sent our way.
This is not a good answer for Israelis
who have been tolerating this war,
tolerating this pain because they believe
that that will lead to better results later.
But now they are questioning their government's ability
to run this war effectively.
And there are those who are questioning,
are we waging a war because Netanyahu
wants to avoid corruption trials?
Are we doing that because he wants to win
the elections later this year?
These questions are testing what we've been reporting
in the past of 80% support of the war amongst Israelis,
a highly militarized society,
a society that has always seen Iran as a threat.
But now they're saying that maybe the government
is not achieving the war goals it's promised its people to.
And at the same time, they are questioning
whether Netanyahu is doing it
for his own political agenda.
So that test, that number is diminishing
the support of the war, we can see it.
And we've seen people taking to the streets of Tel Aviv
requiring and calling and demanding an end of this war.
Of course, for the political leadership, for the army,
they still have more time to go.
And there's also this interest in separating
between the front with Iran and the front with Hezbollah
as the army says, even if the war with Iran stops,
they will continue their battle against Hezbollah.
You know, Abraham reporting from Ramallah.
Thank you very much, Nitta.
And the threat of escalation in Iran
has put the Gulf region directly in the line of fire.
Health authorities in Kuwait report
that six people have been injured
after debris from a missile landed in a residential area.
Al Jazeera's Malik Trena is in Kuwait city.
Malik, you're monitoring developments
across the region.
Kuwait has been particularly hard.
It was yesterday, but it's also,
as we just reported today, what are you seeing?
Yeah, that's right.
Well, throughout the night and this morning,
the alarm sounded here in Kuwait three times.
We now know from the Ministry of Health
that those people were injured
in the northern part of the country
in a residential area.
The ministry is now saying that they've all been treated
and are doing very well now.
But we've also seen attacks across the region.
In the UAE, one person was injured
in an attack in the industrial city of Abu Dhabi.
He was a Ghanaian national
from debris from an interception.
You know, what we've learned now
is that the debris from these successful interceptions
can be dangerous and sometimes quite deadly.
In Saudi Arabia, the Ministry of Defense saying...
24 hours on, what's the damage assessment
from those attacks?
Well, according to what we understand,
there are still some of these fires
that are ongoing with civil defense teams
trying to put them out.
Some of the fires,
including the finance ministry building
and the oil complex,
those fires, the authorities said, were put out.
But numerous fires.
I'm talking about several different locations.
The petrol chemical company, also oil facilities.
Several fires were put out there.
Some operational units were taken offline.
You talked about the water and powered infrastructure here.
The Ezur water plant,
which is one of the places that was targeted.
It's one of the biggest desalination plants
in the entire Middle East.
You know, water infrastructure,
extremely important in the Gulf,
but here in Kuwait,
eight desalination plants accumulate
for more than 90% of the drinking water.
So, you know, for officials here,
that's a red line that continuously is being crossed.
This was the fourth time
that a desalination plant was hit here in Kuwait.
And what we've seen in the last couple of days
is that these Iranian drones
have been able to get through
the Kuwaiti air defense system.
So, as this looming deadline
that's been imposed by Donald Trump,
you know, we edge closer and closer,
people here have become extremely concerned.
I think, you know,
for Gulf officials across the region,
you know, people are trying,
officials want to de-escalate the situation.
We heard from the Omanians yesterday
that they're in talks with the Iranians
to come up with some kind of mechanism
to ensure passage through the Strait of Hormuz.
I think what officials here in the Gulf
will try to relate to President Trump is,
look, the Iranians are playing ball.
They're trying to negotiate.
Let's de-escalate the situation.
Let's move this deadline
so we can find a diplomatic path,
a solution that will bring long-term stability
here in this entire region.
Malik Trena reporting from Kuwait City.
Thank you very much, Malik.
And US President Donald Trump
has been giving Iran shifting deadlines
to reopen the Strait of Hormuz.
That is as Iran insists
that the key waterway isn't actually closed
and that only ships that belong to its enemies
are barred from passage.
Trump issued his first ultimatum on March 21st.
He threatened at the time to bomb Iran's power plants
if the Strait wasn't reopened within 48 hours,
but he later extended that deadline by five days,
claiming that negotiations were underway
and were going well.
Trump issued a new deadline on March 26th
that that time he gave Iran 10 days
or until the evening of April 6th to reopen the Strait.
Trump issued his latest Hormuz threat on Sunday.
That's yesterday,
after vowing to bomb power plants and bridges
if Tehran doesn't comply.
He posted what appears to be
a Tuesday 8 p.m. Eastern, that's US time,
8 p.m. Eastern deadline for a deal.
So that brings us to Wednesday
in the early hours of Wednesday morning,
Iran time for that to happen.
I'm joined in the studio by Mohammed al-Mastri,
professor of media studies at the Doha Institute
for Graduate Studies and in Moruya in Australia.
We are joined by Michael Shubridge,
director of strategic analysis Australia,
a defense and security think tank.
Gentlemen, thank you for joining us
from Australia in the studio.
Really the big question I think that is animating
all of us, certainly all the people
who live in the region, but far beyond as well.
point is, can this threat by Donald Trump actually change anything?
Is it conceivable that what hasn't worked for five weeks, this massive U.S. military
pressure on Iran and bombing campaign, hasn't worked for five weeks?
We were talking about that with Michael earlier.
Is it possible that if you escalate it, bomb the power plants, bomb the bridges, then
it can work?
Michael?
Cyril, I don't think so.
I think Donald Trump is having a hard time understanding that Iran is not working to his timeline.
He's used to business deals and threatening people to get a better deal.
This is a different problem.
So no, I don't think more threats will change things.
My real concern is this is going to lead to an escalation of the war and cause much
broader damage across the Gulf and in Iran.
I agree.
I agree with Michael.
I think if anything, it could have the opposite effect.
We're in effectively what Professor Robert Pape has been calling the escalation trap.
So when Trump, if Trump escalates, then it will kind of force the hand of the Iranians
to escalate themselves and then we end up in this perpetual cycle.
So no, I don't think that this is likely to yield the kind of result that Trump wants.
Now I think what Michael said at the end there of his comment is important about the
Gulf because this is dangerous not just for Iran and for Iranians.
Obviously the consequences could be catastrophic for people in Iran if Donald Trump carries
out his threat, but I think also for people in the Gulf because Iran has promised this
kind of tit for tat response and we're getting reports that there have been some, and I just
want to emphasize some attacks from some, perhaps Gulf countries, U.S. attacks on Iran that
is from these bases.
France 24 was able to verify footage yesterday showing missile attacks from Kuwait.
You all were just covering reporting from Kuwait City.
So that could explain why Kuwait has come under heavier fire over the past two or three weeks.
And again, Iran has promised to basically make the response very costly for the Gulf if
Donald Trump does what he promises to do.
Michael, off the back of mom's point there, do you see the Gulf countries or the Gulf
regions military posture changing?
Most of them have been playing defense for now.
Do you see them going on the offense if Iran's attacks continue?
That's a possibility, but I don't think it's likely because I don't think that putting
more bombs and missiles into Iran is going to change things.
That's the problem with the Israeli and American.
The Gulf states know that if the Americans in Israelis start broadly targeting
civilian infrastructure inside Iran, Iran will start broadly targeting civilian
infrastructure across the Gulf and in Israel, and air defenses are already
struggling to defend against more limited attacks.
So I don't think the Gulf states want to see this next escalatory step.
So you believe Iran has the ability to step up its attacks then because I had a
guest yesterday tell me, and this was from the Gulf region, tell me that
actually they're not really afraid of escalation from Iran because they didn't
feel that Iran had the ability to do more than it's already doing.
Well, I think that makes a mistake about the breadth of targeting.
So if Iran fires the number of missiles and drones, it seems to be
capable of, but broadens their targets to a much wider set of civilian targets,
then the defense problem, the air and missile defense problem becomes much
more difficult and more drones and missiles will get through and strike
more targets in the Gulf.
Mohamed, since you're a professor of media studies, in addition to being
a commentator on regional politics, what is the perception through the
lens of the media in the U.S. and Israel on how they're doing five weeks in?
Well, in the United States, the the perception is pretty negative.
Actually, the opinion polling data continue to be continued to be negative.
So if you look at this Fox News poll, which already tends to be there,
there tends to be a slight right leaning sampling bias on Fox News polls.
But they found that 64 percent of respondents believe
that Donald Trump is mishandling the war.
So that's that's quite that's quite significant.
A majority of Americans continue to be opposed to the war,
to be opposed even to the decision to go to war.
The vast majority of Americans are opposed to the idea of ground troops.
So Donald Trump's messaging hasn't hasn't really worked.
And so it is it is largely negative.
It's becoming more negative in Israel, but it's still not negative on the whole.
The support has dropped from roughly 95 percent to the low 70s in recent weeks.
And I think still strong support.
Still strong support.
And but the longer the war goes on, the the the more unpopular it will become.
Could I just say something about this?
This this idea of Iran perhaps not being able to continue
the war, step up its attack, step up its attack.
So CNN did an interesting investigation last week, and they found that
and they were consulting with US intelligence officials who spoke to them off the record.
But Iran still maintains half of its missile launchers.
And it is believed that they still have quite a stockpile of of missiles
and thousands of drones.
And it's also believed that they are continuing to
manufacture drones and and missiles at a
slower pace. But but it is quite likely, I mean to say,
it is quite likely that Iran could could carry this on for for many months.
That's something that Michael and I were addressing a little earlier.
I've got more questions for you on that, Michael, but I have to run for now.
But we'll speak again.
Thank you very much, gentlemen.
Michael Shubridge and Muhammad al-Masri for joining us this hour.
Thanks.
And details are emerging of the rescue of a US airman from Iran
after an intense 48 hour search operation.
The weapons systems officer had been missing since Friday
when the fighter jet that he was in was shot down over a remote area in southern Iran.
Al Jazeera's John Hendron reports from Washington, D.C.
It was a daring and risky mission to save an American airman
from becoming an Iranian prisoner of war.
Iranian forces search the mountainous areas of southwestern Iran
after an F-15E fighter jet went down on Friday.
It was the first time a U.S.
aircraft had crashed in hostile territory in the five-week old war.
Two Black Hawk helicopters took fire as U.S.
teams raced to find the missing crew member.
An A-10 Warthog, an air support aircraft, was also damaged,
its pilot ejecting over the Gulf.
Iran broadcast photos of what it said was debris from the fighter jet,
including a jump seat.
Although the pilot had been rescued on Friday,
the weapon specialist remained in hiding, evading Iranian forces for two days.
Finally, early on Sunday, deep in Iranian territory,
the U.S. search operation was successful.
President Donald Trump made the announcement on social media,
posting, we got him, saying the Colonel had been behind enemy lines
in the treacherous mountains of Iran being hunted by our enemies.
He said U.S. forces had been monitoring his location 24 hours a day
and sent dozens of aircraft armed with the most lethal weapons in the world
to retrieve him.
Trump added he sustained injuries, but he will be just fine.
A U.S. official told Al Jazeera the rescue operation began in darkness
but ended in an intense firefight and daylight
before dozens of heavily armed aircraft and hundreds of troops
transported the airmen out of Iran.
A U.S. officer in Iranian custody could have given Iran leverage,
as it had when Iran took U.S. hostages in 1979.
With that crisis averted, attention now shifts to the U.S.
deadline for Iran to open the Strait of Hormuz.
John Hendrin, Al Jazeera, Washington.
And Israel has carried out multiple strikes across southern Lebanon
and the capital Beirut, causing widespread damage and death.
Israeli military attacks targeted multiple areas in the Nabatae district
in the south. What you're seeing right now, actually,
are live pictures, the aftermath of a strike that just occurred,
again, in the Lebanese capital Beirut.
So at least four people were killed in a drone strike targeting a car.
That was the previous strike.
And in a separate attack in the same area, one person was killed.
Al Jazeera, Zayna Hodor, is in Beirut with the latest.
Civilians are increasingly being caught up in this conflict.
The attack in Beirut on Sunday, there were two.
One in the district of Jnech, five people were killed,
three Sudanese nationals, a 15 year old child
and the apparent target, a Hezbollah military commander.
So even in the so-called targeted assassination,
civilians are being killed.
In another strike in Beirut last night in Ain Saadi,
that's a district north of Beirut, three people were killed.
The missile targeted the third floor of the building
and these civilians were on the second floor of the building.
The Lebanese health ministry saying that 1,461 people have been killed,
4,000 people wounded.
That doesn't include the latest casualties this morning in Mashkara.
That's in West Bikar, three people killed.
In Farouman, a car was hit.
That's in the Nabati district in south Lebanon, four people killed.
There was another strike in Nabati, another person killed.
So, you know, the death toll keeps climbing.
And this conflict is in its sixth week.
The Lebanese health ministry, in its figures,
it doesn't differentiate between combatants and civilians.
But if you count the number of women, children, paramedics,
that's roughly 25 percent.
So there is increasing concern as this conflict really has no red line,
even though Israel may want to, you know, target a specific Hezbollah member.
You know, it doesn't really matter if that member is an intensely populated area.
The Iran War is piling pressure on Sri Lanka's fragile economy,
still recovering from its financial crisis of four years ago.
Fuel prices have surged, with petrol and diesel now being rationed.
As Menel Fernandez reports from Colombo, many people are struggling to cope.
Lasseth Gyan has worked for a food delivery company in Colombo for four years.
The 39-year-old's income depends on the number of deliveries he makes.
But restrictions on fuel and price increases caused by the Iran War
have affected his earnings.
I make around $20 a day, but I have to buy all my meals.
That costs more than $5 a day.
I use what's left for fuel, rent and to send home to my family.
Restaurants like this, where Gyan is picking up his first order for the day,
are also struggling.
Gas for cooking is more expensive.
And manager Suranga Thirunagama says good quality ingredients are difficult to find.
This has forced many outlets to increase their prices.
Something Thirunagama says he's trying to avoid.
We're trying our best to manage without raising prices,
but it's getting more challenging day by day
because today's prices are not the same tomorrow.
We can't budget. Prices are increasing.
And it's already evident, Gyan says he's delivering few orders these days.
Many people we spoke to told us the worst part is the uncertainty.
On the way to his next pickup, Gyan fills up.
The government has imposed fuel restrictions.
Motorbike riders get a weekly quota of 8 litres.
Half the fuel Gyan says he usually goes through.
Station owner Sampat Kotalavala is also dealing with uncertainty.
We only receive about 50% of the supplies we order.
And we manage these stocks according to the framework the government has given us.
It's not enough for some, but generally it's okay.
But that's for today. I can't say what tomorrow will be like.
There are other pressures too.
A long-pending electricity price increase took effect this month,
with some bills set to go up by 25%.
The government has asked people to use power sparingly.
Ironing and washing clothes only once a week.
And government officers have been told to switch off air conditioners early.
Gyan says Sri Lanka is recovering from its worst economic crisis.
The Iran war is causing more uncertainty.
People are paying more for fuel, food and even public transport,
as a conflict thousands of kilometres away, since prices soaring.
On the road, Gyan has stopped for a cup of tea and a snack
that's costing him more now than it did two weeks ago.
But he must hurry because the next order is waiting.
Minal Fernandez, Al Jazeera, Colombo.
At least 41 miners are trapped underground
after an attack on a coal mine in the Russian-controlled Luhansk.
A Russian-appointed official in the region says Ukraine was behind the strike
and that a power substation was damaged.
Emergency crews are working to rescue the miners and restore power to that site.
Four astronauts are hours away from becoming the first people
to see the dark side of the moon.
The Artemis II mission crew has entered the final phase of its journey,
preparing to loop around the far side of the moon.
At this point, the moon's gravity has a stronger pull on their capsule than Earth's.
They will lose communications for about 40 minutes while passing behind the moon,
where they are also expected to witness a solar eclipse.
Our coverage of the war between the U.S., Israel and Iran continues
after the listening post. Stay with Al Jazeera.
The United States military began major combat operations in Iran.
We are not joined by the U.S. and Israeli offensive scruples.
The position of the Spanish government can be summed up in four words.
No to the war.
I have condemned the massive military strikes by the United States and Israel.
And I also condemn the subsequent attacks by Iran.
The attacks on energy capacity that has happened on both sides
is a dangerous precedent that will cause repercussions throughout the world.
We can now see a regional conflict with unintended consequences.
Stay with us for the latest developments on Al Jazeera.
President Trump launched the war in Iran a month ago,
but does he know how to end it?
Now European leaders say they'll help Trump on the Strait of Hormuz,
but how much damage will be done to U.S.-European relations
long after Trump's epic fury subsides?
Your weekly take on U.S. politics, the bottom line.
This week, our coverage of the war on Iran
starts with the media story coming out of Israel.
Citizens there are not getting the full picture.
Military censors are filtering what they see.
Israel is growing more oppressive,
whether it's free speech or a new law that could sentence Palestinians
to death by execution, translating propaganda and exporting it online.
Israel in Persian is the name of the account
and it's being used to target Iranians, plus the Iranian countermeasures.
They include an internet blackout.
This is a way for them to show the populace that they are in control
and exporting their own content, including AI in the battle over hearts and minds.
The fog of war created by the U.S.-Israeli attack on Iran is not lifting, it is thickening.
Mixed messages keep coming out of Washington, rehashed by the day,
it seems, generating more confusion than clarity.
In Israel, the gap between political rhetoric
and the on-the-ground reality has been widening.
The Netanyahu government's prediction of a quick war
to topple Iran's leadership and destroy its nuclear program
has given way to a reality that is far messier
and much more dangerous for Israeli civilians.
Complicating matters further still is what Israelis are allowed to see of this war.
That is being tightly controlled.
Journalists face unprecedented levels of military censorship
while being urged to raise morale rather than just report the facts.
And Israelis who do push back against the war
or against a controversial new law legalizing the death penalty
but only against Palestinians know that the authorities are out to repress them,
if not silenced.
Benjamin Netanyahu wouldn't put it this way,
but five weeks into the U.S.-Israeli war against Iran,
this is what he's up against domestically.
Iranian missiles keep hitting Israeli targets,
causing casualties and severely injuring the country's infrastructure.
The collapse that Israel was hoping for of the Iranian government,
the galvanizing of rebellion there, has not happened.
Given the multiple fronts and entanglements,
Lebanon, the West Bank, Gaza,
and the unprecedented number of reservists called up,
Israel risks running out of soldiers.
And like his ally, Donald Trump,
Netanyahu has no clear exit strategy.
What he can be countered on, however, at times like these,
is having a media strategy, scapegoating his crates.
In the theatrics that Netanyahu sometimes indulges in,
he says, what are you doing in the TV studios?
Why are you sapping the morale of the public?
Why are you helping the enemy, not our own people?
And that's Netanyahu calling out the media for two and a half years.
You've done the job designated to you
of being a fully mobilized machine to create consensus for genocide.
And now to make sure this war can continue indefinitely.
And those are your marching orders and go back to them.
Those orders in their most specific form
come from Israel's military censors.
In the war, we're Israelis, before we're refugees, right?
But what happens when refugees come to the censor?
He says, no, no.
whether the country is at war or not.
But reporters and citizens alike say they have never seen censorship to this extent, where
it can inadvertently put the citizens the censors are supposed to protect at greater risk.
Nader Gontar's works for the Israeli newspaper Haaretz.
After a military base was hit by an Iranian missile, he went on X, saying, it's nice
that they put up warning signs about the asbestos, scattered from the military base
throughout the neighborhood following the strike.
But no government official explained what the implications and dangers are, what the kids
are breathing, while the soldiers on the base walk around in protective suits and masks.
Tightly controlled images and carefully shaped narratives from Israel, AI material on social
media designed to exaggerate Iran's military prowess.
Combined with videos first posted weeks ago of missile strikes on Israeli targets, then
reposted and presented as new, have caused all kinds of confusion.
With mainstream outlets under the thumb of the censors, Israelis are scouring sources
online where it is increasingly difficult to separate fact from fiction, reality from
propaganda.
The image that you see out of Israel is very carefully choreographed.
This is a country self-professed as a democracy, but it has a military sensor that can and
does control the kind of information that can be used or disseminated by the media.
But in this war, the kind of restrictions that have been imposed are unprecedented.
The only thing you see are damage to civilian areas and so on.
You know that you're not getting the full picture and that in itself tells you that
it's something that the state doesn't want you to know about.
They are definitely trying to portray an Israel that is much more capable of defending itself
than it actually is and is implying that Iran knows less about the country's infrastructure
and sensitive sites than it does.
There is a reason why only after the fact when Israeli officials are on the scene
are news crews able to film exact locations of strike sites and why most of these videos
of sensitive sites being bombed are oftentimes by anonymous people, not journalists on the
ground.
Although the percentage has fallen slightly from roughly 90% down to 80, an overwhelming
majority of Jewish Israelis still support this war.
The authorities are out to keep it that way, cracking down on the relatively small
anti-war protests on the streets.
This protest says she was roughed up just for being there.
Another demonstration called after Israel's parliament passed a new capital punishment
law applicable only to Palestinians got similar treatment.
Protesters rounded up, journalists hit by water cannons.
For the security minister who championed the law, Itamar Ben Gavir, its passage was
a champagne moment worth savoring.
For this popular and sometimes depraved Israeli TV comedy show, the prospect of executing
Palestinians was played for laughs.
So what did you start to do to protect the human form, let's say, because my name is
also a massage?
The law essentially forces the death penalty on Palestinian prisoners who are convicted
of terrorism offenses.
But even within opposition to this law, it was on the basis that it would threaten
potential future Israeli hostages, not the crime of mass executing by hanging Palestinian
detainees.
So it's a problem of process, not of moral depravity.
And this was an extremely popular bill amongst the Israeli public.
I went to the protest in Tel Aviv and the security forces were very quick to crack
down.
I'm a journalist.
I'm filming and they took a clearly aggressive position.
The death penalty.
Some people say, well, there will be challenges that will never really be implemented even
if it is passed.
I don't think it matters.
These are signposts of where a country is going and it is not a good direction.
With news feeds still dominated by Iran's blocking of the Strait of Hormuz, the Israeli
occupation of south Lebanon, the missiles still landing in Israel and Iran, the typically
scant coverage of Israeli settler violence in the West Bank has all but evaporated.
When the West Bank story does get reported in Israel, the settlers are usually described
as rogue operators separate from the state and the army that supports them.
This week, an American news crew from CNN was confronted by Israeli soldiers in the
West Bank, their guns pointed at the journalists, one of whom was put in a chokehold.
That story made news even in Israel, not because it happened, but because of who it
happened to.
It's rare to hear these soldiers speak so openly, especially to foreign media.
They believe that all of the West Bank is Israel's land, that it is Jewish territory
only.
I watched that report from our colleagues at CNN and I would never dare do what he did
because had this crew not been an American crew, things would have turned out very different.
Many of our colleagues were beaten to a pulp in similar situations because they were
Palestinian.
But Israelis don't hear and don't see what happens to Palestinians in the occupied
West Bank.
And at this point, most of them don't care.
They want to try to show that they are doing something about Israeli perpetrators committing
terrorist attacks in the West Bank, to show the White House primarily that they're doing
something.
But it's really the system of settlement expansion, annexation.
Many Israelis will say, oh yes, it's terrible.
These very few people, a handful of bad eggs.
And what the settler leaders say is that many of them are not even from the settlements,
they're troubled youth, that they give the entire settlement project a bad name.
We better crack down on them so that we can continue expanding the settlement project.
That's what they say very openly.
Israel is in an impunity-fuelled march towards seeing how far it can go to impose
its domination, the largest military operations in the West Bank in half a century, seizing
more territory in Lebanon, still holding 60% of Gaza.
That continues as long as Israel can get away with it.
But it only actually becomes overreach when blowback arrives.
When something holds Israel to account diplomatically or on the battlefield.
And unless that moment comes, I don't expect the Israeli side to recognize how far out
of its depth this may take it.
Staying with Israel and the propaganda it has directed at Iranians in their native tongue.
This is a playbook we've seen before with Palestinians, Tarek Nafa is here with more.
Since the start of the war on Iran, one of the most active platforms for messaging
aimed at Iranians has been Israel in Persian, the Israeli government's official Farsi
language account on X.
It's posted a steady stream of content mocking Iran's leaders, framing them as the drivers
of this conflict and trying to position Israel as a friend of Iranians.
This week the account posted this video ridiculing a woman whose home had just been
destroyed in an airstrike because she was holding a nice handbag.
There are also these posts which suggested scenes of destruction in Tehran had been
fabricated by the Iranian government using a paid actor.
These claims have been thoroughly debunked by fact checkers, but that hasn't stopped
this narrative that the Iranians are faking it from spreading, including by voices in
the Iranian diaspora who are supportive of the Israeli-U.S. war.
Casting doubt on victims questioning their legitimacy, these are tactics that the
Israelis have used before on Palestinians, summed up in terms like Pollywood that
suggests Palestinians have staged their own suffering.
Another Farsi language account is operated by Mossad, Israel's Foreign Intelligence Agency.
It is being used to openly try and recruit Iranians as spies.
Just as it has done elsewhere in the region in Arabic, Israel's use of Farsi
is designed to whitewash its image and shape public opinion, leaving Iranians with the
realization that even their online spaces have been infiltrated.
Thanks Tarek.
Turning now to the counter-narrative, the one that's coming out of Tehran.
Officials there have been framing their case to international audiences, tailoring their
language and ideas accordingly while accusing Western media outlets of distorting the
facts of this war.
Inside Iran, a sweeping internet blackout remains in place severely limiting what people
can see and share.
And a new front has been opened, shaped by some increasingly sophisticated AI content, further
blurring the line between information and the truth.
To help us understand the strategy behind all of this, we're joined now from Washington
by the Executive Vice President of the Quincy Institute for Responsible Statecraft,
Trita Parsi.
Mr. Parsi, let's start with this.
This past week, Iran's President, Masoud Pazeshkian, addressed an open letter to the American people,
urging them to look beyond what he called a machinery of misinformation in the US.
What are the chances of a message like that actually cutting through, given the current
media environment in America?
I find the likelihood of that message getting through to be rather limited.
At the end of the day, the American public is very skeptical of this war.
Even Trump's voters are starting to turn against this war, and certainly they're already very
much against going in with ground troops.
But the Iranian government's ability to be able to take advantage of some of those schisms
beyond scoring points on social media, I've not seen any clear signs that there is
any success there.
And again, through the mainstream media, you will hardly be able to get any impact from
that end.
But the Iranians are nevertheless doing this because from their standpoint, this is not
America's war.
They strongly believe that Israel led America into this war.
And the more they can hammer that point home with an American audience that already
is very receptive to that view, particularly on the right, the more they think they
can increase the opposition inside of the US against this war.
Now the Iranian state is displaying some online skills here that many in the West were
unaware that it had, both the foreign minister and the Speaker of the Parliament there have
acquired a fan following on X, and there are AI animations that are in the mix as well.
What are the core messages being sent here?
How effective do you think those techniques have been in influencing public opinion outside
of Iran?
It's really fascinating because I don't know if there's been a lot of other major wars that
simultaneously have been fought on the ground, but also within an arena of meme wars, essentially.
Various videos produced by both sides, propaganda videos, AI produced propaganda videos.
We really haven't seen that until this war.
And the Iranians are clearly scoring some points.
Whether that is the core reason why the public is negative to this war or not is really difficult
to disaggregate, because at the end of the day, the public was overwhelmingly against
this war from the outset.
It may have reinforced their opposition to it.
It may have made it stronger, but I don't think it necessarily has led to a shift in
public opinion.
If anything, what has shifted is because of higher gas prices, a clear sign that
Trump doesn't have a plan.
And certainly, I think there will be an even greater shift if he goes in with ground troops
and you have a large number of American soldiers coming home in coffins.
Let's turn to Iran itself now, the internal narrative there.
The Iranian authorities, as you know, have largely blacked out the internet there for
more than a month now.
And it's not the first time that this has happened.
Give us an idea of how crippled communications are there with the outside world.
What is this blackout and the censorship within the Iranian media space defensible in your view?
So the manner in which the government closed the internet entirely on January 8th, roughly
till January 10th, and then slowly, slowly they'd open it up, is a degree of closure
I don't think we have ever seen before.
And it's during this short period as well that a very large number of Iranian protesters
and others were killed by the government, but also by some elements
amongst the protesters who used violence.
That level of closure is not what you're having right now.
There's still a lot of limitations.
It's still difficult to get through to friends, etc.
But if they use VPNs, etc., it is possible.
Whereas during those first couple of days in January, even with VPNs,
even with Starlink, it was very difficult to get in touch with people
because the Iranian government was shutting everything down and jamming Starlink as well.
What do you make of the Iranian authorities and their argument that part of this is defensive,
protecting Iranians and their institutions by blocking off the outside world
from penetrating via the internet?
Well, let's first remind ourselves that during these times of war,
this is measures not necessarily similar to this one,
but others that are taken by almost everyone.
So in Israel right now, if you film Iranian missiles hitting Israel, you can end up in jail.
Same thing is happening in Dubai in which everything is being censored right now
in order to make sure that this information does not come out.
Now, internal communication has not been blocked by those countries.
It has been by the Iranian government.
Now, is there an element of truth in some of what they're saying?
I think there is because you already have admissions from the former head of the CIA
that Mossad and other American agents were on the ground in Iran during those days of protests.
You have opposition figures who have more or less admitted
that there were some of their elements that also stood for some of the violence.
But is that the only reason why the government is shutting it down?
No, I think this is both because of those first stated reasons,
but also because this is a way for them to show the populace that they are in control
and that they will tolerate absolutely no uprisings or protests,
but also in order to make sure that outside elements that are trying to penetrate Iran
during these sensitive times are blocked.
What do you make of the IRGC, the Iranian Revolutionary Guard Corps message
from just a few days back that it would target all those U.S. tech companies,
including Apple, Google, Metta, Amazon and Palantir?
And what does that list of targets tell you about Iran's larger strategy in this war?
Well, the larger strategy is that they're going after elements that exist within the GCC countries
that are being used directly or indirectly by the United States
in order to conduct the offensive elements of this war.
Going after the tech companies would be an indication of them identifying
that these companies, particularly their AI elements,
are being used extensively within this war in a manner that has not been the case
in previous war because, of course, a lot of these technologies are entirely new.
We saw the Israelis use AI extensively and using Palantir extensively
in the genocide in Gaza.
Now, the Iranians have not done these attacks yet.
It's not clear whether they cannot or whether this is a warning
because they want to prevent Trump from going forward with some of his escalatory threats.
But part of the reason why Trump hasn't gone forward with his escalatory threats
is precisely because of the knowledge that the Iranians can strike back very hard
at the U.S. itself, and that will only aggravate the situation
rather than enable him to get out of this war.
Let's get to the label Epstein regime.
It was popularized under the late Ayatollah,
who was assassinated in that Israeli attack.
It's now embedded throughout Iranian messaging.
And it seems to resonate not just at home in Iran, but also abroad.
Why does that label stick?
What do you think makes it so effective as a narrative weapon?
It is effective because his base were dead set against new wars.
They voted for Trump because he promised that he wouldn't start any new wars.
His conduct right now, not only with the new wars,
the stronger alliance with Israel, regime change efforts
are all completely contradictory to what he promised his base that he would do.
And in the absence of a better explanation,
the Epstein factor has emerged as a potential explanatory factor
as to why Trump is doing things that is not in the interest of the United States
and that clearly he said that he would not do.
And so the Epstein factor emerged on the US side.
Iranians are taking advantage of it rather than inventing it
because a lot of people, particularly on the American right,
being completely perplexed by Trump going in this direction,
drew the conclusion with or without evidence
that this has something to do with Epstein,
that this has something to do with the Israelis using Epstein
and other things against Trump in order to force him in this direction.
I want to emphasize no evidence has been emerging to support these type of theories.
But precisely because there are no other strong theories
that explains why in a rational sense Trump would be doing any of this stuff,
those type of conspiracy theories or theories about Epstein
have actually become quite popular.
And it's not just in the US or in Iran.
We saw Canadian officials explicitly saying that no Canadian
should be partaking or dying in this Epstein war.
Instead, the Epstein war should be fought by the.
Epstein class.
Trita Parsey of the Quincy Institute for Responsible Statecraft.
Thank you for speaking with us here at the Listening Post today.
Thank you so much for having me.
And finally, a Pentagon policy restricting press access, which ended up back in front
of a judge this past week.
It all started with changes that came from Defense Secretary Pete Hexeth that put journalists
at risk of losing their access to the Pentagon if they pursued information the Defense
Department had not approved of.
A federal judge then struck that measure down, declaring it unconstitutional.
A few days later, the Pentagon came back with a different set of restrictions, limiting
where reporters could go, requiring escorts inside the building and preserving the new
rules that could deter anonymous sourcing.
So back to court it all went, where the same judge struggled to make sense of it, describing
parts of the policy as, quote, weird, even kafkiesk, and questioning whether the
Pentagon was simply working around his initial ruling.
And all of this is unfolding as the war in Iran plays out, with Hexeth still harping
at the press, accusing American journalists of distorting their coverage and even suggesting
what their headlines should look like.
The Pentagon is supposed to determine what happens on the battlefield.
Instead, it has become one over how American reporters should cover this war.
Hello, this is Al Jazeera live from Doha with our continuing coverage of the war between
the U.S., Israel and Iran.
I'm Sara Khairat and coming up on the program, search and rescue efforts in Iran after overnight
U.S. and Israeli strikes kill at least 34 people.
A top university is among the targets.
Iran carries out strikes in Israel, killing two people in the city of Haifa and causing
extensive damage around Tel Aviv.
Israel carries out more strikes across Lebanon.
One strike hits a residential building in Beirut, killing at least three people.
Donald Trump sets a Tuesday deadline for Iran to reopen the Strait of Hormuz and says
he will, quote, unleash hell if they don't.
The Artemis II mission enters the final phase of its journey just hours away from reaching
the far side of the moon.
The U.S. and Israel have stepped up their attacks on Iran.
At least 34 people have been killed in Iran in overnight strikes.
Several areas have been targeted, including university in Tehran and also an airport in
the southwest.
Iran's Islamic Revolutionary Guard has announced that the head of its intelligence
organization, that's majored Khademi, has been killed.
Meanwhile, Tehran has continued its retaliatory strikes, sending missiles across Israel
and at least two people have been killed there in the northern city of Haifa,
as well as extensive damage around Tel Aviv.
Now, U.S. President Donald Trump, well, he's renewed his threats to destroy Iranian
power plants and bridges if it doesn't reopen the Strait of Hormuz by Tuesday.
And Iran has said it will retaliate to any strikes on infrastructure.
We are live in Ramallah, that's an occupied West Bank, Beirut, Kuwait City,
as well as Tehran.
And that is where Tahir Assadi, our correspondent, is live for us in the Iranian capital.
So he brief us on what these targets are exactly, because it seems to have
also been a heavy night there.
Well, actually, since the beginning of the night,
upon the moment we are witnessing the continuation of the air strikes,
this time very much broader when it comes to scope.
And the latest, as you mentioned, came from the IRGC.
They came out with a statement to confirm that the head of IRGC's
intelligence organization, Majid Khademi, was killed in these attacks.
And we know that over the past few hours, Tehran has been witnessing
the continuation of these strikes in the eastern, western and southern parts
of the capital from the early hours of actually night.
We witnessed the continuation of these attacks.
Of course, one of the most important ones was actually
Sharif University of Technology, which was targeted in the early hours of
the morning, and the footages are indicative of the huge amount of damage.
This is not the first university.
We know that previously we had attacks on three major universities of the country.
And we also talked to the Minister of Science, Research and Technology.
The other day when we were visiting the campus of Shahid Behishti University,
another targeted university, and he told us that more than three,
more than 30 universities all in all across the country have been impacted
as a result of these strikes.
But beyond the capital, we know that there is a relatively longer list
of cities experiencing the heavy bombardment of the Americans in Israel.
He's in Karaj, Shiraz, Isfahan, Bousheh, Bandar-e-Lenge, where six people were killed,
bomb, where five people were killed, Baharistan, where 13 people were killed.
And now we are receiving reports from Shahriah, where a residential area was targeted.
And at least nine people, including women and children,
were killed as a result of this very recent terrorist strike.
And obviously, this is part of the story.
On the other hand, we know that Iran is talking about the retaliatory strikes.
And we've got a very strong message in that regard from the spokesperson
for the Khatam-Olambiya Joint Military Headquarters,
talking about stronger and more crushing retaliatory strikes down the range.
And Tauhi Donald Trump threatening to blow up Iran's bridges and power plants
if it doesn't reopen the Strait of Hormuz by Tuesday.
And he's given a deadline for that time.
It's 8 p.m. Eastern time.
Is there any sign that Iran may moderate its approach before the deadline
and it will change it anyhow?
Not at this point.
You know, Sarah, what we hear from Tehran is a message of deterrence,
defiance, resistance and retaliation.
And this is not just limited to the military,
but also diplomatically speaking, Tehran has said that at this certain point,
it's not going to get engaged in any direct negotiation between Washington and Tehran.
And also they're talking about mediated communication between the two sides.
But frankly speaking, the extent to which this diplomatic engagement
could pave the way for a ceasefire for a de-escalated situation is quite vague
because we see that the reality on the ground is far from any point of de-escalation.
We see the continuation of airstrikes,
we see the continuation of retaliatory strikes.
And obviously Iran is in that regard trying to use the leverage
of the Strait of Hormuz in this already delicate situation.
And they are also trying to set plans for tariffs for the ship's war,
trying to go through this passage.
And this is one part and one important part of this story.
But speaking of the threatening language,
we have to keep in mind, Sarah, that this is not the first time
that Iranians are facing this threatening language
from the U.S. President Donald Trump from the very, very early days of the war
and even before they were experiencing such sort of rhetoric.
But what is concerning and what is being seriously taken into consideration
is the very fact that right now these threats are getting translated into real action
as in the past one or two weeks we are witnessing increasing attacks
on the infrastructure of the country.
So Iranians know that there is a possibility for further attack
on the infrastructure of the country while they're talking about retaliation,
if that happens.
All right, thank you very much, Tohid Asadi there with the latest for us from Iran.
Now at least two people have been killed in an Iranian strike
on a building in the city of Haifa, and that's according to Israeli media.
The residential structure partially collapsed after the attack on Sunday.
At least four others have been wounded.
Search and rescue operations continue at the scene, though.
Nader Ibrahim is following the latest developments in Israel from Ramallah.
That's in occupied West Bank.
Nader, after five weeks of war, can you give us sort of an overall
brief of how much damage Iran is actually causing to Israel?
Because there has been a number of barrages since midnight.
I think I believe around six of them hitting Israel.
Yes, indeed. And these barrages of missiles continue to affect the Israelis
and also damage houses, buildings, but also it's important to keep reminding ourselves
that the Israeli military sensor is detecting everything that's being
published about the damage and the impact that these missiles cause.
So if there's something hitting a strategic asset, security asset,
places that Israel has like interesting or has important military sites,
then we are rarely going to hear about it.
But we are indeed hearing about the impact on people's lives.
People who continue to head to shelters for five weeks now
and continue to face these cluster ammunition threats.
Why? Because even if these missiles are intercepted, they continue to cause
damage because of the fragmenting bomblets on the warhead that splintered,
detonating in several areas.
For example, in Haifa, that missile was not intercepted.
It also had a warhead that had bomblets.
But for some reason it did not detonate.
And that kind of saved the Israelis more and more damage.
Even though the damage that has been incurred is considered the big one,
two people killed, two others in a critical condition under the rubble,
while search and rescue continue to try and get them out of there.
But the idea is that these missiles continue to disrupt life while.
Speaking of that search and rescue, I just want to interrupt you there.
But we are seeing those live pictures from Haifa.
What we're just seeing now obviously is the damage that's been caused
by that Iranian barrage of rockets.
As you were mentioning that, Nidhat cluster munitions.
And then also we just saw someone, perhaps someone alive.
It's still not clear on a stretcher being it looks like it was a body
that was covered actually being recovered from that strike.
Seems to be a residential building.
We do know that a couple of people have been killed and there have been
many injuries, so we may see a rise in that still not sure.
But Nidhat, sorry, back to you people in Israel, you know,
they are hearing those sirens.
We know that those sirens give them an ability.
They know that these rockets are coming and they give them a time frame.
They rush to the bunker.
Of course, there are areas where Palestinians are that don't have that opportunity.
But we're hearing now that people are actually taking to the shelter,
not just occasionally, but living in them because of the number of attacks.
Yes, indeed. And let me just update on what you've been mentioning just now,
Sarah, about the four missing people in Haifa who were found
lifeless under the rubble.
So that might be part of the footage you were referring to with the stretcher.
Now we are talking about four people who were under the rubble.
Two of them have been rescued or recovered rather early this morning.
Now we are talking about an additional two.
And two back to your question about people living in shelters
because of the continued barrages specifically in northern Israel,
from Hezbollah and from Iran, sometimes happening at the same time.
People have found it very difficult to try and go to shelter.
Sometimes these sirens do not last long enough
for people to make their way to these fortified areas or shelters.
That is raising many questions about the strategy of the government about
have they been undermining Hezbollah's capabilities?
Are they in for a war that they cannot fight?
So these are questions that are being raised.
And these questions also show us that while at the beginning of the war,
we were reporting that 80 percent of the Israelis are supporting the war,
are showing much support for it.
Now we can sense that diminishing support for this war as a result
of the continued barrages of missiles and also as a result of Netanyahu,
who first started the war by saying it's going to be a decisive one.
It's going to lead to a clear win.
But then he started backtracking by saying, OK,
we limited Iran's existential threat against us,
but we are not able yet to stop these missiles from being fired into Israel.
More or less, these were his words.
This is far from enough for Israelis who have been tolerating this war
because they believe it's going to end the threat altogether,
but not that they're going to still be going to shelters every now and a day.
We want to I want to stay with you.
They may have lost that connection. Here we go.
But I actually want to speak to some of those live pictures that you're seeing
there, because again, we've just now seeing a second body
being removed from the rubble of the aftermath of an Iranian attack on Israel.
This is in Haifa, it's a port city.
It's been one of the main targets of Iran because of military infrastructure there.
And this is the second body, two missing bodies,
Nadat that you had been mentioning there.
So this is the second one that has been found.
Obviously, people are being hit very hard in Israel,
but I want to turn the attention now to the West Bank.
We will continue with those live pictures so you can see.
But back to you, Nadat, in the West Bank, as this war is happening
and as Israel is continuing its attacks on Iran,
there are also attacks happening on Palestinians by illegal Israeli settlers.
What's the update there?
Well, Sarah, it's not enough
that people continue to fear these missiles coming into their lands,
into their territories while they don't have any aerial defense systems or have
even what to do, even rescue efforts like we're seeing just now in Haifa,
with the four people now announced dead after one missile made impact.
We are talking about a population in the occupied West Bank that is
completely defenseless, but not only that, they're facing yet another war
front, and that is the continued attacks by Israeli settlers against them.
It's hard to count for you, Sarah, the amount of attack
and the numbers that have been affected by that just in the past few weeks,
almost with every village you go, every town you go, you would see these Israeli
settlers rocking, having and making life more and more difficult for Palestinians.
Just overnight, we've been reporting the injury of 10 people in one village
close to Nablus as Israeli settlers launched an attack.
What's been happening now is a growth in these attacks, using the fog of war,
using the world's attention that's being focused elsewhere to continue disrupting
life and prevent Palestinians from living on the lands they've been living on for
decades. This fear, this real realistic fear is the reason why people have been
packing their stuff and leaving places that they've been in for decades
because they cannot protect their own children, given that these settlers
are not just armed with weapons, but they are armed with their government's
lack of accountability towards them, with their impunity, with the fact that they
can just now decide to bring a caravan, put it wherever they want in the occupied
West Bank, and fear no accountability.
Yes, we're seeing a pushback now from the Israeli security and the Israeli
authorities trying to limit that.
Apparently, according to media reports, the Americans have been pushing
the Israeli government to limit these attacks by Israeli settlers.
But it's still too little, too late, because these settlers have been emboldened,
have been growing, have been becoming more and more violent and disrupting
Palestinians' lives, sometimes even setting their homes and tents on fire.
All right. So thanks very much, Nadat Ibrahim, as we've just seen two
bodies removed from the rubble in Haifa and it seems a probe in Israel has
found that the missile that was sent from Iran hadn't been intercepted.
Hence the damage that you're seeing there in the port city of Haifa in Israel.
Now, the threat of escalation in Iran has put the Gulf region directly in the line
of fire. Iran's army says that US forces located on Kuwait's Bobeyan Island
were targeted. Health authorities in Kuwait also report that six people have
been injured after debris from a missile landed in a residential area.
And for more on that, let's go to Kuwait City, where Malik trainer is live for us.
Well, you've been monitoring those developments across the Gulf now.
What do we know exactly as to what's happened there?
Well, as you mentioned, we saw from the Khatum-e-Lambiax spokesperson saying
that they targeted American forces in the Bobeyan Island here in Kuwait.
You know, what we've seen throughout this conflict is if and when American bases
are hit, we usually don't hear something from the host countries.
Just a few weeks ago, we heard in Saudi Arabia on the air
Sultan air base was hit and 15 people were injured.
Confirmation came later from the Americans themselves.
So I don't think we'll hear anything from the Kuwaitis as to that.
But we've seen a range of attacks across the Gulf.
Six people injured, as you mentioned, in the Northern Kuwait due to debris
from an from an interception in the residential area.
In the UAE, we've seen attacks in Abu Dhabi in the industrial city,
where one person, a Ghanaian national, was injured.
Another attack in the Fujeda area where that where authorities responded
to an incident at a telecommunications company.
And we've seen also in Saudi Arabia, where the Ministry of Defense said
it intercepted two drones.
So, you know, as these as this war continues, there
has been no, no letting up of these retaliation attacks across the Gulf.
And Manic, obviously, where that deadline by Trump is looming, has there been any reaction
from the GCC in terms of anticipation as to what happens? How will that affect the GCC
even?
Well, I think everywhere across the GCC, people and officials are extremely concerned,
right? Because the Gulf has spared the brunt of these retaliation attacks, you know,
more than 85% of these attacks have targeted the Gulf. You know, more than 6,000
ballistic missiles, drones, and cruise missiles have been targeted here.
We just heard from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs in Qatar where the Prime
Minister and Foreign Minister had a conversation with the Spanish Foreign
Minister. And, you know, they talked about de-escalation and that there
needs, there's no military solution that, you know, there needs to be a space
for negotiations, for a diplomatic path. You know, here in Kuwait, you know,
yesterday, we've seen, we saw numerous attacks, you know, probably the most
devastating day in terms of Kuwait. You know, I think what the Iranians
proved yesterday is that they can indeed target and hit a civilian
infrastructure. Two water plants and desalination plants and power plants
were hit here yesterday. That's extremely critical infrastructure for the
Gulf. Here in Kuwait, 90% of their drinking water comes from these desalination
plants. So that's a red line yet again being crossed. Kuwait is also the
closest to Iran. Just 80 kilometers of water is what separates these two
countries. And also borders Iraq where we've seen in recent, in the
recent week, officials believe that a lot of these attacks are coming
from affiliated, Iran-affiliated groups in Iraq. So if there's a real concern
here, I think, you know, the call has been consistent, de-escalate the
situation. We saw that yesterday, the Omanians said they're in talks with
the Iranians to come up with some kind of mechanism to ensure passage
through the Haramu Strait. I think realistically, nobody believes that,
you know, they can come up with a deal that everybody can agree on within
the next, you know, 12 or 24 hours. But, you know, what I think the message
will be relayed to Trump is, look, the Iranians are talking, there's talks
going on to open up the Strait. Let's give diplomacy a chance and let's
get a solution that will bring long-term stability across the entire
region. All right. Thanks very much. That's Malik Trainer there, live for
us in Kuwait City. Well, Israel has carried out multiple strikes across
southern Lebanon and also on the capital Beirut, causing widespread
damage and death. The latest targeted Beirut southern suburbs. And this
comes after the military issued a forced evacuation threat for residents
for seven neighbourhoods. On Sunday, multiple attacks on the
southern suburbs, densely populated areas, killed at least five
people. Meanwhile, in the south of Lebanon, Israeli military attacks
targeted areas in the Nabata district. At least four people were killed in
a drone strike targeting a car there. And in a separate attack in the
same area, one person was killed. Let's go live now to Zayn al-Khodr, who's
been following the latest from the capital Beirut. Zayn, earlier, we
saw a smoke that seemed to be coming from the Dahya area. What more do
we know about that? Well, yet again, the Israeli military targeting
Beirut southern suburbs, they issued an evacuation order before
those strikes come in. But not all strikes are preceded by a
warning. As I'm speaking to you now, Israeli warplanes are flying over
the Lebanese capital. They've been doing this for the past few days.
Really, there's been an escalation with Israeli strikes,
relentless, not just in Beirut, but in the south of the country, in
the east of the country. Yesterday, a densely populated
neighbourhood was hit, killing five people, among them a child. And
the target appeared to be a Hezbollah military commander. But
even though Israel calls these targeted assassinations, pinpoint
strikes, it really doesn't matter if civilians are killed as
well. And there is growing concern that the latest figure
released by the Lebanese Health Ministry is 1,461 killed among
them, children and women, more than 4,000 wounded. And that
number has not been updated because since the early hours
of the morning, there have been repeated strikes. Now,
while the ministry doesn't say or differentiate between
combatants and civilians, if we count the number of women,
children and paramedics alone, that's roughly 25% of the
casualty toll.
And Zeina, where are the Israelis in terms of their ground
invasion in the south? You know, talking in the Israeli
media is that they're up against a bit of a struggle
there.
Hezbollah has been putting up resistance. It is fighting
back. It is making it a costly invasion for the
Israeli army. In the past 24, 48 hours, the Israeli army
cannot report any significant military gains on the ground.
The latest in its latest effort is trying to besiege
strategic town, Bint Jbeil, in the central sector, trying
to cut supply lines to reach the town, lay siege to this
whole area. They still have not been able to do that.
Yesterday, the Israeli army acknowledging that 66 soldiers
were wounded in the past three days. Already 11 soldiers
have been killed in this ongoing invasion. And then we
hear from Israel's chief of staff who says, yes, Israel's
goal is to disarm Hezbollah. But the current
campaign is about advancing this goal. He doesn't use
the word achieve this goal, but to advance this goal.
So there's a growing realization that even if the
Israeli army reaches up until the Letoni River as
declared by the Israeli defense ministers, the stated
objective of this operation, it's not going to be enough
because Hezbollah has strategic weapons north of the river.
So this is proving to be a difficult campaign for the
Israeli military. Hezbollah promising a prolonged
fight, both sides really. This is for Hezbollah.
This is an existential battle. And for Israel, you
know, it wants this group to be disarmed, but it
hasn't been able to do so. And this is not the
first conflict that it has engaged with Hezbollah.
All right, thank you very much, Zayna Khordor there for
the latest for us on what's happening in Lebanon. Now
I'm joined in our studio by Muhammad al-Masri, a
professor of media studies at the Dahat Institute for
Graduate Studies. And in Moria in Australia, we're
joined by Michael Shubridge, he's the director of
Strategic Analysis Australia. That's the defense and
security think tank. Thank you both gentlemen for
joining us today. Michael, I want to start with you.
We just heard there from Zayna Khordor. And before
that, we've heard from Tohid Assadi in Iran, as
well as our correspondent Malik Traina in Kuwait
City about the attacks that are being carried out by
Iran, but also the attacks that are being carried
out by Israel. Zayna Khordor in Beirut was saying
that Israel is finding it quite difficult. They're
not making the gains they wanted to do. Michael,
I'm just going to actually stop you, stop this
conversation there because we are now going to
go to breaking news there. The spokesperson for the
Iranian Ministry of Foreign Affairs. When it's
necessary, we will defend our country with all the
might under the leader of the Islamic Revolution
and according to the Iranian Constitution. We
will defend our country and one its peace whenever
it's necessary and according to the priorities
and the mechanisms that are mentioned in the Iranian
Constitution. We follow up all the efforts that are
aiming at reaching peace in reality. They have no
red lines. The U.S. and Israel have no red lines.
They have no respect to the international
constitutions and the international agreement.
We are defending our country. This is our priority
now. The Iranian armed forces are sacrificing a lot to
defend the country and to defend the Iranian
people. We are supporting these efforts, the
efforts of defending our countries, the efforts
made by the armed forces of Iran. A question,
there are some news saying that there is a plan
to put an end to the war and at the same time we
hear some contradictory attitudes from the U.S.
President Donald Trump regarding attacking the Iranian
infrastructure. Is there any new plan to put an end to the war?
What is the answer of the of Iran regarding the American threats?
We have discovered that the plan is clear. The mediators
have mentioned a project or a plan that is consisting of 15
items through Pakistan and some other countries.
And at that time we had confirmed that we
consider these items not logic at all and it
it has nothing to do with the logic and we will never accept
these 15 items, these 15 American conditions.
And according to our interests we adopt the necessary
decisions. We have submitted some visions and
some ideas and I want to make everything clear.
Clearly we talk about our rightful requests.
When there is a plan or a project we also have our own requests
regarding that plan or that project and no one has the right
to consider it a plan for the ceasefire. At the time where the Iranian armed
forces in a very brave manner defend our country
and our people the people of Iran the criteria for us
are the national security of Iran the national interests of Iran
and our legitimate requests in any plan and in any project because we know
what do we need and what do we want and we know
in prior what are the red lines. So when this project or this plan has
been submitted we have sent our reply to this
matter and we will announce that clearly and publicly to the Iranian people
but when it comes to the role of the mediators the mediators are conveying
the different attitudes from here to there and from there to here
this is normal this is normal to happen and I have mentioned
this when it comes to our red lines we need not
to compromise when it comes to our national security
and our national interests these points have been
submitted to us previously we had exchanged messages and letters from
Iran and the U.S. through the mediators but
honest to God the talks cannot go parallel with the threats
they cannot threaten us and they cannot ask us to sit on the table of negotiations
we have experiences bitter experiences before
with the United States of America and
our achievements of today the achievement of
Iran has cost have cost us an expensive price
the United States and the Israeli entity
are increasing their crimes against humanity and the Iranian
foreign ministry being one of the main sovereign
institutions of the Iranian regime is making everything
documented in order to reply and respond to all the claims
and the threats of both countries regarding the threats
matter of fact undoubtedly I can say that the mere
talk about the threats is a crime in itself is a war crime in itself and
these crimes are there and we cannot heal from time to time that the
United States of America is threatening Iran
threatening Iran threatening the infrastructure of Iran
and at the same time and within the tasks that are to be done
they are giving the Israeli entity the green light
to hit our military locations according to the international law
this is a war crime and undoubtedly again
any country has the right to defend itself
and those countries who are supporting the enemies to commit their war crimes
must be responsible and must be blamed for their
support to both countries the US and Israel in front of the
international courts and the humanitarian law
these are responsible for committing these war crimes against the Islamic
Republic of Iran and because of the American Israeli
crimes against humanity question from Anatolian news agency
peace be upon you doctor
there are some information regarding the American pilot
in the south of Isfahan the American
pilot American they said he was in the south of Isfahan
this question is to be answered by the Iranian armed forces
and I cannot give you complete answers in this regard but the main topic is
the defeat of the United States of America in this
particular area their flights have fallen there
all right well we were just hearing there from the spokesperson
for the Iranian foreign minister and joining us
as well as Muhammad al-Mustri and Michael Shubridge in Australia we have our
correspondent Osama bin Javed Osama you've just come back from Pakistan
and of course the Iranian foreign ministry spokesperson just mentioned
Pakistan because it seems they are playing a
mediatory role we know that and he also referred to the
15-point plan that has been put forward by the US
so what did you think of the response from Iran well just before this briefing I
was talking to senior Pakistani officials excuse me who've told me that
Pakistan is involved in frantic diplomacy as they put it
there have been a number of phone calls in the last few days between
Abbas Iraqi the Pakistani foreign minister Masood Pazeshki on the
president as well as others to try and find some sort of an offer
what the Pakistanis are doing is trying to pave way for talks
as the as the spokesman mentioned there that there is a 15-point plan
that was put forward by the US that Iran responded to it by its own plan it
wants reparations for all the damage caused it wants
complete sovereignty of the state of home moves it wants to
make sure that it has assistance as well as the ability to carry on with a
civilian nuclear program so these are maximum dispositions that
still are there that were there 10 days ago
in the last 24 hours as this deadline was extended again
by President Trump what the Pakistanis are telling me is that they
are still involved in diplomacy and what they don't want to do is do diplomacy
via newspapers or headlines it is very delicate
now problem that they're facing as one official put it is essentially
it's a schoolboy brawl that they are dealing with it is
egos that they have to maintain it is also a sea of distrust that they
have to build bridges with you you heard the Iranian spokesman mentioned
there that this is this they've come under attack multiple
times by the United States in Israel and then if there is some sort of rapprochement
if there is some sort of an agreement then what are the guarantees that their
leaders are not going to be targeted who's going to make sure that they
are they're safe if they have to get to that table
or the Pakistanis are in touch with is various levels of the Iranian
power structure if you can call it that one source told me
that they're speaking to clergy they're speaking to the diplomats and they're
also speaking to military commanders alluding to the IRTC now the problem
there now is the leadership that has taken charge now
feels one it has the upper hand militarily because it has been able
to stave off the United States in Israel for the last five weeks or so
it is giving them a really difficult resistance
they're not able to enter they've not even to be able to
open the Strait of Hormuz and that is why they think that they can drag this on
to get their own demands in order and that is a really risky game
because as these deadlines continue to be extended
the real threat is that if this deadline comes to pass
and if there are those attacks that the US president is threatening
what happens in the region next so am I understanding from you
very briefly that the Pakistanis are trying to push something before this
deadline before the actual time that has been given by
Trump perhaps to have a ceasefire of some some sort
yes that is exactly the case so in addition to the points that Iranians
have put on the table and the Americans have put on the table
we believe that the Pakistanis are pushing for a point of agreement could
that be a ceasefire could that be an end to hostilities
could that be a temporary opening of Strait of Hormuz all options are on
the table what they're saying is that let's find a point of convergence
and then you can sit down and talk about the points of divergence
but unless there is that
that both sides can come to an agreement on.
And there are guarantees, especially by Israel,
that it will not continue to target Iranian top officials.
It is very unlikely that these talks will take place.
All right, and Michael too, Osama was saying that
the Pakistanis have sort of made it clear
to him based on what the Iranians are saying
to the Pakistanis that they are, if anything,
emboldened six weeks into the war.
And if anything, they've actually stepped up those attacks.
We've just seen, before we came to you,
and that was my question to you earlier,
seeing the attacks that have hit Haifa,
six barrages on Israel, as well as attacks on the GCC.
So where do you think this war will move forward from it?
If, as Osama says, a ceasefire isn't possible,
and Trump was to go ahead with his attacks.
Well, I heard the Iranian spokesperson just now
say that they wouldn't negotiate with the Americans
while the Americans were threatening to escalate
or actually escalating.
I think that's a pretty clear message.
But what seems to me to be likely is
because there is that fundamental lack of trust
and because the Iranians have obvious leverage,
not just over the Strait of Almuz,
but over broader attacks across the Gulf.
If America does escalate, Iran will too,
and that will drive this war in a much more damaging direction.
That's obviously what the Pakistanis
are so feverishly trying to avoid.
And Mohamed Masri, we just heard there
from the spokesman for the Iranian Foreign Ministry,
and he says he mentioned the red line a number of times,
saying we won't compromise on our national security
and our interests without going into specifics.
What do we know of what Iran wants out of this?
Well, Osama spoke to a couple of the demands.
My sense is that that 15-point plan
that the U.S. presented is kind of a non-starter,
that the Iranians view it as a sort of surrender document.
The U.S. is demanding that Iran
not only give up its nuclear program,
but that it gives up its right to longer-range missiles
that could target Israel,
in addition to breaking down their network of proxies.
And from the Iranian perspective,
this would leave Iran completely defenseless
against a potential Israeli attack.
So these points in particular
are non-starters for the Iranians,
and I think that's probably what he was referring to
on those red lines.
It was interesting that he said,
and Michael mentioned, I think, part of this,
but the other part was he talked about the threat.
He said, we will not negotiate while we are under threat.
So he's talking specifically there about this threat
that Trump has to bomb the bridges
and power plants in Iran.
So from, look, I don't wanna be negative,
but from where we stand right now,
it seems to me that these two sides
could not be farther apart.
The fact that there's a huge lack of trust,
that's a major problem here.
The fact that the United States
walked away already from an agreement in 2018,
that's a serious issue.
The fact that the U.S. and Israel bombed Iran
in the middle of negotiations in June of 2025,
while the negotiations were going well,
according to Trump himself, right?
And then that they did the same thing again
at the end of February, 2026,
while the negotiations again were going well,
according to the Omani mediator,
this has completely broken down trust.
And so it doesn't look to me like there's a path forward
except to say, and I'll just leave on a positive,
I'll say this as maybe a more of a positive note,
both sides are really hurting.
This war is not helping the Iranians
and it's not helping the Americans.
Now Israel, we can have a conversation about Israel.
I do think Israel has an interest in keeping this going,
but the fact that it's going so badly
for Iran, for the United States,
for the region as a whole gives us some hope
that at some point they will agree to end hostilities
if for no other reason
then this could just lead to even more disastrous
consequences for everybody.
Osama, back to what you were saying earlier,
the Pakistanis, you've spoken to them
and they, as you said,
are speaking to all different levels within Iran.
The clergymen, the military, perhaps the intelligence.
So what is Pakistan saying in terms of,
perhaps they have, I don't know,
the type of leadership, the replacement leadership
that they are dealing with now
as opposed to the elders that have all been killed?
But in one word, it is not as experienced
as the previous ones.
This is leadership which has come on board,
especially if you look at the military leaders
that have come to the front,
are younger, are not as known in the battlefields
as the previous ones who had fought wars.
So essentially what the Pakistanis are dealing with
are people who, A, feel that they have
the upper hand militarily,
B, want to tell their people what are they made of,
what they can teach the enemy in a battle space.
But building on to what Mohammad just said,
there is multiple off-ramps that are still available.
I asked some sources about this question of,
what gives you hope?
Because these are maximalist positions,
nobody's willing to budge.
And what I was told,
that while you'll see a lot of chest thumping
on the airways, there is quiet diplomacy taking place.
And indication was the deadline.
It wasn't this deadline that was extended by Donald Trump.
It was the previous one.
It was two days, then it was a week, then it was 10 days.
And now another day extension.
So do you think we could see an extension to this one?
People who are involved in this believe
that there might be another extension to this
because of the sheer inability of people
to communicate within Iran,
because so much of the infrastructure
as well as command structure has been degraded.
And that is why you're seeing diplomacy
when it comes to Iranian stalking to the French,
Iranians stalking to diplomats of the region.
And frantic phone calls between Ankara, Riyadh,
you're seeing them in Oman,
speaking to them about a possibility of an opening.
Just before coming here, I was talking to somebody
and they said that, look,
if the Iranians wanted to tell the Americans a message,
they've let 15 ships go through the Strait of Omuz
in the last 24 hours.
So there is a partial reopening
if the American president wanted to sell it as that.
So there are multiple avenues
if there is serious impetus behind finding peace.
But as Mohammed said, the real equation,
the real deal breaker here is Israel,
as you've seen time and again,
even diplomats who were involved in this
have been targeted.
Michael, to you, one last question, Michael Shubrid.
Just 15 minutes ago, I thought perhaps
based on what Trump was saying
is that there could be negotiations
to sort of end this idea of Israel
and the U.S. pummeling Iran
and its infrastructure.
But now hearing from Osama
and also hearing from the spokesman for the Iranian farmers,
it seems Iran is intent
that they are feeling more emboldened
and they intend to get what they want out of this.
So Trump really is in a sort of difficult position also
because whatever the U.S. decides to do next,
the repercussions will be felt in the region here,
in the GCC.
If it's been an eye for an eye,
it's tipped for tact throughout this whole war
and Iran won't hold back, it said.
Well, exactly.
So the problem here is that Donald Trump
has to make some gesture to the Iranians
and it's hard for that not to look like him backing down.
So my concern is that's not what's going
through the American president's mind.
What he wants to do is double down
and cause more damage
to look like he's in the position of strength
and I hope that he's getting enough advice
about the broader damage to the region
that that would likely provoke
and about the damage to the global economy from that.
That to me, that sort of fear of the markets,
fear of gasoline prices,
that's more likely to be the thing that moderates him
but I think the risks of broad escalation
happening soon are very high.
All right, thank you.
I'd like to thank all of you.
Michael and Shoebridge in Australia.
We also had Mohammed Mastri here in the studio
as well as Salman bin Javed, our senior correspondent.
Thank you very much, gentlemen.
Right, well, US president Donald Trump
has been giving Iran shifting deadlines
to reopen the Strait of Hormuz
and that says Iran insists the key waterway
isn't actually closed and that only ships
that belong to its enemies are barred from passage.
Trump issued his first ultimatum on March 21st.
He threatened to bomb Iran's power plants
if the Strait wasn't reopened within 48 hours
and he later extended that deadline by five days
claiming that negotiations were underway.
Trump issued a new deadline and that was on March 26th.
He gave Iran 10 days or until the evening of April 6th
to reopen the Strait.
Trump also issued his latest Hormuz threat on Sunday.
That's after vowing to bomb power plants and bridges
if Tehran doesn't comply.
He posted what appears to be a Tuesday 8 p.m. EST
eastern time that is deadline for a deal.
Well, Al Jazeera's Mike Hanna
has more on Trump's comments from Washington, D.C.
The unusual use of an expletive by a national leader,
perhaps a symbol of President Trump's frustration
with the Iranian government
and their refusal to concede to the demands
that he is making.
That reference as well was to the Strait of Hormuz
which in recent days, President Trump had insisted
he did not care about saying
the U.S. did not need the oil passing through the Strait
and it was up to the countries who are reliant on that oil
to deal with the situation.
But now the demand about opening the Strait of Hormuz
appears front and center
of the President's new demands of the Iranian government.
President Trump threatening to, and I use his words,
blowing everything and taking the oil
if Iran does not meet his new deadline,
which has now been set at 8 p.m.
eastern time on Tuesday evening.
He says in an earlier media post
that a power plant day and bridge day
all wrapped up on Tuesday.
But on the other hand, in addition to these threats,
President Trump is sending signals
that there's some kind of negotiation process underway.
He's indicated that his close confidants, Jared Kushner
and Stephen Whitcoff are in consultation
with either the Iranian government
and identified figures or some form of intermediary.
And speaking to U.S. news outlets,
President Trump says that he is optimistic
that there can be an agreement very soon.
He says the agreement could come
within a matter of days rather than a matter of weeks.
So you've got this dichotomous approach
from the President on the one hand threatening
obliteration to civilian targets within Iran,
which some observers would contend to be a war crime.
But on the other hand, what he is saying is,
yes, we are talking, the talks are going well,
and they could come to fruition
before that new deadline I set,
which is 8 p.m. eastern time on Tuesday.
Mike Hanna, Al Jazeera, Washington.
The Iran war is piling pressure
on Sri Lanka's fragile economy,
still recovering from its financial crisis four years ago.
Fuel prices have surged,
with petrol and diesel now being rationed.
Electricity costs are also up by 25%.
And that says Manel Fernandez reports for us from Colombo.
Many people are struggling to cope.
Lassit Gayan has worked
for a food delivery company in Colombo for four years.
The 39-year-old's income depends
on the number of deliveries he makes.
But restrictions on fuel and price increases
caused by the Iran war have affected his earnings.
I make around $20 a day,
but I have to buy all my meals.
That costs more than $5 a day.
I use what's left for fuel, rent,
and to send home to my family.
Restaurants like this,
where Gayan is picking up his first order for the day,
are also struggling.
Gas for cooking is more expensive.
And manager Suranga Tirunagama says
good quality ingredients are difficult to find.
This has forced many outlets to increase their prices.
Something Tirunagama says he's trying to avoid.
Can I have a pulon tiran price?
We're trying our best to manage without raising prices,
but it's getting more challenging day by day
because today's prices are not the same tomorrow.
We can't budget.
Prices are increasing.
And it's already evident.
Gayan says he's delivering few orders these days.
Many people we spoke to told us
the worst part is the uncertainty.
On the way to his next pickup, Gayan fills up.
The government has imposed fuel restrictions.
Motorbike riders get a weekly quarter of eight liters.
Half the fuel Gayan says he usually goes through.
Station owner Sampat Kotalavala is also dealing with uncertainty.
We only receive about 50% of the supplies we order.
And we manage these stocks according to the framework
the government has given us.
It's not enough for some, but generally it's okay.
But that's for today.
I can't say what tomorrow will be like.
There are other pressures too.
A long-pending electricity price increase
took effect this month,
with some bills set to go up by 25%.
The government has asked people to use power sparingly.
Ioning and washing clothes only once a week.
And government officers
have been told to switch off air conditioners early.
Gayan says Sri Lanka is recovering
from its worst economic crisis.
The Iran war is causing more uncertainty.
People are paying more for fuel, food
and even public transport
as a conflict thousands of kilometers away
since prices soaring.
On the road, Gayan has stopped for a cup of tea and a snack
that's costing him more now than it did two weeks ago.
But he must hurry because the next order is waiting.
Minal Fernandez, Al Jazeera, Colombo.
All right, let's take a look at some of the other world's news.
Israeli forces have shot and killed
a UN employee in Gaza and injured another.
The World Health Organization's staff members
were travelling in a vehicle along Salahid Dean Road
in southern Gaza.
And that's when Israeli soldiers opened fire.
Three other people were also injured in the attack.
Hamas says it will not hand over its weapons.
Disarmament is part of the second phase
of the Gaza ceasefire plan.
But the armed group says calls to lay down
its weapons are unacceptable,
especially as Palestinians continue
to be targeted by Israel.
More than 700 people have been killed
since the ceasefire came into effect in October.
As for raising the issue of weapons
in this crude manner, it is nothing but a scandalous attempt
by the occupation to continue killing
and genocide against our people,
which we will not accept under any circumstances.
We affirm that what the enemy was unable to seize from us
with tanks and genocide, it will not
seize from us with politics or at the negotiation table.
The occupation's aggression against our people
and its continued closure of the blessed al-Aqsa mosque
to worshipers in an unprecedented manner
and the approval of the law for executing
Palestinian prisoners.
We call upon the masses of our Palestinian people
in the brave West Bank, the blessed Jerusalem,
and the occupied interior to march toward al-Aqsa mosque.
Thousands of Palestinians are still waiting
for Israeli permits to evacuate for medical treatment.
As the elder Adwan and her grandson
were granted permission to travel to Egypt
after he was diagnosed with a congenital heart condition
requiring urgent surgery, but he died.
When Adwan returned to Gaza,
she found her husband and children
had been killed in an airstrike.
Now alone, she shares her story.
In the war, all of them were martyred.
What was left of the feeling,
what was left of the words, what was left of the story?
What was left of the one who was able to do what he wanted?
What was left of him in his heart?
They were all young people,
young people like Warda,
young people from all over the world.
One of them was a lawyer, a lawyer.
My daughters, Warda,
became my heart.
All of them were killed.
My husband,
my wife and my brother-in-law in my heart,
they were all killed.
My father-in-law was a great man,
he was able to take care of my children,
take care of my family.
He was able to tell me I was a stranger
and I was close to the border,
close to my home.
Well, at least 41 miners are trapped underground
after an attack on a coal mile
in the Russian-controlled Luhansk.
A Russian-appointed official in the region
says Ukraine was behind the strike
and a power substation was also damaged.
Emergency crews are working to rescue the miners
and restore power to the site.
Serbia says explosives have been found near a pipeline
that carries Russian gas to Hungary.
Authorities say the discovery was made
outside of Serbia and town
that's near the Hungarian border
and it comes just a week
before closely watched elections in Hungary.
Prime Minister Viktor Orban is fighting
to extend his 16 years in power.
He's linked Ukraine to those explosives
without blaming Kiev directly.
Ukraine has been working to cut Europe off
from Russian energy.
They blew up Nord Stream,
shut down the gas pipeline supplying Hungary
and this year placed Hungary under an oil blockade
by closing the Druzba pipeline.
The Russian section of the Turk Stream
is also under continuous military attack.
Ukraine's efforts pose a life-threatening
danger to Hungary.
Kiev has rejected Orban's accusations
Listing on X, the Foreign Ministry spokesman said Ukraine has nothing to do with this, most
probably a Russian false flag operation as part of Moscow's heavy interference into
Hungarian elections.
Well, four astronauts are hours away from becoming the first people to see the dark
side of the moon.
The Artemis-2 mission crew has entered the final phase of its journey, preparing to
loop around the far side of the moon.
At this point, the moon's gravity is a stronger pull on their capsule than the Earth's,
and the three Americans and one Canadian will travel further from the Earth than any human
before them as they complete their first crewed lunar fly-by in more than 50 years.
They'll lose communications for about 40 minutes while passing behind the moon,
where they're also expected to witness a solar eclipse.
Right, well, we will be back in just a moment of more extensive coverage of the
war between the US, Israel and Iran. I'm Sara Khairat, I'll be handing over to Cyril Varnier.
For now, I will be back later with more of today's coverage. Stay with us.
The latest news as it breaks.
A Russian oil tanker is on its way to Cuba carrying something like 670,000 barrels
of desperately needed fuel.
With detailed coverage.
We have been hearing a number of gunshots by the Israeli military,
and this is another explosion, very close to where people are living.
From around the world.
Many have told us that they're here to take a stand against what they call the politics
of hate and division.
Hard-hitting interviews.
I don't think you are afraid that you might be one of the targets.
Anyone could become a target.
We have seen that they have no hesitation about targeting any place.
Facing realities.
Does Qatar still trust Iran enough to mediate?
Let's say that this aggression brings a benefit for no one.
Thought-provoking answers.
How many have been displaced inside Iran?
I've got three million.
It could be more.
Hear their story on Talk to Al Jazeera.
Hearing the facts.
The busy day for Iran today could mean when Iran retaliates,
it will be a busy day for cities in the Gulf.
With the latest global news and insightful documentaries,
Al Jazeera's teams across the world bring you closer to the heart of the story.
Hello, this is Al Jazeera live from Doha with our continuing coverage of the
war between the U.S., Israel and Iran.
I'm Cyril Vanier.
Coming up in the program this hour,
search and rescue efforts in Iran after overnight U.S.
and Israeli strikes kill at least 34 people.
The top university is among the targets.
Iran carries out strikes in Israel,
killing four people in the city of Haifa
and causing extensive damage around Tel Aviv.
And Donald Trump sets a Tuesday deadline
for Iran to reopen the Strait of Hormuz
and says that he will quote,
Unleash Hell if they don't.
Israel carries out more strikes across Lebanon.
One strike hits a residential building in Beirut,
killing at least three people.
The crew of the Artemis II mission
are just hours away from becoming the first humans
to see the dark side of the moon.
So Iran says that negotiations are incompatible with threats
as the U.S. and Israel step up their attacks on Iran.
At least 34 people have been killed in the country in overnight strikes.
The Islamic Revolutionary Guard also announcing
that the head of their intelligence organization,
Majid Khademi, is his name, has been killed.
Iran's Foreign Ministry spokesperson says
that Tehran is focused at the moment
on the security of its country.
Ismail Barahi has acknowledged diplomatic efforts
by Pakistan, but he says that Tehran
will never accept a 15-point plan
put forward by the United States.
The mediators have mentioned a project
or a plan that is consistent of 15 items
through Pakistan and some other countries.
And at that time, we had confirmed that we consider
these items not logic at all.
And it has nothing to do with the logic.
And we will never accept these 15 items,
these 15 American conditions.
And meanwhile, Iran has continued its retaliatory strikes,
sending missiles across Israel.
At least four people have been killed
in the northern city of Haifa,
and there has been extensive damage around Tel Aviv as well.
Earlier, U.S. President Donald Trump renewed threats
to destroy Iranian power plants and bridges
if it does not reopen the Strait of Hormuz by Tuesday.
Iran has said that it will retaliate
against any strikes on its infrastructure.
Now, we're live in Dubai, in Ramallah,
in the occupied West Bank,
and in the Iranian capital, Tehran.
That's where we start Al Jazeera's Toheed Asadi
is there in Tehran.
So, Toheed, I want to start with this.
The Revolutionary Guard confirmed
that the head of their intelligence unit has been killed.
What have you been able to learn about that?
Well, actually, Tehran had yet another night
of heavy bombardment yesterday.
And of course, earlier, we've got this statement from IRGC
about the killing of actually the head
of the Intelligence Organization of IRGC,
which is being interpreted as another major blow
when it comes to the security apparatus of the country.
We know that earlier,
the Intelligence Minister of the country,
a parallel to the Intelligence Organization of IRGC,
was also killed along with many other top military security
and intelligence officials of the country,
top and high-profile ones indeed.
But still, we know that the scope of these area strikes
is not basically limited to that one.
We know that in the North, in the Southeast,
and Western areas of the capital,
attacks are reported, most notable of which
I can refer to the attack on the campus
of Sharif University of Technology,
which is known as MIT of Iran,
a huge amount of damage according to the footages
that we saw is visible there.
But we know that when it goes outside the capital,
there is a relatively long list of different cities,
including Karaj, Shiraz, Isfahan, Boucher, Bandar-e-Lenge,
in which six people, home in which at least five people,
Bahar-e-San in which at least 13 people,
and recently Shahyar in which at least nine people,
including women and children,
were killed. Iran is coming out with a very strong message
of retaliation in that regard.
And diplomatic engagement at this point
doesn't seem to be option on the table,
as we heard from the spokesperson
for the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Ismail Barahi,
in his press conference coming out to say
that the U.S. proposal at this point
seems to be illogical and extremely maximalist,
which is decreasing the hopes for diplomacy
on the one hand. And on the other hand,
we've got this statement from the spokesperson
for the joint military headquarters of Khatam-e-Olambiya,
who called for a stronger wave of retaliatory strikes.
He said that there are going to be quote-unquote
devastating and violent spread operations
if attacks on the civilian area,
civilian infrastructure of the country is repeated.
Tahir Asadi reporting from the Iranian capital Tehran,
commenting there or reporting, I should say,
on what Iran is saying, the latest on diplomatic efforts.
Tahir, thank you very much.
We take this conversation to Osama bin Javed,
who joins us with more on that.
You've been tracking this since day one.
Where is diplomacy going?
For the longest time, for weeks,
it seemed to be going nowhere.
And then Pakistan became the intermediary.
Where are we now?
Well, it is still the hub of all diplomatic activity,
just coming to the studio.
I was speaking to a source who's told me
that there's been frantic diplomacy
that is still taking place between all sides.
So Pakistan is in touch with all sides.
Pakistan has been taking messages from one side to the other.
And what Pakistan is trying to do
is bring them onto a point of convergence
where they can discuss everything that they diverge with.
This has not been fruitful so far
because of various reasons.
I've been told by a senior source
that they are hawks within the Iranian administration.
They are detractors in the US administration.
And then obviously the biggest issue of all is Israel
because nobody's been able to give guarantees
that the Israelis will be on board.
They will not carry out assassinations.
They will stop killing Iranian leaders.
And as you heard from the Iranian spokesperson,
saying that the talks cannot take place under threats.
And that is what Pakistanis are trying to build as well.
That there should be some sort of either a ceasefire,
a temporary opening of the Strait of Hormuz,
something that both sides can give to the other.
Saying that they have confidence in peace.
Right now what you're hearing on the public front at least
is that there is no trust.
There is no confidence.
There is no line that crosses with the other side.
And that is why they are finding it difficult
to bring them to the table.
Now the other thing that some sources told me
is the level of leadership that they're dealing with
in Iran because of such a degradation
of the communications network
as well as the top senior leaders being taken out.
Now the leaders who are there feel that they're emboldened
by the last six weeks of stiff resistance
that they've been able to put
against one of the world's largest
and most strongest militaries combined.
And they have to tell their people to prove their metal
that these are people who are in charge
who can give the enemy blows in the battlefield
and they will dictate how this war ends.
So the decision makers for Iran
are more hardline now than five weeks ago.
Is that a fair way to put it?
That is my understanding based on the sources
that we've been speaking to inside Pakistan
that because the Americans killed the supreme leader
the Americans and the Israelis assassinated
everybody even in the last 48 72 hours
in part of the negotiations
they've wiped out senior leaders of the military command
as well as targeting infrastructure, schools, hospitals.
So there's real sense of revenge
that they want to inflict on the enemy
because they feel that this is a war
that was brought upon them.
And that is why the stance have hardened
they have not softened.
The people who are now in the corridors of power
want to tell Israel and America
that they're nothing like any of the wars
that they've fought in the recent past.
I think that's a key piece of information
because the American logic from the start
has been hit Iran hard enough
and Iran will soften one way or another
either they will cave militarily or diplomatically
there will be a better deal to be made for the U.S.
after you've bombed them
and the information that you're getting
what your sensors are picking up is the opposite is happening.
There's an important word that you said
I think we need to spend time on this guarantees
this has been important for Iran
really ever since we started talking
about any diplomatic efforts
they want for this to move ahead
they want guarantees that they won't be attacked again right.
Absolutely not just that
but also guarantees that their leadership
is not going to be targeted guarantees
that they will have some sort of say
in how the Strait of Hormuz is run.
You're seeing the Iranians talk to the Omanis
based on that point
that it was going to be a joint Omani Iranian mechanism
which allows these ships to go through
but as you see all of this equation becoming
dire and bleak some sources in Pakistan
are hopeful that if there are takers
there are multiple avenues that they can take off ramps
the Iranians have allowed at least 15 ships
to pass through the Strait of Hormuz
in the last 24 hours
the Iranians have said that they are willing
to talk based on the terms that you know
they need reparations
and some indications are that
these reparations could come from the revenue
they're generating
They're still seeking reparations
and they could come from the Strait of Hormuz
and it is also possible
that the US president could say
that this could claim
this is the opening of the Strait of Hormuz
albeit partial
the Iranians could claim
that they have now taught less into the Americans
so there's still room for diplomacy
the big question is
how do you get Israel to give
that word that you mentioned guarantees
and then the sea of distrust
that exists between those sides
if there's anyone who can bridge it
Osama, I'm just going to go down the checklist
of things that where we are
right in this moment
as regards diplomacy
because I think what you're telling us
is going to feed into all the conversations
we'll have later in this program
you're telling us that right now
messages are still being passed
but it does sound
based on your reporting
like the US and Iran are no closer
to an agreement
than they were a few weeks ago
that's number one
is that is that fair
that is true
you're also saying
the Iranians are probably
more hardline at this point
more ensconced in their views
than they were even before the war
there is less room for concession
and the Iranians are still adamant
that they want reparations
and they're still keeping
I mean as far as the Strait of Hormuz is concerned
that's something you haven't really addressed
the Iranians are still going to keep
their control over the Strait of Hormuz
no movement on that
the Iranians want autonomy
over Strait of Hormuz
is what their demand is
they want to say
they will decide
who passes through the Strait of Hormuz
how and at what price
now that is that is a real concern
not just for the Americans and the Israelis
but for the region as well
because the bulk of the energy
that passes through
is essentially from these Gulf States
and if there is a toll
that they have to pay
that is going to raise
a lot of question marks
in Gulf States as well
so as we hear these
maximalist positions
one source told me
that diplomacy
is a delicate matter
which is being
discussed behind closed doors
there's still room for diplomacy
you will see more
stances being taken
in a hardline manner
from both sides
before something gives
and if this is
if the history of the U.S. president
is anything to go by
he's going to up the ante
to a point
where everybody is going to scamper
to find some sort
of ladder
that they can ask him to come down on
yeah that's the moment
we find ourselves in right now
because less than 48 hours from now
and as I say this
I'm fully aware the U.S. president
has extended his deadline several times
but still we're under this deadline
which is also a threat
to Balmiran's power plants
and Balmiran's bridges
thank you very much for this brief
on the diplomatic efforts
and where they stand
I think it's very important
Osama bin Javade
thank you
Israeli media is reporting
that at least four people have been killed
in an Iranian strike
on a building in the city of Haifa
earlier search and rescue teams
recovered the bodies
of two missing people
from under the rubble
the residential structure
partially collapsed
after the attack on Sunday
at least four others have been wounded
Al Jazeera's Nida Ibrahim
is following those developments in Israel
from Ramallah
in the occupied West Bank
Nida can you give us a picture
after five weeks of war
of how much damage Iran
has actually done in Israel
well there's several ways
you can assess the damage first
how these missiles continue
to disrupt life in Israel
and every time the home front
tries to ease restrictions
they are surprised with more attacks
from Iran
forcing them to change that estimate
also when you talk about the economy
it's taken a toll
when it comes to how much
disruption is happening
no one is allowed to go to work
if they don't have a close by shelter
there are limitations
on how many how many people
can gather in one place
but also you have the damage
you have the damage
the infrastructure
the homes
you have this idea
that the Israeli military censor
does not share everything
that is related to the damage
caused to strategic assets
so this is something we won't know
until a long long time
also you talk about these continued
barrages from Hezbollah
that threaten the northern Israeli communities
and you have the skepticism
amongst these communities
in the strategy that the government is employing
not just in the war with Hezbollah
but also in the war with Iran
remember the war goals
that Netanyahu has talked about
in the beginning
then he started backtracking on saying
that you cannot force Iranians to take
to the streets to revolt against their government
and that the existential threat of Iran
has been gone
but not necessarily
the continued barrages of rockets or missiles
these things do not sit very well with Israelis
remember
when you talk about Haifa
this is a very strategic important location
but today
it was a scene of chaos
because for 18 hours
the civil defense were looking
for those trapped under the rubble
and why did they do that very delicately
because there's a warhead in this missile
where the shrapnel have hit
that did not explode or detonate
and they were fearing
that as they're going through the rubble
trying to recover the four bodies
that they would face yet another disaster
they say it's by sheer luck
that this warhead did not detonate
cause more damage
so you were talking about the damage
that is continuing
that is showing no signs of abating
Nita Israelis had been broadly supportive
of this war that's being carried out
by their government and their military
but it's five weeks now
five weeks of this being under constant threats
going into bunkers
hearing the sirens
there are casualties
there are deaths as well
do you have a sense of
how much more patience
they're going to have with this war
well this patience is starting to be tested
as we've seen with multiple religious people
taking to the court
saying that they have the right to worship
and that that court allowed them
to gather in groups that are up to 100
of course the same does not apply
to Christians celebrating Easter
or Muslims trying to go
to a lot of Samoas compound
but you can sense that level
of trying to go back to normalcy
yes in the beginning of the war
we were reporting that the support for this attack
is around 80% amongst Israelis
but that is being changed
with more Israelis sensing
that the war goals are not being met
estimates of Hezbollah's capabilities and power
have been hugely underestimated
so they feel like there's not a real strategy
and they're wondering whether
what they're going through right now
is because of Netanyahu's political calculations
as he tries to win this war
tries to show
victory, but that's proving very, very difficult in light of the defiance of the Iranian regime,
in light of the continued barrages of missiles being targeted towards Israel.
So all of that is playing against Netanyahu's image, and in recent polls, these show that
should elections be held now, Netanyahu's coalition will take very little seats.
And basically he won't be able to create a majority 49, while the opposition's chances
are at 61, so they can form this government if elections were held now.
If that gives you an idea, it gives you an idea about Netanyahu's popularity and why he's
trying to expand the war to hit the power plants, to hit the energy infrastructure as a way
to try and boost his popularity and show that he indeed is succeeding.
That is not happening yet.
Yeah, it is important to understand the domestic political landscape for these decision makers
at times of war.
Nid Abraham reporting from Ramallah, thank you very much.
The threat of escalation in Iran has put the Gulf region directly in the line of fire.
Iran's army says that U.S. forces located on Kuwait's Boubian island were targeted with
drone attacks.
Health authorities in Kuwait also report that six people have been injured after debris
from a missile landed in a residential area.
Al Jazeera Zain Basravi is live for us in Dubai.
Zain, you're monitoring attacks across the Gulf.
They've been happening daily since the beginning of this war.
What are you seeing today?
Well, in addition to the attacks you mentioned that were significant, the UAE this morning
was responding to an attack targeting a telecoms company.
According to authorities in Fajera, they were responding to a drone launched from Iran,
they say, targeting a building belonging to the telecommunications company due, that's
according to state news.
Saudi Arabia destroyed two drones earlier today, intercepting those earlier this
morning.
The nationals were injured moderately from falling debris in Abu Dhabi on the RIN systems
company in Musaffa, and then the list goes on and on.
The UAE saying once again in the last few hours this morning, or the earlier hours
of this morning that was responding to incoming missile threats from Iran.
So we're into day 38 of the war, nearly 40 days of war, and the consistency of
these attacks continues to target nearly every GCC country, every day or every
other day as part of Iran's retaliatory strategy.
And Zayn, you've been covering this war since day one, tracking these developments that
are currently, as we speak, shaping the future of this region, military
developments, political, diplomatic, how would you describe the Gulf's position
right now?
Well, the position is exactly as it's been since day one of this war, smack
dab in the middle of it, politically, strategically, geographically, and
continuously trying to keep it from happening, trying to stop it from going on
much longer, and continuing to call for dialogue as the way to do it.
Now, let's look at some of the indicators of what's been happening on the
ground and what's actually being said just from the last 12 hours.
Iran, as we have discussed exhaustively at the beginning of this show, has
said it will not exchange opening the Strait of Hormuz for a temporary
ceasefire. What Iran wants is this to be the last time anything like this
happens in the region and to illustrate to the world that it is
the consequential power in the region. The U.S. might start stuff, but
Iran will end it if and when it wants. So in terms of being a consequential
force that must be spoken to and respected, whose ability to bring
force to bear on the region and whose political priorities must be
respected. That's really the indicator here. The IRGC has said it's
attacked Kuwait's Boubian Island, attacking satellite equipment,
munitions, drones, U.S. forces that relocated there from elsewhere. So
they're tracking these movements. It says that depots were hit that
housed ammunition, missile systems, high-mars, communication and
surveillance equipment in facilities, and American forces. So the IRGC
saying clearly that it is targeting forces and targets that it says are
located in the GCC countries and will continue to do so. Meanwhile,
what is the GCC saying? Well, Qatar's Prime Minister and Foreign
Minister, one of those vocal communicators from the GCC throughout
this war, continues to say that we must resolve this through
peaceful means, otherwise there will be serious repercussions with any
ongoing or any additional military escalation. He said the
necessity of stopping Iran's unjustified aggression remains, the
aggression against the GCC, that is still a priority for these
countries, but there must be a return to the negotiating table and we
must prioritize language of reason and wisdom to contain the crisis. It
must be contained. They realize that what has happened, you can't go
back. But going forward, there is a need to contain the crisis, with
all of the bluster coming from Washington about escalating with all
of the ongoing retaliation and militarized rhetoric coming from
Iran. The GCC stuck in the middle, physically and politically and
militarily, continuing to experience these retaliatory attacks
still says there has to be a return to dialogue. Now, how are
things going to go? The one thing that doesn't spin where
there's no narrative messaging is the market. Market forces are
practical market reactions are practical and looking at the
market. Let's look at the look at the big picture here, prices
of oil and everything are going up. And what we are seeing
countries that are reliant on the energy resources that
come from this region, they're doing two things. Many of them
are negotiating with Iran to secure passage through the
Strait of Hormuz. We've seen that in the case of a France
flagship, Japan, Greece. So there is some success that Iran
is enjoying in terms of getting people to negotiate with its
maritime authorities. What we are also seeing is countries
beginning to look for bypass ways around the Strait of
Hormuz. So that is a practical step that is being
taken. So perhaps the indicator is that people know that
there won't be a quick end to this conflict. And really, that
is an indicator that people will be pivoting to. But again, the
call for dialogue is coming loudest from the GCC countries.
Azan Basravi, reporting from Dubai. Azan, thank you very much.
I'm joined by Mohamed El-Masri, a Middle East
commentator, a professor also of media studies at the Doha
Institute for Graduate Studies. Mohamed, you heard Azan
there talking about Gulf countries that they've been in
this predicament for five weeks that they're in the
middle of this. And right up until the war started, I think
most Gulf countries would have argued that having US bases,
US military protection, this security umbrella around them
was an asset for them. But Iran has been with every
missile and drone making the case that actually know it's
a liability. And five weeks into this war, the GCC still
still caught in this dilemma that the thing that was
supposed to protect them is now the thing that's making them a
target.
Yeah, I mean, I think you articulated that really, really
well. I'm quite certain that there are a lot of questions
being asked right now in in the Gulf across the Gulf by
citizenries, but also among the among the leadership, to what
extent is this viable and worthwhile going forward? And
you know, to your to your point, the US bases and these
security agreements with the United States are supposed to
bring a measure of protection and safety and security to the
Gulf. But it seems as though they're having an opposite
effect, at least at least right now. And let's not forget
that Israel attacked Qatar in September. And so even at
that time, there were questions being raised
about why Israel, America's closest ally, would be able
to attack Qatar, despite the fact that there's this large
military base here in Qatar. So this is a very sensitive
issue. I don't think we can put all of the Gulf countries in
the same bucket. There are huge differences and
different disagreements, obviously, among them. And
even on this, you know, on the current war, you're
seeing kind of a separation, right? I do think you can
kind of put all man and Qatar in one sort of box, I
think, perhaps Bahrain and Kuwait and the UAE in another.
And it's, I think, important to note that Iran has
differentiated its strategy. Attacks on Qatar and all
man have decreased substantially. While attacks on Kuwait
and the UAE and Bahrain have, I think, increased over
the course of time. And I mentioned this in an earlier
interview, but there was verification by France 24.
So pause for a second, because the point that you make,
which is true, and we all know it living in these
countries, right? You have countries that have been
targeted more. The UAE, Kuwait recently, Bahrain have
been, have received more missiles and drones from
Iran than Oman and Qatar, which is not to say Oman and
Qatar haven't been attacked. They very much have
been. Qatar has had to stop its main money maker,
which is its production of LNG. So they've been
targeted, but we're talking about volumes of
missiles and drones, the amount of attacks,
right? Do you think that is maybe partially intended
to drive a wedge, or at least to incentivize and
disincentivize certain behavior within the GCC on
the part of Iran? In other words, Iran saying to
UAE, Bahrain, Kuwait, well, we feel you're closer to
the U.S. side, we're going to attack you more.
Saying to Qatar and Oman, we feel you're a more
conciliatory, you'll get attacked less.
I think that's very much a part of it. I do
think that that's part of the Iranian thinking,
the Iranian strategy here. It's also possible that
Iranian intelligence is telling them that there are
perhaps attacks coming from these countries. I'm
talking about Kuwait, the UAE and Bahrain. We've
heard some whispers. I was just mentioning
France 24. They were able to verify footage that
there were U.S. attacks against Iran launched
from Kuwait on March 24th and March 31st at
least, a number of attacks on Iran.
And so it may be that Iran is looking at sort of
the battlefield and saying, well, you, these
countries are actually launching attacks against
us. Now, I'm not confirming or denying whether
or not that's the case. What I'm saying is that
it's likely that Iranian intelligence believes
that. And if they believe that, it makes sense
then from their perspective that they would be
more aggressive toward those countries as
compared to the other countries.
International law here seems to be a complete
non-factor, right? And I think I'll strike
seems it is a complete non-factor. Like it
doesn't look like anyone is observing any
restraint or is, you know, saying we won't
target this or that because that would be
illegal. That could be a war crime. We're
not hearing that. In fact, we're hearing,
we're seeing civilian infrastructure and
civilian targets, whether it's universities,
hospitals, schools, bridges, desalination
plants, power plants, you name it. All of
that is being targeted, yes, in Iran by the
U.S. and Israel, but also in the Gulf and
across the Middle East by Iran.
International law, just there are no more
the boundaries that are supposed to be set
by international law no longer exist.
I think that's fair. I mean, the first
thing I'll say is that sadly, there are
often violations of international law and
international humanitarian law during
violent conflicts. But I do think that
we're seeing a different scale and
trajectory now. And I think that's
largely a byproduct of what we saw in
Gaza. I think that war crimes, atrocity
crimes, even the most serious crimes
were kind of normalized to a certain
extent. The world sort of just looked
on and shrugged as Israel committed
atrocity crimes in Gaza on live stream.
And they were getting support at the time
by the United States, right? Diplomatic
support and other forms of support,
military funding and so on and so forth.
And at times direct participation from
the United States. So that was a really,
I think sad moment for the international
order. And I'll just add that the U.S.
and Israel have spent years kind of
undermining the rules based order in
various ways. I actually wrote an article
about this is maybe a year, a year and a
half ago on Al Jazeera's website,
aljazeera.com, about how the U.S.
and Israel are undermining the rules
based order. So in some ways it's not
a surprise. And in this case, you have
the U.S. and Israel and to your point,
they have been going at civilian
infrastructure in Iran, as a matter
of policy. This is the Israeli MO.
I liked what Dr. Trita Parsi said
last week. He said that we're seeing
an Israelification of the war.
So essentially the Americans are
fighting like the Israelis.
It's not, you know, the other way around.
It's not that the Israelis are following
the lead of Big Brother, the United
States. It's it's the other way around
that the Americans are following the
Israelis. And yes, the Iranians are
retaliating in kind.
And some of their attacks would
certainly qualify as war crimes.
Mohamed Amasri, thank you very much
for joining us in the studio today.
Thanks. You're watching Al Jazeera
with continuing coverage of the war
between the U.S., Israel and Iran.
Our headlines this hour. Iran has
rejected a 15 point plan put forward
by the United States and says
negotiations are incompatible with
threats. The foreign ministry
spokesperson says Tehran is focused
on the security of its country.
Meanwhile, at least 34 people have
been killed in Iran and overnight
strikes by the U.S. and Israel.
Iran also says the head of the
IRGC's intelligence unit has been
killed. And Iran has continued to
send missiles at Israel.
According to Israeli media, at least
four people have been killed in the
northern city of Haifa.
There has also been extensive
damage in and around Tel Aviv.
Israel has carried out multiple
strikes across southern Lebanon and
the capital Beirut, causing widespread
damage and death. The latest
targeted Beirut southern suburbs.
This comes after the military
issued a forced evacuation threat
for residents from seven
neighborhoods. On Sunday,
multiple attacks on the southern
suburbs densely populated areas
killed at least five people.
And meanwhile, in southern Lebanon,
Israeli military attacks targeted
areas in the Nabache district.
At least four people were killed in
a drone strike that targeted a car
and in a separate attack in the
same area, one person was killed.
Seina Khuder is in Beirut with
the latest.
Well, yet again, the Israeli
military targeting Beirut southern
suburbs. They issued
an evacuation order before those
strikes come in.
But not all strikes are preceded
by a warning.
As I'm speaking to you now, Israeli
warplanes are flying over the
Lebanese capital.
They've been doing this for the
past few days.
Really, there's been an escalation
with Israeli strikes.
Relentless, not just in Beirut,
but in the south of the country,
in the east of the country yesterday,
a densely populated neighborhood
was hit, killing five people, among
them a child.
And the target appeared to be a
Hezbollah military commander.
But even though Israel calls these
targeted assassinations, pinpoint
strikes, it really doesn't matter
if civilians are killed
as well.
And there is growing concern that
the latest figure released by the
Lebanese health ministries, one
thousand four hundred and sixty one
killed among them.
Children and women, more than
four thousand wounded.
And that number has not been
updated because since the early
hours of the morning, there have
been repeated strikes.
Now, while the ministry doesn't say
or differentiate between combatants
and civilians, if we count the
number of women, children and
paramedics alone, that's roughly
twenty five percent of the casualty
toll.
The US president, Donald Trump, has
been giving Iran shifting deadlines
to reopen the Strait of Hormuz.
That is, as Iran insists that the
key waterway is not actually closed
and that only ships that belong
to its enemies are barred from
passage.
Trump issued his first ultimatum
on March 21st.
He threatened to bomb Iran's power
plants if the Strait was not
reopened within 48 hours.
He later extended that deadline by
five days, claiming that negotiations
were underway and that they were
going well.
Trump issued a new deadline on
March 26th.
He gave Iran 10 days
or until the evening of April 6th
to reopen the Strait.
And then Trump issued his latest
Hormuz threat on Sunday.
After vowing to bomb power
plants and bridges, if Tehran
does not comply, he posted
what appears to be a Tuesday,
8 p.m. Eastern time deadline
for a deal to be made or for the
Strait to be reopened.
Joining us to discuss this from
Tehran, Mustafa Khoshcheshem,
professor at the University of
Applied Sciences of Iran and in
Moria, Australia, Michael
Shubridge, director of Strategic
Analysis.
That's a Strategic Analysis
Australia, beg your pardon.
That's a defense and security
think tank. It's good to have
you both on the program.
Mustafa, what is
Iran's strategic thinking right
now? They are under this
deadline. We already know that
they've rejected the deadline.
We've said we don't negotiate
under threat.
But the fact is that there is a
credible threat from the U.S.
President to bomb Iran's
power plants and bridges, which
would be no matter how you look
at it, if he executes
that threat, which would be a
big deal for Iran.
So what's the strategic thinking
in Tehran?
Thanks for having me.
Well, there is no other way
but resistance and a
retaliation against the United
States and its allies.
Because if you just
go for negotiations, that
means right there because
Donald Trump has raised his 15
conditions in terms of
for the negotiations.
And we have the experience, two
experiences of being
bombed while negotiations
were underway.
According to one of the top
diplomats in the UK, Iran
in the last rounds
of meetings before the war
even raised a very
lucrative, very generous offer
that they shunned away.
Apparently, they are headed
for this part of the war.
It's phase six
infrastructure war, no
matter what we do.
So there is no other way
but resistance and retaliation
in order to end everything
once and for all.
That's the strategy.
Not only of these long
republic and the army
or armed forces, but also
millions of people that appear
in the streets every night
aren't demanding very
eloquently and loudly.
They say no negotiations.
We want to go on this
road to the end because
there is no other option
available.
Michael, the American logic
seems to be that they can
at some point reach
Iran's pain threshold
and exceed it.
In other words, they can hit them
hard enough so that Iran's logic
changes, right, which is the
logic that most of it just laid
out. Do you think that that is
still a possibility five
weeks into this war, for the U.S. and Israel to bomb Iran hard enough that Iran will somehow
change its behavior?
No, I don't, because I think the limits militarily of bombing are already being reached as far
as it goes to military targets and military combat capability, and the Iranians are showing
despite all of the destruction, and it's been widespread, they can still keep the
straight closed and attack the Gulf states and Israel, and their attacks seem to be quite
damaging. So there's a military limitation already here, and if the attacks are broadened
to civilian infrastructure, that doesn't look to me like it's going to prevent Iran doing
what it's able to do now.
Well that's a key question. Does it become harder for Iran to fight if it runs out
of power, or if the power plants are hit?
Well, a total national blackout would make it harder to operate everything in the country,
but that would also cause an enormous humanitarian disaster, which would be entirely disproportionate
to the military value, and therefore a war crime. But we've got to remember the Houthis
managed to keep fighting against the U.S. Navy and keep the Red Sea blocked, and
they were living in a ravaged Yemen that was destroyed by civil war under intense bombardment
from the Americans. So I think it's quite credible to see the Iranians being able to
keep fighting.
Mustafa, if we follow your logic, you're saying that Iranian decision makers feel
their best strategy, their best course of action is to resist and retaliate, right?
That's what you told us. Then what? What's the next step? You resist and you retaliate
to what end?
And, of course, keep the straight shot. That's the pillar of this strategy, actually. They
are not going to reopen the street or propose for any reason under any force that they might
exert over the pressure they exert on Iran. Until the United States agrees to Iran's
five terms that it has raised. One is paying war indemnity. It should be also condemned
globally. Also, there should be guarantees, objective guarantees, that war will not break
out in about a few months like the last time. And this means one of the meanings of this
objective guarantee means evacuation of the U.S. bases in the region. We cannot make
sure that war has ended and peace will be established permanently as long as the United
States is present around us in 30-something bases, 38 bases. So Iran has raised also the
condition that peace should be globally, regionally, in all fronts, for Lebanon, for Gaza, for Yemen,
for Iraq and for Iran. And also, there is another condition. So Iran will fight until it could
make the United States agree to these terms. And now Iran believes that it has the upper
hand that the U.S. ran out of their defense missiles. And after more Iranian missiles
are hitting Israel and U.S. bases in the region. So Iran now believes that it has the
upper hand. It's not just Iran, but many around the globe, including the United States
former officials, CIA chief former, also the Secretary of State of the United States
in Britain and everywhere. They now believe that Iran has the upper hand. That's why
Donald Trump's gun creates a warning to go forward with respect to war. I think they're
helpless.
Michael, Mustafa has reminded us of what is essentially Iran's list of demands. And adding
one that I hadn't heard previously in terms of security guarantees, what that could look
like for Iran. Because Iran has been saying for us to end this conflict, we need to
have the guarantee we won't be attacked again. So Mustafa was detailing that what
that could be from Iran's point of view is that the U.S. simply evacuate, pack up and
leave in some of its bases around the region. It's very difficult to imagine the U.S.
ever doing that, Michael. What's your take on that?
Exactly. Look, I think Mustafa is articulating what he thinks is the Iranian
government's set of demands. He's probably going a bit further than what we've
actually heard through official channels. But really, the Iranian plan is as unacceptable
to the Israelis and the Americans as the American 15-point plan is to the Iranians.
This is the value of the one thread of hope here, which is the Pakistani plan,
because it has the advantage when Americans look at it of not being the
Iranian demands, and when the Iranians look at it of not being the American and
Israeli demands. So the hope here is that Donald Trump can somehow convince
himself that the Pakistani plan is a victory for him, and also that the
Iranian government can convince themselves that the Pakistani plan has
enough victory for them. So really, what we're hearing from Mustafa is the
intractable demands of Iran, and what we're hearing from Donald Trump are the
intractable demands of America. That's why the Pakistani third path is so
important. Michael, remind us, when you say the Pakistani plan, do you mean the
proposal that was put forward by both Pakistan and China jointly? Is that
what you're referring to? No, I'm talking to the latest plan that's
being reported throughout that's like Reuters at the moment.
Okay, so tell us what you mean then, because I'm not sure what you're referring
to specifically. So what I've been reading just this evening is the
Pakistanis are providing a proposal to both the US and Iran that's a two
phase plan that starts with an immediate ceasefire that lasts for 45 days,
and during that ceasefire, a broader agreement, a broader peace agreement
is worked out. And its starting point is not the American 15 point plan and
not the Iranian plan that Mustafa has been describing. Okay, I don't have
that reporting as of this moment or it's not reporting that Al Jazeera has been
able to confirm. Mustafa, can I get you to Reuters report? Right, yes, but
we're very careful, especially in this moment when we're hearing so many
things and not everything can be stood up, not everything gets confirmed in
the end. So we're very careful at Al Jazeera to try and bring our viewers
only what we've been able to confirm. But in light of what you've just said,
Mustafa, what would be your reaction to that? So Michael's laying out this
idea that... Sorry, go ahead, go ahead. As far as I know, that's not
palatable to Iran. I mean this 45 days ceasefire is going to be rejected
because this includes easy the Street of Hormuz and Iran knows its nuclear
bomb is the Street of Hormuz and it should keep it shut. As soon as two to
three weeks from now, there will be economic crisis badly felt across the
globe if this trade is kept shut. And Iran knows that it now has the
upper hand. If it continues the same way, maybe in about two to three weeks, it
will be possible for Tehran to meet some of its demands. But if it goes along
with this 45 days, then the Americans and Israelis will reinvigorate
and renew attacks and there is no peace possible. With regard to the
objective guarantees for my colleague, I need to say that it's not my
understanding. Objective guarantees have been interpreted in eight, nine
subcategories. One of the main one that has been ordered by the Iranian
supreme leader is a evacuation of the U.S. from the region. Another one is
keeping this trade shut for quite a long time. So these are just two
of the meanings of the objective guarantees. Street of Hormuz is Iran's
trickier mechanism like the one that was in the way of working in the
interests of the United States and Europeans. Now Iran is thinking of
keeping this trade and the parliament has approved a new regime
protocols actually for commuting for the transit of ships through the
Street of Hormuz after the war and after the war rules end.
And there's been a meeting just yesterday between Iran and Oman where
they were starting to have preliminary conversations about how they
might be able to essentially administer and manage passage through
the Strait of Hormuz. Gentlemen, I'm going to have to run. Thank you
very much to both of you for your analysis and your insights this
hour. And thank you for joining us on Al Jazeera, Mustafa HaShashem
and Michael Shubridge. Thank you.
Nuclear energy provides just nine percent of the world's electricity
and that is according to the most recent International Energy
Agency figures from 2023. But the industry may be on the upswing
as countries look for clean and consistent supplies in the midst
of geopolitical upheaval. Even smaller countries with no history
of nuclear energy such as Greece are reassessing as
John Seropoulos reports from Athens.
This is the closest Greece ever came to nuclear power.
A small research reactor on the outskirts of the capital
switched on in the 1960s. It was meant to be the foundation
of the country's nuclear age, but left wing opposition and
safety concerns led to the reactor being shut down.
Today an EU survey suggests only 13 percent of Greeks
support nuclear power. But wars in Ukraine and the Gulf
have driven up the cost of oil and gas and caused countries
that rely on energy imports to reassess.
I want to explore the possibility of whether nuclear,
especially the emerging nuclear technologies, could make sense for Greece.
Climate change caused by burning fossil fuels has also helped
rekindle the nuclear debate.
Like most EU members, Greece has increasingly shifted towards
renewable energy, both to decarbonise and to become less
dependent on imported fossil fuels. Last year it generated
more than half its power from solar, wind and hydroelectric
sources. But it needs baseload electricity when the sun
doesn't shine and the wind doesn't blow. And that currently comes
from gas, which is neither cheap nor secure.
Greece sits on a tectonic plate in the Aegean Sea and is prone
to earthquakes. Many here still remember the one in 1999
that killed dozens of people, just as they remember the
Chernobyl nuclear disaster in 1986.
I was a boy and I could see the terror on people's faces.
And when it used to come to the market, I saw that people
weren't eating anything. There was a huge problem.
But Greeks are also beginning to think more about the cost
of energy. I think it's possible, because in this way
we'll be able to stabilise our energy costs and bring them down.
But of course it won't happen overnight. It'll take time to
be of real benefit to the economy.
Buildings can now be insulated from earthquakes and the
nuclear industry is designing smaller and safer modular reactors.
They are created in modules that are fabricated somewhere
else and then you transport them to a location where you
can assemble them and operate them in a relatively,
let's say, faster time scales.
Greece is also trying to make an economic leap forward.
Two large data centres are under construction and Greece and
Saudi Arabia plan to build Europe's first undersea
data cable to the Middle East. Nuclear fission might be the
key to powering those dreams.
John Saropoulos Al Jazeera Athens
Taking a look at some of the day's other news now,
Israeli forces have shot and killed a UN employee in Gaza
and injured another.